. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
WELCOME TO THE JULY 14TH 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT MANDEL MEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MALE GUARD PRESENT SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL PRESENT SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WANG WANG
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE INDIGENOUS
STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR
TRADITIONS THE RAMAKRISHNA MATERIALS WE HAVE NEVER CEDED
LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
AGAIN BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES
OF THE RAMAKRISHNA ALONI COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING
THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD, INDIVISIBLE, WITH LIBERTY,
JUSTICE FOR ALL. ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I'D LIKE
TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT US OF TV TODAY THAT IS ESPECIALLY
KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE
. AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK,
LET'S GO TO OUR 2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER THE MAYOR'S APPEARANCE
BEFORE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS .
>> YES. THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 2 P.M. IS
THE APPEARANCE BY THE HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE TO DISCUSS
THE ELIGIBLE TOPICS SUBMITTED BY THE DISTRICT NINE SUPERVISOR
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. THE MAYOR MAY ADDRESS THE BOARD
INITIALLY FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES.
>> WELCOME, MR. MAYOR. DO YOU HAVE ANY OPENING
REMARKS? I DO.
GOOD AFTERNOON. BOARD PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT
AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
I WANT TO START BY THANKING EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU FOR
YOUR PARTNERSHIP OVER THE PAST 18 MONTHS.
DURING THAT TIME WE HAVE MADE OUR STREETS SAFER, IMPROVED HOW
WE SERVE RESIDENTS AND CREATED CONDITIONS WHERE FAMILIES,
BUSINESSES AND COMMUNITIES CAN THRIVE.
THE RESULTS FROM THE FIRST HALF OF THIS YEAR SHOW THAT OUR
APPROACH IS WORKING AND WE ARE BUILDING ON LAST YEAR'S
MOMENTUM. DURING THE FIRST SIX MONTHS OF
2026 OVERALL CRIME WAS DOWN 22% COMPARED TO THE SAME POINT
AND PERIOD LAST YEAR. BUILDING ON A NEARLY 30%
CITYWIDE DECLINE IN 2025, CAR BREAK INS FELL 42%.
CAR THEFTS DECLINED 26% AFTER DROPPING 44% IN 2025.
THIS YEAR TEN ENCAMPMENTS HAD FALLEN TO THEIR LOWEST LEVELS
ON RECORD AND ARE DOWN 15 3% SINCE WE TOOK OFFICE.
APRIL AND JUNE RECORDED THE FEWEST MONTHLY OVERDOSE DEATHS
SINCE THE CITY BEGAN TRACKING THEM IN 2020 AND PEOPLE ARE
RETURNING TO SAN FRANCISCO IN MAY.
>> MUNI WEEKEND RIDERSHIP SURPASSED PRE-PANDEMIC LEVELS
FOR THE FIRST TIME AS OF SFO RECORDED ITS BUSIEST MEMORIAL
DAY WEEKEND EVER AND HALF A MILLION MORE TOURISTS ARE
PROJECTED TO COME TO OUR CITY THIS YEAR THAN IN 2025.
OUR ECONOMIC RECOVERY IS GAINING MOMENTUM THROUGH PERMIT
S.F. THE CITY IS ISSUING A RECORD 86% OF PERMITS WITHIN 30
DAYS OR FEWER. OUR NEW DIGITAL PERMITTING
SYSTEM HAS PROCESSED OVER 1500 PERMITS IN ITS FIRST FIVE
MONTHS AND OFFICE LEASING REACHED ITS HIGHEST VOLUME
SINCE 2018 A PROMISING SIGN THAT BUSINESSES ARE CHOOSING TO
INVEST IN SAN FRANCISCO. WE STILL HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO
DO. I'M CONFIDENT THAT THE UPCOMING
BUDGET WILL BUILD ON THE PROGRESS WE'VE ALREADY MADE.
AMID FEDERAL CUTS WE ARE STRENGTHENING OUR SOCIAL SAFETY
NET SO SAN FRANCISCANS KNOW THEY CAN COUNT ON THIS CITY.
THE BUDGET MAINTAINS HEALTH CARE AND FOOD ASSISTANCE
INVESTS IN PREVENTING INDIVIDUALS AND FAMILIES FROM
FALLING INTO HOMELESSNESS AND PROTECTS CORE SERVICES THAT
KEEPS OUR STREETS SAFE AND CLEAN.
AND WE ARE ALSO ON TRACK TO CLOSE A $642 MILLION DEFICIT.
THIS BUDGET REFLECTS WHAT IS POSSIBLE WHEN WE WORK TOGETHER
. WE ARE PROTECTING THE SERVICES
THAT SAN FRANCISCANS DEPEND ON AND CONTINUE TO DRIVE A DURABLE
AND BROAD ECONOMIC RECOVERY. SAN FRANCISCANS ARE ALSO
HELPING MOVE OUR CITY FORWARD. THIS PAST SATURDAY
IN PARTNERSHIP WITH EACH OF YOUR OFFICES, WE LAUNCHED SAN
FRANCISCO'S INAUGURAL ONE CITY DAY MORE THAN 4000 SAN
FRANCISCANS VOLUNTEERED CLEAN PARKS PLANTED TREES, PAINTED
MURALS, PACKED FOOD AND WORKED SIDE BY SIDE TO IMPROVE THE
COMMUNITIES THEY CALL HOME. IT WAS A REMINDER THAT SAN
FRANCISCO IS STRONGEST WHEN PEOPLE COME TOGETHER TO SERVE
ONE ANOTHER. THAT IS THE SPIRIT I HOPE
CONTINUES TO GUIDE US AS WE CONTINUE THE WORK AHEAD.
I LOOK FORWARD TO PARTNERING WITH ALL OF YOU TO MAKE SURE
SAN FRANCISCO IS SAFER, CLEANER AND WHERE EVERY FAMILY
COMMUNITY MEMBER AND SMALL BUSINESS HAS THE OPPORTUNITY TO
THRIVE. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, MAYOR LURIE. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
TOPIC FOR DISTRICT NINE. >> YES, THE TOPICS SUBMITTED BY
THE DISTRICT NINE SUPERVISOR JACKIE FIELDER IS STRATEGIES
AND METRICS OF SUCCESS AT THE MISSION STREET BART PLAZAS.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER PLEASE ASK HER OPENING QUESTION.
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MAILMAN THANK YOU, MARY LARRY FOR BEING
HERE. >> MAYOR AS YOU KNOW, THE BART
PLAZAS HAVE BEEN A TOP PRIORITY FOR ME SINCE TAKING OFFICE.
I'M ENCOURAGED THAT THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT IS LEADING A NEW INTERDEPARTMENTAL EFFORT THAT
BRINGS MULTIPLE CITY DEPARTMENTS TOGETHER TO
COORDINATE STRATEGIES AND ADDRESS THE LONG STANDING
CHALLENGES THAT HAVE IMPACTED THE MISSION.
>> HOWEVER, I'M STILL GETTING COMPLAINTS FROM CONSTITUENTS
AND FROM SMALL BUSINESSES AND SEEING FOR MYSELF WITH MY
OWN EYES EVERYDAY PEOPLE SUFFERING ON THE STREET WITH
SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER WHO NEED TREATMENT.
PEOPLE VENDING BOTH WITH AND WITHOUT PERMITS CONTAIN
CHAOTIC AND UNPREDICTABLE ENFORCEMENT AND PERMITTING
SYSTEMS AND UNHOUSED PEOPLE WHO NEED HOUSING.
WHAT STRATEGIES AND METRICS OR BENCHMARKS DOES YOUR OFFICE USE
TO MEASURE THE SUCCESS OF THE NEW IWD LED 90 DAY EFFORT ON
MISSION STREET? AND ACCORDING TO THESE METRICS
ARE YOUR ADMINISTRATION'S INTERVENTIONS MAKING A
MEANINGFUL DIFFERENCE? >> SUPERVISOR THANK YOU.
I APPRECIATE IT AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR SHARED INTEREST
IN SHARING. OUR PUBLIC SPACES ARE SAFE
AND WELCOMING FOR ALL AND I WOULD AGREE WITH YOU IT IS NOT
CONTROVERSIAL TO SAY THAT THE CONDITIONS AT 16TH STREET
AND 24TH STREET BAR PLAZAS HAVE BEEN UNACCEPTABLE FOR FAR TOO
LONG. WE MUST DO BETTER FOR THE
RESIDENTS, COMMUNITY COMMUTERS ,WORKERS, FAMILIES
AND BUSINESSES WHO RELY ON THESE PLAZAS EVERY SINGLE DAY.
YOU AND I AGREE ON THAT AND OUR TEAM RECOGNIZE THAT RESTORING
THESE SPACES WILL TAKE SUSTAINED COORDINATED WORK.
WE BROUGHT TOGETHER CITY DEPARTMENTS AND OUTSIDE
PARTNERS FOR A 90 DAY MULTIAGENCY EFFORT TO IMPROVE
CONDITIONS IN THIS COMMUNITY AND LAY THE GROUNDWORK FOR
LASTING AND DURABLE PROGRESS. UNDER MY OFFICE AS YOU
MENTIONED AND YOGI, WE HAVE LAUNCHED A COORDINATED RESPONSE
THAT COMBINES AND COMBINE COMBINES ENFORCEMENT OUTREACH,
SUPPORTIVE SERVICES AND COMMUNITY ACTIVATION.
OUR GOALS ARE SIMPLE IMPROVE SAFETY, STOP ILLEGAL FENCING,
ELIMINATE OPEN AIR DRUG ACTIVITY, IMPROVE CONNECTIVE
CITY FOR TRANSIT RIDERS AND PROVIDE WELCOMING COMMUNITY
CENTERED PUBLIC SPACES ON THESE PLAZAS.
AND WE'RE NOT JUST INCREASING PRESENCE.
WE'RE GIVING EVERY DEPARTMENT A REAL TIME VISIBILITY INTO WHO
IS DEPLOYED, WHERE THEY ARE DEPLOYED AND WHAT ROLE THEY ARE
FULFILLING BY ALIGNING SCHEDULES AND OPERATIONS ACROSS
AGENCIES SO WE CAN REDUCE SERVICE GAPS AND ENSURE MORE
CONSISTENT COVERAGE THROUGHOUT THE DAY.
WE ARE ALSO STRENGTHENING DATA COLLECTION BY INTEGRATING
OBSERVATION ACROSS TEAMS SO WE CAN IDENTIFY WHAT'S WORKING,
MAKE ADJUSTMENTS AND GET MORE EFFECTIVE OVER TIME.
OVER THESE 90 DAYS WE WILL USE THAT INFORMATION TO EVALUATE
PROGRAMS, MAKE TARGETED IMPROVEMENTS AND BUILD A LONG
TERM STRATEGY THAT EXTENDS EXTENDS BEYOND THIS INITIAL
INTERVENTION. THESE PLAZAS BELONG TO THE
COMMUNITY AND OUR COMMITMENT TO ENSURE SAFETY, DIGNITY
AND ACCESSIBILITY FOR ALL THE RESIDENTS, COMMUNITIES
AND FAMILIES WHO SHOULD BE ABLE TO USE THESE SPACES
COMFORTABLY. >> SUPERVISOR.
THANK YOU MR. MAYOR. SUPERVISOR FIELDER YOU MAY NOW
ASK A FOLLOW UP QUESTION DIRECTLY RELATED TO THE OPENING
QUESTION. >> THANK YOU FOR THAT, MR.
MAYOR. CAN YOU ELUCIDATE MORE WHAT
METRICS OR BENCHMARKS YOUR OFFICE IS USING TO MEASURE
SUCCESS? >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR. OVER THE FIRST MONTHS OF OUR 90
OVER THE FIRST MONTH OF OUR 90 DAY COORDINATED EFFORT WE'RE
SEEING ENCOURAGING SIGNS THAT MULTIAGENCY APPROACH IS
STARTING TO MAKE A DIFFERENCE. WE'RE DOING MORE PROACTIVE
POLICING WHICH I KNOW YOU AND THE RESIDENTS COMMUNITY
HAVE ASKED FOR WRITTEN ROUTINE PATROL CHECKS ARE UP 56% AT
16TH STREET AND 36% AT 24TH STREET WITH MAJOR INCREASES
IN NARCOTICS ENFORCEMENT MOVING VIOLATIONS AND FELONY ARRESTS.
AT THE SAME TIME, MENTAL HEALTH AND HOMELESSNESS RELATED CALLS
ARE DECLINING ALONG WITH PROPERTY CRIME AROUND 24TH
STREET. WE'VE ALSO EXPANDED ENFORCEMENT
AGAINST ILLEGAL FENCING. WE'VE IMPROVED LIGHTING,
INSTALLED NEW CAMERAS AND DEPLOYED AMBASSADORS WHO
ARE HELPING PREVENT EMERGING ISSUES BEFORE THEY ESCALATE.
THANKS TO THE STATE LEGISLATION WE GOT PASSED LAST YEAR WE
PASSED WITH WITH THE SUPPORT OF THE VENDING GROUPS WE'VE ISSUED
300 WARNINGS AND STARTED ISSUING CITATIONS TO PREVENT
RESELLING OF STOLEN GOODS WHICH WE KNOW CAN BECOME DANGEROUS.
OUR CLEANLINESS STRONGER COORDINATION ACROSS STATE
DEPARTMENTS IS LEADING TO FASTER RESPONSES AND MORE
CONSISTENT MAINTENANCE. ENCAMPMENT REPORTS ARE DOWN 8%
AT 16TH STREET AND 30% AT 24TH STREET.
OUR DEDICATED MISSION STREET OUTREACH TEAM NOW UNDER THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH IS HELPING TO ADDRESS IMMEDIATE
NEEDS WHILE SPECIALIZED TEAM PROVIDES INTENSIVE SUPPORT FOR
RESIDENTS WITH COMPLEX BEHAVIORAL HEALTH AND MEDICAL
NEEDS TOGETHER ENFORCEMENT AND OUTREACH ARE WORKING HAND
IN HAND. NOW THESE ARE JUST EARLIER
RESULTS WHICH ARE PROMISING. WE KNOW AND I AGREE WITH YOU
SUPERVISOR THAT THE WORK IS FAR FROM FINISHED.
WE ARE JUST GETTING STARTED. AND CONDITIONS STILL GET WORSE
AT NIGHT WHEN RESOURCES ARE LIMITED AND NEARLY THREE
QUARTERS OF SERVICE OFFICE SERVICE OFFERS ARE STILL
DECLINED BY PEOPLE STRUGGLING ON OUR STREETS.
OUR WORK WILL NOT BE DONE UNTIL RESIDENTS WORKERS, MERCHANTS
AND FAMILIES FEEL SAFE AND ARE SAFE AND THE PLAZAS ARE ONCE
AGAIN PLACES WHERE COMMUNITY CAN GATHER.
I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING THIS WORK WITH YOU SUPERVISOR
AND THE COMMUNITY WITH URGENCY SEE ACCOUNTABILITY
AND SUSTAINED COLLABORATE. >> MR. MAYOR YOU MAY NOW ASK A
QUESTION TO SUPERVISOR FIELDER OR TO ANY OTHER SUPERVISOR
IN ATTENDANCE PERTAINING TO THE SAME TOPIC BUT NOT NECESSARILY
RELATED TO THE PREVIOUS QUESTION.
NO, I APPRECIATE IT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR THANK YOU ALL AND I'LL LET YOU GET DOWN TO
BUSINESS. >> THANK YOU FOR COMING TO
VISIT US, MR. MAYOR. ALL RIGHT.
>> LET'S GO. >> MADAM CLERK.
COMMUNICATIONS. >> MINUTES BEFORE
COMMUNICATIONS. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
AS THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO ATTEND THIS
MEETING IN PERSON IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER.
AND WHEN YOU ARE UNABLE TO BE HERE, THE PROCEEDING IS AIRING
LIVE ON S.F. GOP TV'S LOCAL CABLE CHANNEL WHERE LIVE
STREAMING AT S.F. GLOBE TV.ORG. AS SOME OF YOU MAY KNOW SB 707
NOW REQUIRES REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT AT THE FULL BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS MEETINGS. AS A REMINDER IT DOES NOT APPLY
TO COMMITTEE MEETINGS TODAY AT GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT.
WE WILL WELCOME REMOTE PUBLIC CALLERS.
OF COURSE WE WILL PRIORITIZE SIZE.
THOSE OF YOU WHO'VE JOINED US IN PERSON FIRST AND THEN WE
WILL TAKE THE REMOTE CALLERS. I WILL POINT OUT THAT THE BOARD
HAS AN APPROVED BOARD, A RULE OF ORDER TO PREPARE FOR
DISORDERLY CONDUCT DURING A REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT.
PUBLIC COMMENT MUST REMAIN GERMANE TO THE MATTERS WITHIN
THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION AND ANY
SELF-EXPRESSION THAT CONTAINS PERSONAL ATTACKS, HARASSMENT OR
DISCRIMINATORY REMARKS DIRECTED AT ANY CITY EMPLOYEE OR BOARD
MEMBER. ARE NOT WITHIN THE SCOPE
AND FAILURE TO IMPEDE GENTLY REDIRECT COMMENTS WOULD RESULT
IN THE FORFEITURE OF YOUR REMAINING TIME AND A TRANSITION
TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. REMEMBER TO ADDRESS YOUR
COMMENTS TO THE BOARD AS A WHOLE AND NOT TO INDIVIDUAL
MEMBERS. IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT
YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING YOU CAN SEND IT AN EMAIL TO
BOSS AT AS OF KORG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE ADDRESS YOUR
ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON. GOOD LITTLE PLACE CITY HALL
ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102.
AND IF YOU'D LIKE TO REQUEST A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A
FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITY ACT
OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S
OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING
(415) 554-5184. THANK YOU MEMBERS THANK YOU,
MR. PRESIDENT. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
NOW LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING MINUTES.
>> YES. APPROVAL OF THE JUNE 9TH, 2026
BOARD MEETING MINUTES. >> COLLEAGUES, CAN I HAVE A
MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY
SUPERVISOR CHEN AND SUPERVISOR SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED SUPERVISOR SAUDER SAUTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDEL
MAHAN I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EITHER ARE LEBANESE
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC
COMMENT AS PRESENTED AND WITH THAT'S LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT
AGENDA PLEASE CALL ITEMS TWO THROUGH FOUR TOGETHER ITEMS TWO
THROUGH FOUR ARE ON CONSENT. THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO
BE ROUTINE IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED
AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEMS TWO THROUGH FOUR SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR ONE WONG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I'M A SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISE HER FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I RANDLEMAN I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I THERE ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION
THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM FIVE ITEM FIVE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE OF ENVIRONMENT,
HEALTH, LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT PART PLANNING POLICE PUBLIC
WORKS SUBDIVISION TRANSPORTATION AND BUILDING
INSPECTION COMMISSION CODES TO MODIFY NUMEROUS REPORTING
REQUIREMENTS AND TO AFFIRM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT SEGMENT
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> I SEE MANY NAMES POPPING UP ON THE ROSTER I WOULD LIKE TO
SPEAK FIRST. I DO NOT BELIEVE IT IS
APPROPRIATE FOR ME TO SPEAK FIRST FROM THE DAIS SO I'M
GOING TO ASK SUPERVISOR WALDEN WHO WE WILL SPEAK LATER TO TAKE
THE DAIS WHILE I'M TALKING PRESIDENT MELLOW MAN ADVISOR
WALTON ADMONISHED ME NOT TO LOOK AT HIS NOTES.
>> COLLEAGUES I HAVE CIRCULATED AMENDED NOTES THAT I WOULD HOPE
WE WILL ADOPT TODAY AND THEN PASS THIS ORDINANCE ON FIRST
READING BY WAY OF BACKGROUND TO CATCH PEOPLE UP.
THIS ORDINANCE HAS BEEN A LONG TIME IN THE MAKING.
CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHIU HAD HEARD FROM MANY DEPARTMENTS
OVER TIME THAT THEY WERE FEELING BURDENED BY THE VOLUME
OF REPORTS THAT THEY WERE BEING ASKED TO PRODUCE THAT IN THEIR
MIND NOBODY WAS REVIEWING AND THAT WE HAD TO MAKE WORK
EXERCISE GOING ON THAT THEY WOULD LIKE THAT THEY WERE
HOPING SOMEONE WOULD PRUNE AND FOR MANY YEARS WELL FOR
YEARS SUPERVISOR OR CITY ATTORNEY CHIU HEARD THIS WASN'T
QUITE SURE WHAT TO DO WITH THAT.
>> THERE'S BEEN A LOT OF TALK ABOUT HOW AI HAS BEEN USED WITH
THIS ORDINANCE THE WAY I WAS USED WITH THIS ORDINANCE WAS
THAT A STANFORD A STANFORD LEARN LANGUAGE MODEL WAS
BROUGHT TO BEAR TO IDENTIFY ALL OF THESE REPORTS.
>> THE ORDINANCE WAS NOT WRITTEN BY THE I DID NOT DO THE
ANALYSIS OF WHETHER THESE REPORTS WERE WORTHWHILE OR NOT
WORTHWHILE. ALL THEY DID WAS PULL OUT ALL
THE REPORTING REQUIREMENTS THAT MIGHT HAVE BEEN PUT INTO OUR
VAST CODE OVER OVER TIME. THIS EXERCISE IDENTIFIED 15 540
REPORTS AND THEN THE REAL WORK FOR THE CITY ATTORNEYS AND THE
PEOPLE IN THE DEPARTMENTS BEGAN WHEREIN THEY LOOKED AT EACH OF
THESE REPORTS AND THEY TRIED TO FIGURE OUT WHETHER THEY WERE
VALUABLE, WHETHER SOMEONE OUT IN THE WORLD SEEMED TO BE
PAYING ATTENTION TO THESE REPORTS AND WANTING THESE
REPORTS OR WHETHER THEY WERE JUST TO MAKE WORK EXERCISE
BASED ON THAT THEY DECIDED TO LEAVE.
I THINK TWO THIRDS OF THE REPORTS ALONE SO ABOUT 380 OF
THE REPORTS THAT THEY IDENTIFIED ARE NOT BEING
TOUCHED. THE REST 140 SOME ODD REPORTS
THIS ORDINANCE WOULD ELIMINATE OR MODIFY THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE WAS ASKED TO PREPARE SOME TO MANY, MANY MONTHS AGO A
SMALLER DOCUMENT A NINE PAGE REPORT THAT WALKED THROUGH EACH
OF THE CHANGES AND GENERALLY SUMMARIZED IT SO PEOPLE COULD
KNOW AT LEAST WHAT MORE TO LOOK FOR IF THEY HAD CONCERNS.
>> SOME OF US TOOK ADVANTAGE OF THAT.
>> I DID SUPERVISOR CHEN DID, SUPERVISOR CHERYL DID I BELIEVE
OTHERS MAY HAVE THIS ORDINANCE WAS HEARD AT PLANNING
COMMISSION OF THE BUILDING INSPECTION COMMISSION AND ALSO
AT OUR OWN GAO. I DO WANT TO THANK CHAIR CHERYL
FOR THE WORK THAT HE AND PARTICULARLY HIS STAFF I
THINK LORENZO WAS WORKING ON THIS DID IN SORTING THROUGH
SOME OF THE CONCERNS THAT THEY HEARD AND THAT WAS THE MEASURE
THAT WAS FORWARDED TO THE FULL BOARD.
NOW AS WE RECALL THERE WAS SOME DISCUSSION ABOUT THIS TWO WEEKS
AGO A DIFFERENT CONCERNS WERE EXPRESSED AND WITHIN THE WEEK
BEFORE BETWEEN THIS GOING TO GAO AND COMING TO THE FULL
BOARD, WE DID HEAR FROM THE LBB, THE SMALL BUSINESS
COMMUNITY WITH CONCERNS ABOUT THIS ORDINANCE ABOUT OTHER
PIECES OF LEGISLATION. AND SO AT THAT POINT I ASKED
AND THE BOARD DECIDED TO CONTINUE THIS ITEM FOR TWO
WEEKS TO ADDRESS THEIR CONCERNS TO ADDRESS OTHER QUESTIONS
PEOPLE MIGHT HAVE ABOUT THE ORDINANCE THROUGH CONVERSATIONS
WITH THE LBB FOLKS I THINK THERE MAY WELL BE WORK TO BE
DONE IN CHANGING THE REPORTING THAT IMPACT THAT THAT THEY ARE
CONCERNED ABOUT BUT I DON'T THINK WE CAN HAVE THOSE
CONVERSATIONS ON THE SAME TIMELINE AS THE REST OF THIS.
AND SO AMONG THE THE AMENDMENTS THAT YOU HAVE IN FRONT OF YOU
ARE AMENDMENTS THAT BASICALLY TAKE OUT ANY OF THE ITEMS THAT
THE THAT THAT THOSE LETTERS FROM THE OBJECT COMMUNITY
IDENTIFIED AS THINGS THEY WERE CONCERNED ABOUT.
WE ALSO HEARD FROM THE DEPARTMENT ON THE STATUS OF
WOMEN WITH LOTS OF QUESTIONS IN THE END I THINK WE ADDRESSED
MOST OF THEIR QUESTIONS BUT THERE ARE TWO CHANGES THAT WE
ARE PROPOSING THAT WOULD OFFER .
ON PAGES 285 ON PAGE 25, LINES FIVE AND SIX RESTORE THE
DEPARTMENT ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN AS A RECIPIENT OF A
QUARTERLY REPORT THAT THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT
AND AND BY THE SAME COMPLETE DEPARTMENT AND THE DIA TO
VARIOUS APARTMENTS REGARDING DOMESTIC VIOLENCE DATA AND THEY
ALSO ASKED AND WE HAVE INCLUDED IN THESE AMENDMENTS A
RESTORATION OF THE ONGOING REPORTING REQUIREMENT FOR DSW
TO REPORT ON THE CITY'S POLICY PROMOTING REPRESENTATION OF
WOMEN ON CITY. I THINK IT'S ON CITY
COMMISSIONS AND THEN ON PAGE 18 THERE'S A RESTORATION OF THE
SEXUAL HARASSMENT REPORT BY THAT THAT'S PREPARED BY THE
DEPARTMENT OF HUMAN RESOURCES ALTHOUGH RATHER THAN HAVING IT
BE A QUARTERLY REPORT AS CURRENTLY IT WOULD BE
SEMIANNUAL. SO THOSE ARE THREE ADDITIONAL
CHANGES THAT HAVE COME UP IN THE LAST TWO WEEKS.
AND THEN THERE WERE THERE ARE A COUPLE OF CLEANUP ITEMS BECAUSE
IT'S BEEN AROUND AS I SAID FOR A YEAR.
THE CITY ATTORNEY'S HAVE PROVIDED SOME CLEAN UP PAGE
THREE 358 LINE 12 UPDATES THE TEXT OF THAT SECTION TO REFLECT
THE CURRENT CODE WHICH IS DIFFERENT FROM WHEN THEY FIRST
INTRODUCED IT PAGE 308 LINE 22 WE'RE REMOVING A SECTION
RELATED TO THE EQUAL PAY REPORTS THAT'S ALREADY BEEN
ELIMINATED AND THEN ON PAGE 282 LINES 14 AND 17 WE'RE PROPOSING
TO CHANGE LANGUAGE TO SEMI ANNUAL INSTEAD OF BI ANNUAL FOR
CONSISTENCY AND CLARITY. >> IN ADDITION TO THOSE CHANGES
WE'VE ALSO HAD I HOPE FRUITFUL CONVERSATIONS BETWEEN OUR
CLERK'S OFFICE AND OUR CITY ATTORNEY AND OUR CITY ATTORNEY
TOOK IT UPON HIMSELF TO DO ANOTHER REVIEW OF THE
LEGISLATION AND BASED ON THAT TO PROVIDE SOME CLARIFICATION
INTO THE TITLE WHICH I'M GRATEFUL FOR AND THEN I BELIEVE
THEY HAVE THEY'VE UPDATED THE DIGEST THAT WILL BE THAT WILL
ACCOMPANY THIS IN THE IN THE OFFICIAL RECORD.
SO THOSE ARE THE CHANGES WE HAVE.
WE ARE PROPOSING FOR THE BOARD'S CONSIDERATION.
>> I, I KNOW THIS IS LONG IT'S A LONG MEASURE.
IT'S NOT THE ONLY LONG MEASURE THAT THIS BOARD HAS CONSIDERED.
WE CONSIDER ALONG ALONG MEASURE IN THE FORM OF OUR BUDGET EVERY
SINGLE YEAR. I DO THINK THERE IS A QUESTION
ABOUT AS THESE REQUIREMENTS THAT THAT GROW UP OVER TIME DO
ACCRUE WHAT THE MOST EXPEDITIOUS AND REASONABLE WAY
TO PRUNE OUR CODE IS AND I HOPE THIS IS NOT THE END BECAUSE I
DO THINK OUR CODE NEEDS MUCH MORE PRUNING BUT I'M NOT
PLANNING ON INTRODUCING ANOTHER MAJOR ONE OF THESE IN MY LAST
SIX MONTHS. I DO THINK IT'S WORTH DOING.
I THINK THERE ARE HARDWORKING PEOPLE IN EVERY SINGLE
DEPARTMENT IN THIS CITY WHO ARE QUESTION THE VALUE OF THEIR
WORK WHEN THEY KNOW THAT THEY'RE PREPARING A REPORT
AND SPENDING MANY HOURS ON IT THAT NO ONE WILL ACTUALLY USE
AND WOULD LIKE TO BE DOING SOMETHING OF MORE IMMEDIATE
VALUE TO THE PUBLIC. I THINK THOSE ARE MY COMMENTS.
I AND I WILL NOW GO BACK UP AND TAKE MY CHAIR AND ALLOW
OTHERS WHO MAY FEEL DIFFERENTLY TO SPEAK.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT MELBOURNE SUPERVISOR FIELDER
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN
FOR HEARING COMMUNITY OUT ON SOME OF THESE REPORTS AND FOR
ALLOWING US MORE TIME TO LOOK INTO THIS LEGISLATION.
I HAD SEVERAL CONCERNS WITH REPORTS BEING REMOVED OR PARED
DOWN INCLUDING REPORTS RAISED BY THE DEPARTMENT ON THE STATUS
OF WOMEN WHICH I'M GLAD TO SEE WHERE WE CONSIDERED AND I'M
THANKFUL TO YOU MAYBE SKELLY AND PRESIDENT MIDDLETON'S
OFFICE FOR GOING OVER OTHER CONCERNS WITH MY STAFF.
JENNIFER FERRIGNO I SUPPORT THE VAST MAJORITY OF CODE CLEANUP
IN THIS ORDINANCE REMOVING OUTDATED AND OBSOLETE REPORTING
REQUIREMENTS AND PARING DOWN THE FREQUENCY OF SOME REPORTING
FROM SOME DEPARTMENTS. HOWEVER, I HAVE ONE MAJOR
OUTSTANDING CONCERN WITH THIS LEGISLATION AND THAT IS THE
PARING DOWN OF THE CONTROLLERS ANNUAL SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY
AUDIT FROM ONCE A YEAR TO ONCE EVERY FIVE YEARS.
SECTION 28.20 REQUIRES THE COMPTROLLER TO AUDIT ANNUALLY
THE USE OF SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY BY DEPARTMENTS
AND REQUIRES THE AUDIT TO INCLUDE A REVIEW OF WHETHER A
DEPARTMENT HAS OPERATED AND IS OPERATING IN COMPLIANCE WITH AN
APPROVED SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICY ORDINANCE HAS
COMPLETED AN ANNUAL SURVEILLANCE REPORT AND SUCH
OTHER INFORMATION AS THE COMPTROLLER DETERMINES HELPFUL
TO ASSESS THAT SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICY AT A TIME
WHEN PEOPLE ARE INCREASINGLY CONCERNED ABOUT DATA PRIVACY
AND HOW THEY ARE BEING MONITORED.
I THINK THE FREQUENCY OF THIS REPORT IS CRUCIAL TO HONORING
CIVIL LIBERTIES AND THE INTENT OF OUR CITY'S STRONG
SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICY .
I'M DISAPPOINTED THAT THIS REPORTING REQUIREMENT WILL BE
PARED DOWN FROM ONE YEAR ALL THE WAY TO FIVE YEARS.
IT IS IT IS A SIGNIFICANT UNDERTAKING IN THE
COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE TO CONDUCT THIS AUDIT.
BUT I THINK THIS IS A PRIORITY FOR SAN FRANCISCANS SO MUCH SO
THAT I WILL NOT BE ABLE TO SUPPORT THIS ITEM.
>> SUPERVISOR ONE THANK YOU, PRESIDENT AMANDA MINUTE I JUST
WANT TO SAY THAT I THINK IT'S GREAT THAT THE CITY ATTORNEY,
CITY DEPARTMENTS AND BORDER SUPERVISORS AND EVERYONE WITH
THE PUBLIC HAD A CHANCE TO WEIGH IN ON THIS DENSE DOCUMENT
WHICH AFFECTS EVERYONE THESE REPORTING REQUIREMENTS ARE
IN PLACE FOR A REASON. SO I THINK, YOU KNOW, YOU
SHOULD BE PROUD TO MAKE SO MANY CHANGES WITHOUT ANYONE KNOWING
WHAT'S HAPPENING. THIS REALLY SHOULD HAVE BEEN
SEPARATED AND TAKEN UP AFTER RECESS WITH THE PUBLIC PROCESS.
THERE IS A LOT OF INFORMATION IN HERE.
>> THERE ARE A LOT OF CHANGES IN HERE.
THIS DOCUMENT IS VERY DENSE AND EVERYBODY YOU DESCRIBE THAT
PARTICIPATED IN THIS CONVERSATION.
IT DOES NOT INCLUDE THE PUBLIC WHICH WILL BE AFFECTED BY THIS
LEGISLATION. >> I THINK THAT IT IS AWFULLY
PECULIAR THAT WE ARE HANDLING A PIECE OF LEGISLATION IN THIS
MANNER WITH NO PUBLIC PROCESS WITH SO MANY CHANGES.
I JUST DON'T UNDERSTAND WHAT WHERE WE'RE GOING WITH THE
DIRECTION WE'RE TRYING TO GO WITH CITY GOVERNMENT BECAUSE TO
SUPPORT THIS IS SAYING THAT WE DON'T GIVE A ABOUT PUBLIC
VOICE AND I'VE NEVER SEEN US DO POLICY LIKE THIS AND MY ALMOST
EIGHT YEARS ON THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WHERE WE HAVE NO
PUBLIC CONVERSATION, NO PUBLIC COMMENT, NO PUBLIC WAY AND I'VE
JUST NEVER SEEN THIS I I'M SURPRISED THIS IS EVEN IN FRONT
OF US. SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANDELL MAN I JUST WANT TO START MY COMMENTS BY
THANKING YOU AND YOUR STAFF FOR A TREMENDOUS AMOUNT OF WORK
AND ALSO CITY ATTORNEY TOO AND HIS STAFF FOR THE MANY
HOURS THEY SPEND ON THE LEGISLATION AND PARTNERS WHO
HAVE DONE THIS. AS I PREVIOUSLY STATED, I DO
BELIEVE THAT THE EXERCISE TO EVALUATE AND ASSESS THE CODE
AND CLEAN IT UP IS AN ACT OF GOOD GOVERNMENT HYGIENE.
>> I DON'T KNOW IF THAT'S THAT'S A PHRASE OUR CODE HAS
BECOME CONVOLUTED OVER TIME AND IT REQUIRES REGULAR CLEANUP
OF OBSOLETE SECTIONS REDUNDANCIES, PURGING OF
SECTIONS THAT ARE NO LONGER USEFUL.
AND I WANT TO BE CLEAR THAT I DO THINK THAT THAT'S AN
APPROPRIATE USE OF I DON'T THINK THERE'S ANYTHING WRONG
WITH THAT. HOWEVER, THERE ARE POLICY
IMPLICATIONS FOR STREAMLINING AND GETTING RID OF REPORTS THAT
I THINK ARE POLICY DECISIONS NOT JUST CLEAN UP DECISIONS.
>> AND I DO APPRECIATE THE AMENDMENTS THAT YOU'RE PUTTING
FORWARD TODAY. THANK YOU FOR INCLUDING A
COUPLE OF MINE. I JUST WANT TO CAUTION US THAT
THIS WEEK OF ALL WEEKS I'VE BEEN READING THE PAPER WHAT'S
GOING ON IN SAN FRANCISCO THE LAST COUPLE OF WEEKS WE WERE
GOING TO GET RID OF THE REPORT ON SEXUAL HARASSMENT THAT'S
WHAT WE WERE GOING TO DO BEFORE THE AMENDMENTS BEFORE YOU
TODAY. AND THEY WERE CAUGHT BY
SOMEBODY AT THE DEPARTMENT OF THE STATUS OF WOMEN WHICH IS
WHY THEY'RE BEFORE US TODAY. I VERY MUCH CARE ABOUT THIS
ISSUE BUT THERE'S LOTS OF OTHER ISSUES AND I'M NOT WATCHING OUT
FOR IN THE 350 SOME PAGES YOU KNOW I WAS ABLE TO FIND A FEW
THINGS BUT I DON'T KNOW THAT I WAS ABLE TO DO EVERYTHING.
SO I WILL BE VOTING AGAINST THIS LEGISLATION.
BUT LET ME BE CLEAR ON WHY IT IS NOT BECAUSE I DON'T THINK
THAT YOU KNOW, I WELL, THAT'S THAT'S NOT REASON I THINK IT'S
UP TO ME IT'S ABOUT THE PROCESS.
>> SO YOU KNOW, WE EACH HAVE VERY DISTINCT JOBS IN THE
CHECKS AND BALANCES OF POWERS OF OUR GOVERNMENT.
I'M VERY PROUD OF OUR DEMOCRACY AND PARTICULARLY PROUD OF THE
DEMOCRACY THAT WE HAVE IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO, THE CITY ATTORNEY'S ROLE AND THE ELECTED CITY
ATTORNEY THAT WE HAVE HAS A RESPONSIBILITY TO KEEP THE CITY
FROM LEGAL HARM TO MAKE SURE THAT OUR CODES ARE EFFICIENT
IN THEIR CLEAR TO MINIMIZE THE HARM TO SAN FRANCISCO, THE RISK
OF LEGAL ENTANGLEMENT AND ALSO, YOU KNOW, HELP MAKE THINGS MORE
EFFICIENT AND I THINK THAT THAT'S GREAT.
OUR CITY CLERK ALSO HAS, YOU KNOW, A RESPONSIBILITY TO MAKE
SURE THAT THE RECORDS OF OUR ACTIVITIES ARE SEARCHABLE
IN THAT THEY'RE TRANSPARENT AND ACCESSIBLE TO THE PUBLIC
AND THAT REQUIRES A LOT OF ORGANIZATION AND BEING ABLE TO
DO THINGS A CERTAIN WAY OUR RESPONSIBILITY AS A PEOPLE'S
BRANCH, AS A LEGISLATIVE BRANCH IS TO MAKE SURE THAT THE PEOPLE
HAVE ACCESS TO OUR ACTIVITIES IN OUR FULL PARTICIPANTS IN OUR
DISCUSSION AND WE HAVE DEVELOPED THESE PROCESSES OVER
TIME TO MAKE SURE THAT THAT HAPPENS TO MY COLLEAGUE
WALTON'S COMMENTS AND WHILE WE DID HAVE A COUPLE OF HEARINGS
AT COMMITTEE I DON'T THINK THAT THEY THE THE PROCESS WAS
SUFFICIENT TO ENCOMPASS THE ENTIRE BREADTH OF WHAT'S
HAPPENING HERE. AND YES, MOST OF IT IS AS MY
COLLEAGUE FIELDER STATED, ROUTINE STAFF STUFF THAT'S
UNCLEAR REDUNDANCIES, THINGS THAT DON'T EXIST ANYMORE BUT
SOME OF THEM ARE ACTUALLY LEGIT POLICY DISCUSSIONS BUT IT'S ALL
MIXED IN TOGETHER IN ONE VEHICLE AND I DON'T THINK THAT
WE HAVE HAD SUFFICIENT TIME BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY I DON'T THINK
OUR PROCESSES ARE ADEQUATE TO BE ABLE TO HANDLE SOMETHING
LIKE THIS. SO I WILL BE VOTING AGAINST IT.
BUT I ALSO WANT TO MAKE A POINT IN PUBLIC TO REQUEST OUT TO OUR
CITY ATTORNEY PLEASE DO NOT EVER DO THIS AGAIN.
THIS WAY IF WE'RE EVER GOING TO DO THIS AGAIN, PLEASE HAVE THE
COURTESY TO US TO OUR INTEGRITY AS A LEGISLATIVE BRANCH, AS A
PEOPLE BRANCH TO BREAK IT UP BY SUBJECT BY ACTIVITY WHERE IF
IT'S JUST CLEANUP VERSUS REPORTING, YOU KNOW, THERE ARE
MANY DIFFERENT WAYS TO DO THIS. BUT YOU KNOW, I DON'T THINK
THAT THIS WAS THE RIGHT WAY AND I JUST YOU KNOW, WANT TO
REITERATE THIS IS NOT ABOUT WELL, SOME OF IT IS THE CONTENT
BUT OVERALL THE CONTENT I THINK IS OKAY.
THE REPORTING I THINK NEEDS WAY MORE WORK AND I THINK FOR ME
IT'S ABOUT THE PROCESS AND THE INTEGRITY OF US AS A
LEGISLATIVE BRANCH AND OUR ROLE IN PROVIDING TRANSPARENT
COMMUNICATION ACCESS AND INPUT FROM THE PUBLIC THAT I'M JUST
NOT COMFORTABLE WITH. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU, BILL.
>> PRESIDENT COLLEAGUES WHEN I FIRST REVIEWED THIS LEGISLATION
I WAS CONCERNED THAT ELIMINATES SEVERAL VITAL REPORTING
REQUIREMENTS THAT ARE FOUNDATIONAL TO INFORM
POLICYMAKING ON LAND USE AND HOUSING.
MANY OF THIS REPORTING REQUIREMENTS WERE CRAFTED WITH
INPUT FROM COMMUNITIES AND COMMUNITY BASED IT
ORGANIZATION THAT RELY ON THIS INFORMATION TO PROTECT TENANTS
AND EXPAND AFFORDABLE HOUSING. SOME EXAMPLES INCLUDE
INDICATORS TO BETTER UNDERSTAND HOW PROGRESS TOURISTS HAVE
PROGRESS TOWARDS MEETING AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
>> ITS IMPACTED BY THE LOSS OF RENT CONTROL UNITS THROUGH ONE
YEAR OF NO FAULT EVICTIONS. ITS CHAIR A JOB HOUSING
ANALYSIS TO BETTER DOCUMENT HOW HOUSING PRODUCED IT MATCHES THE
WAGE LEVEL OF NEW WORKERS SO THAT WE MAY TRACK OUT OUR
ABILITY TO HOUSE OUR LOCAL WORKFORCE REPORTS
AND INDICATORS RELATED TO TENANT IMPACTS AROUND SHORT
TERM RENTALS, ACCESSORY DWELLING UNITS AND FOURPLEX
AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING PRODUCTIONS AND PRESERVATION
FUND THAT HAS SUPPORTED THE DEVELOPMENT OF AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AND THE PRESERVATION OF EXISTING RENT CONTROLLED UNITS.
IT IS CONCERNING TO ME THAT THESE REPORTING REQUIREMENTS
WERE ON THE CHOPPING BLOCK IN THE FIRST PLACE.
>> THIS IS NOT SIMPLE CLEAN UP OF OBSOLETE REQUIREMENTS BUT
REAL POLICY TRADEOFFS AROUND REPORTS AND INDICATORS THAT
REMAIN VITAL NOW THAN EVER GIVEN A CITY'S BEST WHAT
DEPENDING UPON THE QUANTITY AND MANY DISPLACEMENT
PRESSURES. AND I WANT TO REALLY APPRECIATE
SUPERVISOR CHERYL AND YOUR STAFF AND PRESENT MANAGEMENT
AND YOUR STAFF FOR WORKING COLLABORATIVELY WITH MY OFFICE
TO CRAFT AMENDMENTS TO RESTORE THIS REQUIREMENT.
AND I'LL BE SUPPORTING THIS LEGISLATION.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG I WANT TO THANK
PRESIDENT MATLIN AND CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHIU FOR WORKING
ON THIS LARGE PIECE OF LEGISLATION IDENTIFYING THE
THINGS THAT NEED CODE CLEANUP IN OUR CITY CITY CODE.
IT'S VERY IT'S A VERY LARGE CODE AND THERE'S SO MANY
REQUIREMENTS THAT CITY DEPARTMENTS HAVE ALSO WANT TO
THINK AND ACKNOWLEDGE THE GROUPS, SUPERVISORS AND FOLKS
THAT REACHED OUT TO PRESENT MANAGEMENT AND OTHER FOLKS TO
GET THIS FIXED SO THAT WE HAVE MORE FEEDBACK ON IT AND SO THAT
WE CAN GET IT CLOSER TO MOVING FORWARD.
AS A LEGISLATIVE AIDE I WORKED ON SOME LEGISLATION THAT
SOMETIMES INCLUDED REPORTS AS WELL AND LOOKING BACK AT IT NOW
I'M LOOKING AND SAYING DID WE REALLY NEED TO HAVE SOME THOSE
REPORTS? AND YOU KNOW, SOMETIMES WE
PROPOSED THINGS BECAUSE AT THE MOMENT WE WANT SOME ADDITIONAL
ADDITIONAL FEEDBACK OR A KIND OF ABILITY OR WE WANT TO MAKE
SURE SOMETHING GETS THERE. >> AND SO I THINK ALSO IT GIVES
US A LESSON AS LEGISLATORS IN THE FUTURE THEN WHEN WE'RE
WORKING ON OUR OWN ORDINANCES WHAT ARE THINGS THAT WE'RE THAT
ARE IMPORTANT ENOUGH TO JUSTIFY REPORTS AND WHAT ARE THE THINGS
THAT ARE LITTLE BIT EXTRANEOUS THAT MAY NOT NECESSARILY NEED
THAT. SO THAT'S SOMETHING THAT I
MYSELF WOULD BE COGNIZANT IN THE FUTURE WHEN WE'RE
DRAFTING POTENTIAL PIECES OF LEGISLATION.
SO JUST ONE THINK A CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHIU AND ALSO
PRESENT MANAGEMENT FOR THE WORK ON THIS LEGISLATION.
>> THANK YOU AND THANKS TO MY COLLEAGUES FOR THANKING ME.
SCULLY IN MY OFFICE I'D ALSO LIKE TO THANK MELANIE MATHESON
PREVIOUS THE PREVIOUSLY FROM MY OFFICE.
THEY BOTH HAVE DONE A TON OF WORK ON THIS.
I WOULD LIKE TO MOVE THE AMENDMENTS I'VE DESCRIBED
AND CIRCULATED IS SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
CAN WE TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION?
WITHOUT OBJECTION. THE MOTION PASSES AND THEN
MADAM CLERK COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE AMENDED
ORDINANCE ON ITEM FIVE AS AMENDED SUPERVISOR SAUDER
SAUTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON NO. SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN MIDDLEMAN
EYE AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR NO MELGAR NO.
THERE ARE SEVEN EYES AND FOUR NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON
CHIN FIELDER AND MELGAR VOTING NO.
>> THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO OUR 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER YES THE 230 SPECIAL ORDER
IS THE COMMENDATION FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> ALL RIGHTS AND FIRST UP
TODAY WE HAVE DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR WONG.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M PROUD TO RECOGNIZE LEE SAY FRIEND SAY
TO SAN FRANCISCO IN CELEBRATION OF FRENCH-AMERICAN HERITAGE
MONTH IT IS ESPECIALLY FITTING THAT WE PRESENT THIS
COMMENDATION TODAY ON BASTILLE DAY AS WE CELEBRATE THE
ENDURING FRENCH IDEALS OF LIBERTY, EQUALITY
AND FRATERNITY AS WELL AS THE LONG STANDING FRIENDSHIP
BETWEEN FRANCE AND THE UNITED STATES, LEE SAY HAS BEEN PART
OF OUR CITY FOR NEARLY SIX DECADES.
IT WAS FOUNDED IN 1967 BY A SMALL GROUP OF PARENTS
AND TEACHERS BEGINNING WITH JUST 27 ELEMENTARY STUDENTS
IN A ONE ROOM SCHOOLHOUSE ON CURIE BOULEVARD.
TODAY THE SAY SERVES APPROXIMATELY 850 TO 900
STUDENTS FROM PRESCHOOL THROUGH HIGH SCHOOL ACROSS THREE BAY
AREA CAMPUSES. IT'S REMARKABLY DIVERSE.
COMMUNITY REPRESENTS MORE THAN 50 NATIONALITIES AND SPEAKS
OVER 30 LANGUAGES. DISTRICT FOUR IS PARTICULARLY
PROUD TO BE HOME TO THE EARLY SAIS ORTEGA CAMPUS LOCATED AT
19TH AVENUE AND ORTEGA STREET IN THE SUNSET DISTRICT.
WHEN I USED TO LIVE ON 21ST IN NORIEGA I'D ACTUALLY WALK UP
THE STREET AND ALWAYS WONDER WHAT THE BUILDING WAS THIS
HISTORIC CAMPUS HAS SERVED AS ITS MIDDLE AND HIGH SCHOOL HOME
SINCE 2007 AND HAS BECOME AN IMPORTANT EDUCATIONAL
AND CULTURAL INSTITUTION IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD THROUGH ITS FRENCH
AMERICAN EDUCATIONAL MODEL. THE LEE SAY, DOES MUCH MORE
THAN TEACH STUDENTS IN OTHER LANGUAGE IT HELPS YOUNG PEOPLE
DEVELOP INTELLECTUAL CURIOSITY ,ADAPTABILITY, EMPATHY AND THE
ABILITY TO UNDERSTAND THE WORLD FROM MULTIPLE PERSPECTIVES.
FOR FAMILIES WHO MAY ASSUME THAT STUDENTS MUST ALREADY
SPEAK FRENCH TO ATTEND, THE LISA'S MESSAGE IS SIMPLE NO
FRENCH NO PROBLEM. ITS INTERNATIONAL TRACK
WELCOMES STUDENTS WITHOUT PRIOR FRENCH LANGUAGE EXPERIENCE
MAKING ITS BILINGUAL AND MULTICULTURAL EDUCATION
ACCESSIBLE TO AN EVEN BROADER COMMUNITY.
THIS YEAR THE LISA ALSO ACHIEVED AN IMPORTANT MILESTONE
BY BECOMING A FULLY AUTHORIZED INTERNATIONAL BACCALAUREATE
WORLD SCHOOL. ON BEHALF OF THE OFFICE OF THE
DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR, IT IS MY HONOR TO COMMEND LEE SAY
FRANCAIS TO SAN FRANCISCO FOR NEARLY 60 YEARS OF EDUCATIONAL
EXCELLENCE, CULTURAL EXCHANGE AND SERVICE TO GENERATIONS OF
SAN FRANCISCO FAMILIES. CONGRATULATIONS TO THE ENTIRE
SAY FAMILY AND IF YOU CAN COME UP AND SAY A FEW WORDS TO I
FORGOT TO CALL YOU UP EARLIER. >> SO MY NAME IS EMMANUEL TAKES
HIM TO THE HEAD OF SCHOOL OF THE RECEIVE HANDSETS AND PHONE
CISCO'S SUPERVISOR WANDA PRESIDENT MEMBERS OF THE OF THE
BOARD AND THANK YOU IT IS A SPECIAL HONOR TO TO STAND
IN THIS CHAMBER TODAY OF ALL DAY JULY 14TH BASTILLE DAY THE
NATIONAL DAY OF FRANCE AND HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO A DAY WHEN THE
FRENCH AND AMERICAN FLAGS FLY TOGETHER OVER THIS VERY
BUILDING. AND AS IF THE CALENDAR I WANTED
TO MAKE THE POINT FOR ME AT THIS VERY HOUR ON AMERICAN SOIL
FRANCE HAS JUST LOST THE WORLD CUP SEMIFINAL IN DALLAS.
CONGRATULATIONS. IF THERE IS ANYBODY OF SPANISH
DESCENT HERE, CONGRATULATION TO SPAIN.
OUR STUDENTS INDEED HAVE FOLLOWED EVERY MATCH OF
LIEBELER THIS SUMMER RIGHT HERE IN THE UNITED STATES.
CHEERING CHEERING IN TWO LANGUAGES I CAN THINK OF NO
BETTER IMAGE OF THE FRENCH AMERICAN FRIENDSHIP WE
CELEBRATE TODAY AND NO BETTER CITY IN WHICH TO CELEBRATE
NATIONAL FRENCH AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH.
FRANCE IS AMERICA'S OLDEST ALLY.
THE FRIENDSHIP OLDER THAN THE REPUBLIC ITSELF.
BUT FRIENDSHIP BETWEEN NATION IS NOT SUSTAINED BY HISTORY
ALONE. IT IS SUSTAINED BY PEOPLE, BY
FAMILIES, BY CLASSROOMS. THAT IS THE WORK OF THE 87 SAID
SCHOOL. SINCE 1967 THE USA HAS EDUCATED
GENERATIONS OF SAN FRANCISCANS IN TWO LANGUAGES AND TWO
CULTURES FROM PRESCHOOL TO 12TH GRADE.
TODAY NEARLY 1000 STUDENTS LEARN ACROSS OUR THREE CAMPUSES
INCLUDING OUR ORTEGA CAMPUS IN THE HEART OF THE SUNSET
DISTRICT WHICH WE ARE PROUD TO CALL HOME AND WHICH SUPERVISOR
WONG WILL VISIT TOMORROW MORNING.
WE LOOK FORWARD TO WELCOMING YOU SUPERVISOR.
ALL STUDENTS COME FROM DOZENS OF COUNTRIES BUT WHAT THEY
SHARE IS THIS CITY. THEY GROW UP BILINGUAL
AND BICULTURAL AT EASE CROSSING BETWEEN LANGUAGES, PERSPECTIVES
AND TRADITIONS. THEY GRADUATE WITH BOTH FRENCH
AND AMERICAN DIPLOMAS. AND THIS YEAR WITH OUR
INTERNATIONAL BACCALAUREATE TRACK NOW FULLY ACCREDITED WITH
NO FRENCH REQUIRED IN MIDDLE SCHOOL AND HIGH SCHOOL.
AND THAT'S IT FOR EVERYONE IN THE SUNSET OF SAN FRANCISCO.
OUR STUDENTS CARRY SAN FRANCISCO'S SPIRIT OF OPENNESS
INTO UNIVERSITIES AND CAREERS AROUND THE WORLD.
AS WE APPROACH OUR 60TH ANNIVERSARY NEXT YEAR, THIS
COMMENDATION MEANS A LOT AND A GREAT DEAL TO ALL OUR STUDENTS
OUR TEACHERS, OUR FAMILIES AND OUR ALUMNI.
IT AFFIRMS SOMETHING WE BELIEVE DEEPLY THAT A SCHOOL CAN BE
BOTH PROUDLY FRENCH AND THOROUGHLY SAN FRANCISCAN.
SO ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE COMMUNITY, THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WONGA FOR THIS RECOGNITION.
THANK YOU TO THE BOARD FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
LET ME GIVE HONG KONG AMERICAN LEAVES OF COFFEE SCHOOL.
AND HAPPY BEST DAY TO ALL. >> THANK YOU.
YOU'RE HERE DOING 3 TO 1. >> DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR
WALTON. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
PRESIDENT MANAGMENT COLLEAGUES. IN HONOR OF DISABILITY PRIDE
MONTH I WANT TO PROUDLY RECOGNIZE ANTONIO BABY TONY
GARCIA FOR HIS UNWAVERING KINDNESS.
>> BABY TELLING OF YOU TO COME UP AND STAND BEFORE I WANT TO
HONOR HIM FOR HIS DEDICATION TO SERVICE AND THE JOY HE BRINGS
TO EVERYONE AROUND HIM. FROM DAY ONE BABY TONE HAS BEEN
ONE OF MY BIGGEST SUPPORTERS. HE HAS VOLUNTEERED AT COUNTLESS
COMMUNITY EVENTS. HE HAS HELPED SHARE INFORMATION
WITH FAMILIES AND GREETED NEIGHBORS WITH A SMILE
AND ALWAYS STEPPED UP WHEN HELP WAS NEEDED.
>> WHETHER LIFTING BOXES DURING THE COVID 19 PANDEMIC FOR FOOD
DISTRIBUTIONS AND TESTING SITES OR LENDING A HAND AT COMMUNITY
CELEBRATIONS. >> BABY TONY HAS NEVER
HESITATED TO SERVE OTHERS. >> HIS COMMITMENT TO COMMUNITY
SERVICE IS DEEPLY ROOTED IN HIS FAMILY.
HIS FATHER ANTONIO GARCIA SERVES OUR CITY THROUGH THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS HELPING KEEP SAN FRANCISCO
STREETS CLEAN. HIS GRANDMOTHER LORENA OROPEZA
HAS DEDICATED MORE THAN 30 YEARS TO SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL
HOSPITAL WHERE SHE CURRENTLY WORKS IN LABOR AND DELIVERY.
>> THEIR FAMILIES TRADITION OF VOLUNTEERING, SERVING ON BOARDS
AND GIVING BACK HAS CLEARLY INSPIRED BABY TONY, WHO IS
KNOWN AND LOVED THROUGHOUT THE COMMUNITY.
EVERYWHERE HE GOES SOMEONE KNOWS HIM.
>> AND FOR GOOD REASON. DESPITE FACING CHALLENGES THAT
MIGHT DISCOURAGE OTHERS, MAYBE TONY HAS SHOWED US THAT
OBSTACLES DO NOT DEFINE A PERSON.
HE APPROACHES EVERY DAY WITH DETERMINATION, OPTIMISM AND A
CONTAGIOUS SMILE. HE REMINDS ALL OF US THAT
HAPPINESS, RESILIENCE AND PERSEVERE PARENTS ARE
CHOICES. AND THAT WITH HEART
AND DETERMINATION ANYTHING IS POSSIBLE.
ONE OF THE MANY STORIES THAT PERFECTLY CAPTURES HIS GENEROUS
SPIRIT IS WHEN HE LEARNED HOW TO PLACE ONLINE ORDERS USING
HIS FAMILY'S PHONES. >> NATURALLY HE DIDN'T JUST
THINK OF HIMSELF. HE MADE SURE TO ORDER FOR ALL
OF HIS COUSINS AS WELL. AND IF HE EVER HAD $14,000 TO
SPEND WE ARE ALL CONVINCED WE'D EACH RECEIVE AN ELECTRIC BIKE
AND A HELMET BECAUSE BABY TONE BELIEVES IN LOOKING OUT FOR
OTHERS AND MAKING SURE EVERYONE STAYS SAFE.
MAYBE TONY HAS ALWAYS DREAMED OF BECOMING A POLICE OFFICER OR
SHERIFF. AND ANYONE WHO HAS SEEN HIM
IN UNIFORM KNOWS HE TAKES THAT RESPONSIBILITY SERIOUSLY.
OUR COMMUNITY EVENTS HE PROBABLY HELPS DIRECT TRAFFIC
KEEPS A WATCHFUL EYE ON EVERYONE AND PROVIDES HIS OWN
SPECIAL BRAND OF COMMUNITY SAFETY.
WHILE NO ONE IS QUITE SURE HOW HE DEVELOPED SUCH A PASSION FOR
LAW ENFORCEMENT, IT MAKES PERFECT SENSE.
AND HIS GREATEST DESIRE IS SIMPLY TO HELP PEOPLE.
HIS ONE REQUIREMENT FOR EVERYONE HE MEETS IS SIMPLE
SMILE. >> AND THANKS TO HIS INFECTIOUS
JOY IT'S NEARLY IMPOSSIBLE NOT TO.
MOST RECENTLY THROUGH THE OPPORTUNITIES FOR OUR PROGRAM
BABY TONE ACHIEVED ANOTHER MILESTONE BY BEGINNING WORK AT
JIM'S RESTAURANT WHERE HE PROUDLY SERVES BREAKFAST ON
SATURDAYS. IT IS ANOTHER EXAMPLE OF HIS
STRONG WORK ETHIC, HIS WILLINGNESS TO CONTRIBUTE
AND HIS DETERMINATION TO CONTINUE GROWING AND GIVING
BACK. >> TODAY WE CELEBRATE BABY TOM
NOT ONLY FOR WHAT HE DOES BUT FOR WHO HE IS.
HE REMINDS US THAT TRUE LEADERSHIP IS MEASURED BY
KINDNESS, SERVICE, GENEROSITY AND THE ABILITY TO MAKE OTHERS
SEEM FEEL I MEAN FEEL SEEN IN VALUE.
ON A PERSONAL NOTE, BABY TONE HAS WORKED WITH ME IN COMMUNITY
FOR SEVERAL YEARS DURING COVID TO FEED PEOPLE AND IN ALL MY
ENDEAVORS TO GET WHERE I AM TODAY.
THANK YOU BABY TOM FOR BEING AN INSPIRATION A ROLE MODEL AND A
SHINING EXAMPLE OF WHAT IT MEANS TO PUT YOUR COMMUNITY
FIRST. SAN FRANCISCO IS A BETTER PLACE
BECAUSE OF YOU. >> THANK YOU GUYS FOR.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR. >> DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR CHEN.
THANK YOU. BOARD PRESIDENT.
MAY I HAVE PERSON MR. DAVID HOOPER TO COME TO THE PODIUM?
>> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE. TODAY IT'S MY GREAT HONOR TO
RECOGNIZE THE NEW MISSION TERRACE IMPROVEMENT ASSOCIATION
FOR OVER 75 YEARS OF SERVICE TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
FOUNDED IN 1949, AN EMPTY YEAR HAS FOSTERED A CONNECTION US
HOSTING MONTHLY MEETING THAT CONNECT RESIDENTS WITH CITY
DEPARTMENTS ORGANIZING NEIGHBORHOOD EVENTS
AND CREATING OPPORTUNITIES FOR FAMILIES, SENIORS AND YOUTH TO
BUILD FRIENDSHIPS. AND I AM AM TIRED ORGANIZATIONS
FAMILIES LOOK FORWARD TO BELOVED TRADITIONS.
NIGHT OUR ANNUAL 4TH OF JULY PARADE AND PICNICS IN ITS 37TH
YEAR. AND OTHER FUN EVENTS LIKE
EASTER EGG HUNTING AND ALLEYWAY PAST PASTA FESTIVAL.
MORE THAN JUST FOND MEMORIES THIS EVENT'S BUTTE'S COMMUNITY.
SO WHEN SOMETHING HAPPENS, NEIGHBORS SHOW UP FOR EACH
OTHER WHEN THEY NEED IT THE MOST.
EVEN IN ISOLATION AS MISSION TERRACE REMAINS CONNECTED
DURING COVID, THEY REFUSED TO LET THE NEIGHBORHOOD LOSE ITS
SENSE OF JOY AND CONNECTIONS. ON HALLOWEEN THEY ORGANIZED
THEIR FAMILIES PLACING TREES OUTSIDE THEIR HOMES AND BEFORE
LONG CANDY SO CHILDREN COULD STILL EXPERIENCE THE EXCITEMENT
OF TRICK OR TREATING ON THE 4TH OF JULY.
>> VOLUNTEER DISTRIBUTE THAT SIDEWALK TRUCKS SO CHILDREN'S
AND FAMILIES COULD TURN THEIR DRIVEWAYS AND THEIR
NEIGHBORHOOD STREETS INTO SORTS OF ART BEYOND FUN EVENTS.
AND MTI ALSO MAKES A LASTING IMPACT THROUGH ADVOCACY.
THEY SUPPORTED THE FOUNDING OF EXCELSIOR YOUTH CENTER,
SUPPORTED AFFORDABLE SENIOR HOUSING AT 55199 MISSION STREET
FOR THE RENOVATIONS OF THE YOUTH COMMUNITY ART CENTER
AND HELP PRESERVE THE HISTORIC OLD ALAMEIN EMERGENCY HOSPITAL
WHICH TODAY CONTINUES SERVE OUR COMMUNITY AS A CLINIC AS IT
NAMES THE CLINIC BY THE BAY. THEIR COMMITMENT TO COMMUNITY
BUILDING CIVIC ENGAGEMENT AND PUBLIC SAFETY HAS MAKE
MISSION TO STRONGER FOR GENERATIONS.
FINALLY, I WOULD LIKE TO RECOGNIZE SOMEONE WHO HAS
DEVOTED COUNTLESS HOURS TO THIS NEIGHBORHOOD AND MTI IS
LONGTIME PRESIDENT DAVID COOPER.
>> DAVID NEEDS WIT AND UNWAVERING LOVE FOR THIS
COMMUNITY. HIS LEADERSHIP REMINDS US THAT
ONE CARING NEIGHBOR CAN INSPIRE AN ENTIRE NEIGHBORHOOD.
PLEASE JOIN ME IN CONGRATULATING THE NEW
MISSION TERRACE IMPROVEMENT ASSOCIATION ON THIS WELL
DESERVED RECOGNITIONS. AND LET'S GIVE A BIG WARM
WELCOME TO MR. DAVID HOOPER TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
>> THANK YOU. >> PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
SUPERVISOR CHEN AND AND ALL THE REST OF THE SUPERVISORS THANK
YOU VERY MUCH. I APPRECIATE THE HONOR AND I
ACCEPT THAT ON BEHALF OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION
AND OUR COMMUNITY WE DO OTHER THINGS TO.
ON FEBRUARY 14TH WE HAVE A PEDESTRIAN SAFETY WALK AND THE
THEME IS STOP IN THE NAME OF LOVE.
YOU MAY HAVE HEARD THIS SONG WHEN I MOVED INTO THE
NEIGHBORHOOD FROM WHERE I WAS RAISED AND THE MISSION 40 YEARS
AGO THE PRESIDENT WAS THE LATE GREAT TONY SOCKO.
AND UNDER HIS LEADERSHIP AND DIRECTION AND I COULD LIST
40 50 PEOPLE AT A AT A MOMENT AND I THINK THE SAME SAME IDEA
EXISTS IN OUR COMMUNITY NOW. SO I WOULD MAKE A PITCH FOR THE
FULL RESTORATION OF THE GENEVA OFFICE BUILDING AT GENEVA
AND SAN JOSE AS A YOUTH ART RESOURCE.
IT'S ALSO WHERE I TOOK MY ORAL EXAM FOR THE MUNI RAILWAY 50
YEARS AGO. AND I THINK THAT EVERY EFFORT
THAT WE MAKE IS DUPLICATED IN MANY OTHER COMMUNITIES
IN THE CITY. WE AREN'T THAT SPECIAL.
PEOPLE ARE DOING THIS THROUGHOUT THE CITY.
SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH. OH AND ONE THING THE
NEIGHBORHOOD IS MISSION TERRACE BUT THE ORGANIZATION IS THE NEW
MISSION TERRACE. SO JUST TO CLARIFY, IT'S THANK
YOU VERY MUCH. >> THANK YOU.
>> HMM. OKAY.
I JUST CAME TO GIVE IT TO ONE. SORRY.
THANK YOU. >> CONGRATULATIONS, DAVID.
>> CAN I INVITE ALLEGRA MADSEN AND KATE BEAUVAIS AND ANYBODY
ELSE FROM FRAME LINE WHO WANTS TO COME ON UP TO COME ON UP?
>> JUST ALLEGRA JUST ALLEGRA WORDS THAT HAVE NEVER BEEN
SAID. OKAY.
COLLEAGUES, IT IS MY HONOR TODAY TO PRESENT A SPECIAL
COMMENDATION TO FRAME LINE WHICH JUST THIS PAST JUNE
CELEBRATED THE 50TH ANNIVERSARY OF THEIR FILM FESTIVAL THE
FREMONT FILM FESTIVAL. ALSO KNOWN AS THE SAN FRANCISCO
INTERNATIONAL LGBTQ PLUS FILM FESTIVAL IS THE LONGEST RUNNING
AND LARGEST SUCH FILM FESTIVAL IN THE WORLD, DRAWING MORE THAN
50,000 ATTENDEES EACH AND EVERY YEAR.
IN ADDITION TO ORGANIZING AND PRODUCING THE FESTIVAL
FRAME LINE WORKS YEAR ROUND TO PRESERVE AND PROMOTE FILM
AND MEDIA. >> FRAME LINE BEGAN IN 1976
WHEN A GROUP OF YOUNG AMATEUR FILMMAKERS CAME UP WITH THE
IDEA OF A FESTIVAL WHERE THEY COULD PUBLICLY SCREEN THEIR OWN
WORK. THEY ORGANIZED THE GAY FILM
FESTIVAL OF SUPER EIGHT FILMS WHICH SHOWCASED PRIMARILY
EXPERIMENTAL FILMS PROJECTED ONTO A BEDSHEET PINNED TO A
BOARD. >> IN THE YEARS THAT FOLLOWED,
THE FESTIVAL GREW OFFICIALLY ADOPTING THE NAME FRAME LINE
IN 1982 AND MOVING TO THE CASTRO THEATER IN 1990.
IN RESPONSE TO DEMANDS FOR MORE DIVERSE REPRESENTATION, THE
FESTIVAL BEGAN FEATURING MORE FILMS BY WOMEN AND FILMMAKERS
OF COLOR. ONE SUCH DEMAND KNOWN AS THE
LESBIAN RIOTS OF 1986 SAW WOMEN STORM THE ROXY PROJECTION BOOTH
TO PROTEST PROGRAMING IN RESPONSE FRAME LINE.
NOT ONLY EXPANDED THEIR PROGRAMING BUT ALSO CREATED THE
FRAME LINE COMPLETION FUND WHICH HAS SUPPORTED MORE THAN
190 FILMS AND VIDEOS BY EMERGING FILMMAKERS TO DATE
WITH A SPECIAL FOCUS ON WORKS BY AND FOR UNDERSERVED
COMMUNITIES. >> THIS YEAR FRAME LINE 58 HELD
JUNE 17TH THROUGH THE 27TH AT VENUES ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO,
OAKLAND AND BERKELEY SHOWCASED MORE THAN 140 FILMS FROM 35
COUNTRIES AND BROUGHT TOGETHER APPROXIMATELY 600 FILMMAKERS
AND INDUSTRY PROFESSIONALS FROM AROUND THE WORLD.
THE FESTIVAL PROVIDES EMERGING FILMMAKERS WITH A GLOBAL
PLATFORM TO SHARE THEIR WORK, FORGE INDUSTRY CONNECTIONS
AND REACH NEW AUDIENCES. FRAME LINE ALSO HONORS
OUTSTANDING FILMS THROUGH ITS OWN AWARDS PROGRAM AT THE FILM
FESTIVAL AND SERVES AS BOTH A BRITISH ACADEMY FILM AWARDS
QUALIFYING FESTIVAL AND AN IRIS PRIZE PARTNER FESTIVAL ANNUALLY
NOMINATING ONE SHORT FILM FOR CONSIDERATION FOR THE
PRESTIGIOUS INTERNATIONAL AWARD.
>> BEYOND THE FESTIVAL'S 11 DAYS FRAME LINE HOST SCREENINGS
AND SPECIAL EVENTS YEAR ROUND AND PROVIDES VITAL RESOURCES
AND OPPORTUNITIES TO LGBTQ PLUS FILMMAKERS.
FOR THE PAST THREE YEARS FRAME LINE HAS AWARDED THE COLIN
HIGGINS YOUTH FILMMAKER AWARD TO EMERGING FILMMAKERS WITH
THE INAUGURAL RECIPIENTS GOING ON TO PREMIERE THEIR FILMS AT
SUNDANCE. FRAME LINE ALSO OPERATES FRAME
LINE DISTRIBUTION THE NATION'S ONLY NONPROFIT FILM DISTRIBUTOR
DEDICATED EXCLUSIVELY TO LGBTQ CINEMA AND HAS HELPED RESTORE
AND PRESERVE FILMS THROUGH FRAME LINE RESTORATIONS.
>> FOR 50 YEARS FRAME LINE HAS ENSURED THAT STORIES ARE TOLD
AND SHOWCASED THROUGH FILM AROUND THE WORLD AND WE WANTED
TO THANK YOU AND HONOR YOU AND CONGRATULATE YOU ON THAT
ACHIEVEMENT. AND AND TODAY WE HAVE THE
OUTSTANDING EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF FRAME LINE ALLEGRA MADSEN TO
ACCEPT THIS RECOGNITION. >> ALLEGRA.
THE FLOOR IS YOURS. WELL, YOU STOLE MY SPEECH.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT ELSE IS THERE TO SAY?
THANK YOU. THANK YOU SO MUCH ON BEHALF OF
FRAME AND I'M HONORED TO ACCEPT THIS FRAME BY FRAME LINE'S
MISSION IS TO CHANGE THE WORLD THROUGH THE POWER OF CINEMA
AND THAT'S THE WORK THAT WE'VE BEEN DOING SINCE THE 70S.
THIS YEAR WE TURNED 50 AND THIS IS A MILESTONE YEAR.
WE BROUGHT NEARLY 50,000 MOVIE LOVERS AND THIS CONCLUDES 600
FILMMAKERS AND FILM INDUSTRY FOLKS FROM AROUND THE WORLD.
WE BROUGHT THEM TO THEATERS ACROSS THE CITY THE ROXY
AND THE MISSION VOGUE AND PRESIDIO HEIGHTS, THE
CASTRO THEATER AND BEYOND AND THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE SAT
IN THE DARK AND WATCHED THEIR LIVES AND THE LIVES OF THE
PEOPLE THAT THEY LOVE REFLECTED BACK TO THEM ON SCREEN.
AND THAT DOESN'T HAPPEN EVERYWHERE IT HAPPENS HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. IT HAPPENS HERE BECAUSE THE
INFRASTRUCTURE TO SUPPORT ART AND EXPRESSION EXISTS IN THIS
CITY FRAME LINE EXISTS BECAUSE THE IDEA OF SAN FRANCISCO A
CITY THAT VALUES ITS PEOPLE AND THE CREATIVE GENIUS THAT
COMES FROM TRUE DIVERSITY IS HERE WE ARE 50 YEARS OF THAT
FACT MADE REAL. SO THIS COMMENDATION ISN'T JUST
FOR US. IT'S EVERYONE WHO'S WORKED TO
BUILD THE SPACE IN SAN FRANCISCO LONG BEFORE FRAME
LINED SCREENED ITS FIRST FILM AND EVERYONE WHO'S CONTINUING
TO DO THAT WORK NOW AND THAT'S WHO I'M TRULY STANDING HERE FOR
FOR EVERY PROGRAMMER, EVERY STAFF MEMBER, EVERY VOLUNTEER,
EVERY FILMMAKER WHO HAS GIVEN THEIR WORK TO FRAME LINE SO
THAT THIS CITY NOT ONLY REMEMBERS ITS LEGACY BUT KEEPS
BUILDING IT. THAT'S THE JOB.
IT'S NOT JUST PRESERVATION BUT IT'S CONSTRUCTION AND THAT'S
THE JOB THAT WE'RE IN SO BEHALF ON BEHALF OF ALL OF THEM TO SAN
FRANCISCO, TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HERE YOU ARE VERY,
VERY WELCOME TO WE HAVE
OKAY MADAM CLERK WELL WE MADE IT A LITTLE WAY THROUGH OUR
REGULAR AGENDA. >> LET'S GO BACK TO ITEM SIX.
>> ITEM SIX THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE HEALTH
PLANNING POLICE AND BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS CODE TO
ESTABLISH A NEW PERMIT TYPE FOR CANNABIS CAFES TO BE
ADMINISTERED BY THE OFFICE OF CANNABIS THAT WILL AUTHORIZE
THE PERMIT T TO SELL CANNABIS AND CANNABIS PRODUCTS ONLY FOR
CONSUMPTION ON THE PREMISES OF THE CAFE AND TO AFFIRM THE
SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
THIS ITEM WAS REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION FROM THE LAND
USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS ITEM ON ITEM SIX SUPERVISOR
SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR ONE WONG NO SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN
NO. SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANNED
OLDMAN I'M IN SUPERVISOR MELGAR NO MELGAR NO THERE ARE SEVEN
EYES AND FOUR NOS WITH SUPERVISORS WONG CHIN CHIN
AND MELGAR VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER SEVEN ITEM SEVEN THIS IS
A CHARTER AMENDMENT SECOND DRAFT TO AMEND THE CHARTER OF
THE CITY AND COUNTY TO REQUIRE OR AUTHORIZE THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TO AMEND SPECIFIED INITIATIVE ORDINANCES TO
TRANSFER FROM THE CHARTER TO THE MUNICIPAL CODE.
CERTAIN COMMISSIONS AND ADVISORY BODIES IN SOME
CASES WITH MODIFIED FUNCTIONS AND OTHER VARIOUS CHANGES AT AN
ELECTION TO BE HELD ON NOVEMBER 3RD, 2026.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN, COLLEAGUES
I'M VOTING NO ON THIS CHARTER AMENDMENT BECAUSE OF THE
SWEEPING CHANGES IT PROPOSES TO OUR CITIZEN OVERSIGHT BODIES.
>> SAN FRANCISCANS PASSED PROPOSITION E IN NOVEMBER OF
2024 TO REDUCE DUPLICATION AND INCREASE THE EFFICIENCY OF
OUR BOARDS, COMMISSIONS AND ADVISORY BOARDS NOT TO
CONCENTRATE EVEN MORE POWER IN THE HANDS OF THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE TO TAKE A HATCHET TO COMMISSIONS THAT PROVIDE
OVERSIGHT AND TRANSPARENCY FOR THE PUBLIC OR TO STRIP VOTERS
OF THE POWER TO MAKE FUTURE CHANGES.
WHILE THERE MAY BE SOME CHANGES IN THIS CHARTER AMENDMENT THAT
ARE NEUTRAL IN NATURE, THE MAJORITY GO FAR BEYOND THE
ORIGINAL VOTER INTENT. FOR THAT REASON I'M VOTING NO
ON THIS ITEM. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU.
>> PRESENT AMENDMENT I DO WANT TO THANK YOU AND ALL CO-SPONSOR
ON THIS LEGISLATION FOR THE WORK THAT YOU HAVE DONE.
I DO APPRECIATE THE EFFORT OF ACCEPTING THE AMENDMENTS AT
RULES COMMITTEE. THEREFORE WHILE I APPRECIATE
THAT WORK THOUGH I AM NOT GOING TO BE VOTING IN SUPPORT NOT
BECAUSE I DON'T APPRECIATE THE WORK THAT'S BEING DONE IT JUST
SIMPLY BECAUSE I THINK THE OVERALL IDEA OF OF ELIMINATING
SOME OF THESE ADVISORY BODIES AND COMMISSION IS IN MY OPINION
NOT IN THE BEST INTERESTS OF THE CITY.
SO IT'S IT'S I TOTALLY JUST THINK THAT IT'S BASED ON
PRINCIPLE BUT I APPRECIATE THE EFFORT NONETHELESS.
>> THANK YOU. PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS
ITEM ON ITEM SEVEN. SUPERVISOR SAUTER.
SAUTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON I SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MONGOLOID MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR I MELGAR I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO NOS WITH
SUPERVISORS CHEN AND FIELDER VOTING NO AND THE CHARTER
AMENDMENT IS ORDERED SUBMITTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER EIGHT ITEM EIGHT THIS IS A CHARTER AMENDMENT SECOND
DRAFT TO AMEND THE CHARTER OF THE CITY AND COUNTY TO INCREASE
THE AMOUNT OF FUNDING THE CITY MUST APPROPRIATE TO THE HOUSING
TRUST FUND EACH FISCAL YEAR THAT IS USED FOR THE CREATION
ACQUISITION AND REHABILITATION OF AFFORDABLE RENTAL
AND OWNERSHIP HOUSING FOR DOWNPAYMENT LOANS AND HOUSING
STABILIZATION FOR CERTAIN HOUSEHOLDS AND FOR HOUSING
RELATED INFRASTRUCTURE TO PROVIDE FOR A TEMPORARY FREEZE
AND TEMPORARY REDUCTION IN THE ANNUAL APPROPRIATION TO THE
HOUSING TRUST FUND UNDER CERTAIN CIRCUMSTANCES TO EXTEND
THE SUNSET DATE OF THE HOUSING TRUST FUND FROM JULY 1ST TO 43
TO JULY 1ST, 2058 AND TO DELETE OBSOLETE PROVISIONS AT AN
ELECTION TO BE HELD ON NOVEMBER 3RD, 2026.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
COLLEAGUES, I AM SO EXCITED FOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO SEND THIS
MEASURE TO THE BALLOT TODAY AND ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
IT WILL SECURE A STEADY FUND OF SORT OF A STEADY SOURCE OF
FUNDING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND PRESERVATION THROUGH THE
EXPANSION AND THE EXTENSION OF THE EXISTING HOUSING TRUST FUND
TO EVENTUALLY REACH $125 MILLION BY DEDICATING A PORTION
OF FUTURE GROWTH OF PROPERTY VALUES IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THIS IS IMPORTANT BECAUSE IT IS NOT JUST MORE MONEY WHICH WE
DESPERATELY NEED FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING BUT THE WAY THE MONEY
BEHAVES IS DIFFERENT THAN THE WAY THAT WE HAD IT BEFORE.
THIS WILL PROVIDE THE ABILITY TO BOND AGAINST IT BECAUSE IT
IS BASED ON THE VALUATION CERTIFICATION OF THE ASSESSOR
THAT MUST BE SUBMITTED TO THE STATE EVERY YEAR.
SO WE CAN PREDICT THE WAY IT'S GOING TO GROW AND WE CAN BORROW
AGAINST IT THEREBY TRIPLING OUR ABILITY TO PRODUCE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AND GIVING THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING NONPROFITS
WHO BUILD IN ABILITY TO PLAN TO PLAN FOR THEIR CAPACITY, THEIR
STAFFING AND WHAT THEY HAVE IN THE PIPELINE AHEAD AND MOST
IMPORTANTLY THEIR CASH FLOW. >> THIS PROPOSED CHARTER
AMENDMENT INVOLVED A DIVERSE COALITION OF PARTNERS AND IT
WAS IMPORTANT THAT THE EXPANSION OF THE HOUSING TRUST
FUND WAS DONE IN A WAY THAT WAS INCREMENTAL FISCALLY
RESPONSIBLE GIVEN THE BUDGET CHALLENGES THAT WE HAVE FACED
IN THE LAST COUPLE OF YEARS AND AT THE SAME TIME THAT WE
REACH THE FUNDING AMOUNT THAT WE THAT WILL ALLOW THE CITY TO
MAKE THIS USEFUL INTO BOND AND MAXIMIZE THE NUMBER OF
UNITS THAT CAN BE BUILT. I RECOGNIZE THAT VOTERS WILL
HAVE A LOT TO CONTEND WITH IN THE NOVEMBER BALLOT BUT I
CANNOT STRESS ENOUGH HOW DIRE THE NEED IS FOR THIS FUNDING
BOTH IN TERMS OF THE NECESSARY THAT WE HAVE TO CREATE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING GIVEN OUR COMMITMENTS TO THE STATE
AND OUR RESIDENTS BUT ALSO THE STATE OF OUR NON-PRO FIT
HOUSING ORGANIZATIONS, OUR PARTNERS WHO ARE FACING A
FISCAL CLIFF IN 2029 IF WE DON'T DO SOMETHING ABOUT THE
SITUATION. I WANT TO THANK ALL OF MY
CO-SPONSORS AND I WANT TO THANK MAYOR LURIE FOR HIS SUPPORT
ALONG WITH THE STAFF WHO WORKED ON THIS NET.
SIEGEL ALI BONDI, BEN WHITE, LEE LICHTENSTEIN AND JACOB BEN
PHILLIPS. DIRECTOR DAN ADAMS.
COMPTROLLER GREG WAGNER AND HIS TEAM.
ASSESSOR WHO? RECORDER JOAQUIN TORRES AND HIS
TEAM. VICTORIA WANG BRAD RUSTY
AND KEITH NAKAYAMA AT THE CITY ATTORNEY.
AND OF COURSE OUR COMMUNITY PARTNERS THE COUNCIL OF
COMMUNITY HOUSING ORGANIZATIONS QUENTIN MACKEY, CAROLYN FANG,
THE COMMUNITY TRUST, SAKI BAILEY AND KYLE SIMPLY.
>> NONPROFIT HOUSING ASSOCIATION OF NORTHERN
CALIFORNIA AND ESPECIALLY BILL BARNES THE HOUSING ACCELERATOR
FUND. REBECCA FOSTER AND KATE
HARTLEY. THE MISSION ECONOMIC
DEVELOPMENT AGENCY CHINATOWN COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT CENTER.
>> MALCOLM YOUNG A ESPECIALLY ERIC TYLER TODD CO MERCY
HOUSING MISSION HOUSING EPISCOPAL COMMUNITY SERVICES
SELF-HELP FOR THE ELDERLY PINGAN RESIDENT IMPROVEMENT
ASSOCIATION. FIREFIGHTERS LOCAL 797 98
BUILDING AND CONSTRUCTION TRADES COUNCIL.
CARPENTERS UNION LOCAL 22. AND MANY MORE.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR WALTON.
THANK YOU SO MUCH, PRESIDENT MELAMED.
I DO JUST WANT TO STATE ON THE RECORD THAT I THINK IT IS
ARBITRARY TO EXTEND THE HOUSING TRUST FUND AND INCREASE THE
HOUSING TRUST FUND. >> AND AT THE VERY SAME MEETING
VOTE TO DECREASE INCLUSIONARY HOUSING.
TO ME THIS MAKES NO SENSE. BUT I AM GOING TO SUPPORT THIS
BECAUSE I DO BELIEVE THAT THIS IS NECESSARY.
BUT TO DO THIS IN A VERY SIMPLE AGENDA SUPPORT DECREASE
IN INCLUSIONARY HOUSING MAKES ABSOLUTELY NO SENSE.
THANK THE PRESENT AMENDMENT. SUPERVISOR WONG.
>> COLLEAGUES, I'M PROUD TO CO-SPONSOR THIS MEASURE.
THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND HER OFFICE FOR THEIR
LEADERSHIP AND HARD WORK ON THIS AND BRINGING PEOPLE
TOGETHER. WE ALL AGREE THAT SAN FRANCISCO
NEEDS TO BUILD MORE HOUSING BUT AS WE WORK TO MAKE IT EASIER TO
BUILD WE ALSO NEED TO MAKE SURE THAT WORKING FAMILIES, SENIORS
AND YOUNG PEOPLE CAN AFFORD TO REMAIN PART OF OUR CITY.
THE HOUSING TRUST FUND HAS HELPED CREATE AND PRESERVE
AFFORDABLE HOMES AND SUPPORT OPPORTUNITIES FOR FIRST TIME
HOMEBUYERS. THIS MEASURE WILL STRENGTHEN
THAT FUND OVER TIME WHILE INCLUDING REASONABLE
PROTECTIONS WHEN THE CITY FACES A SERIOUS BUDGET SHORTFALL.
THIS IS A BALANCED APPROACH. IT SUPPORTS MORE HOUSING
PRODUCTION WHILE MAKING A LONG TERM COMMITMENT TO
AFFORDABILITY AND NEIGHBORHOOD STABILITY.
HOUSING COSTS ARE PUSH PUSHING TOO MANY PEOPLE OUT OF SAN
FRANCISCO. WE NEED TO GIVE VOTERS THE
OPPORTUNITY TO INVEST IN A CITY WHERE PEOPLE OF DIFFERENT
INCOMES CAN STILL BUILD A LIFE. THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS
ITEM ON ITEM NINE EIGHT. >> EXCUSE ME, MR. PRESIDENT ON
ITEM EIGHT. SUPERVISOR SAUTER.
SAUTER I SUPERVISED FOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON I
WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR AMONG MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I RANDLEMAN I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
CHARTER AMENDMENT IS ORDERED SUBMITTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE
CALL ITEM NUMBER NINE ITEM NINE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND
THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO INCREASE THE MINIMUM GRANT
AWARD AMOUNT REQUIRING BOARD APPROVAL FOR ACCEPTANCE
AND EXPENDITURE FROM 100,000 TO THE GREATER OF 1 MILLION OR THE
FEDERAL SINGLE AUDIT THRESHOLD AMOUNT SET BY THE UNITED STATES
OFFICE OF MANAGEMENT AND BUDGET STARTING OCTOBER 1ST, 2026 TO
REQUIRE BOARD APPROVAL OF A GRANT INCREASE ONLY IF IT
RAISES THE GRANT TO THE APPROVAL THRESHOLD FOR THE TIME
FOR THE FIRST TIME OR INCREASES A PREVIOUSLY APPROVED GRANT
EITHER 110% OR MORE OF THE PREVIOUSLY APPROVED AMOUNT OF
200,000. >> COLLEAGUES, LET'S TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
TEN. >> ITEM TEN PURSUANT TO CHARTER
SECTION 8.42 TO THIS MATTER REQUIRES A VOTE OF THREE
FOURTHS OR NINE MEMBERS OF THE FULL BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO
APPROVE THIS PASSAGE OF THE ORDINANCE ON FIRST READING ITEM
TEN IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROVE HEALTH SERVICES AND PLANS
AND CONTRIBUTION RATES FOR CALENDAR YEAR 2027 AND I THINK
WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 11 THROUGH 13 TOGETHER ITEMS 11
THROUGH 13 ARE THREE RESOLUTIONS THAT AUTHORIZE THE
PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND TWO GRANTS
AND RETROACTIVELY EXECUTE A CONTRACT AMENDMENT.
ITEM 11 AUTHORIZES THE ACCEPT AN EXPENDITURE 4 MILLION FROM
THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN FRANCISCO TO
FUND THE MISSION BAY FERRY LANDING PROJECT MAY 1ST, 2026
THROUGH MARCH 31ST 2028 ITEM 12 RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE
PORT TO EXECUTE AN AMENDMENT THE SIXTH AMENDMENT TO A
PROFESSIONAL SERVICES CONTRACT C OWI FORWARD SLASH OLEMA JOINT
VENTURE FOR ARCHITECTURAL AND ENGINEERING SERVICES FOR
THE MISSION BAY FERRY LANDING PROJECT TO EXTEND THE CONTRACT
TERM RETROACTIVELY FROM JUNE 16TH 2026 FOR A TOTAL TERM OF
JANUARY THIRD 2017 TO JUNE 30TH 2028 WITH NO CHANGES TO THE
CONTRACT AMOUNT OF 6.4 MILLION. AND FOR ITEM 13 THIS RESOLUTION
AUTHORIZES THE PORT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A $4.5 MILLION GRANT
FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO COUNTY TRANSPORTATION AUTHORITY TO
FUND THE MISSION BAY FERRY LANDING PROJECT JULY 15TH, 2026
THROUGH SEPTEMBER 30TH 2028 SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED AND PLEASE CALL ITEMS
14 AND 15 TOGETHER ITEMS 14 AND 15 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT
APPROVE AIRPORT AGREEMENTS ITEM 14 APPROVES THE HARVEY MILK
TERMINAL ONE AND TERMINAL THREE TRAVELERS RETREAT BETWEEN
HOTELS O LLC AS TENANT AND THE CITY FOR A 12 YEAR TERM AND A
MINIMUM ANNUAL GUARANTEE OF 350,000 AND ITEM 15 APPROVES
THE LEASE TERMINATION AGREEMENT FOR THE TERMINAL TO CASUAL
DINING FOOD AND BEVERAGE CONCESSION LEASE SIX BETWEEN
SSP AMERICA INC AS TENANT AND THE CITY ACTING BY
AND THROUGH ITS AIRPORT COMMISSION AS LANDLORD SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 16 AND 17 TOGETHER ITEM 16
AND 17 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT AUTHORIZE THE OFFICE OF THE
DISTRICT ATTORNEY TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND TWO GRANTS.
ITEM 16 IS FOR AN APPROXIMATE $91,000 GRANT TERMS JULY 1ST
2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027 AND 91,000 FOR THE TERM JULY
1ST 2027 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 AND 91,000 FOR THE TERM OF JULY
1ST 2028 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029 FOR AN AMOUNT OF 275,000 FROM
THE CALIFORNIA VICTIM COMPENSATION BOARD FOR A GRANT
TERM OF JULY 1ST 2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029 TO CONTINUE THE
CRIMINAL RESTITUTION COMPACT SHOULD THE PARTIES AGREE TO AN
AMENDMENT AS ALLOWED UNDER THE PROVISIONS OF THE GRANT
AGREEMENT AND FOR ITEM 17 THIS IS FROM THE CHRIS LARSON FUND
$200,000 GIFT FACILITATED BY THE SILICON VALLEY COMMUNITY
FOUNDATION THROUGH FIVE KEYS TO SUPPORT A WOMAN'S INITIATIVE
PROJECT RESTORE WOMEN'S HOUSING FOR VICTIMS OF CRIME GEARED
TOWARDS SERVICING FAMILIES OF VIOLENT CRIME FOR THE PURPOSE
OF PUBLIC SAFETY PREVENTION EFFORTS.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 18 ITEM 18. >> THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT TO ENTER
INTO AN AGREEMENT WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO DOWNTOWN DEVELOPMENT
CORPORATION PERTAINING TO POTENTIAL IMPROVEMENTS
AND RENOVATIONS AT THE EMBARCADERO PLAZA AND THE SOO
BEERMAN PARK AND TO ACCEPT CASH GRANTS OF APPROXIMATELY 20
MILLION FOR THE PROJECT FOR THE TERM STARTING ON THE EXECUTION
OF THE DATE OF THE AGREEMENT THROUGH DECEMBER 2028.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 19 AN ITEM 19 RESOLUTION
TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO
ACCEPT AND EXPEND 87,000 IN-KIND GIFT OF WASTEWATER
ANALYSIS SERVICES FROM BIO BI ANALYTICS IN SUPPORT OF THE
DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH PUBLIC HEALTH FOR THE TERM OF JULY 1ST
2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027. >> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
PLEASE CALL ITEM 20 ITEM 20 RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE
ISSUANCE AND SALE FROM TIME TO TIME OF BONDS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT PRESCRIBING THE TERMS
OF THE SALE OF 270 MILLION OF SAID GENERAL OBLIGATION BONDS.
>> ELECTION OF 2024 SERIES B AUTHORIZING SALE OF SAID GO
BONDS BY NEGOTIATED SALE AND APPROVING THE FORM OF THE
BOND PURCHASE AGREEMENT TO APPROVE THE FORMS OF ONE OR
MORE PAYING AGENT AGREEMENTS AND AUTHORIZING THE EXECUTION
OF NECESSARY DOCUMENTS AND CERTIFICATES RELATING TO
SUCH BONDS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEM 20 ONE. ITEM 21 IS A MOTION TO DIRECT
THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST TO INITIATE A
PERFORMANCE AND MANAGEMENT AUDIT IN COLLABORATION WITH THE
COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE OF THE ACADEMY OF SCIENCES AND FISCAL
YEAR 2026 THROUGH 2027. >> CHAIR CHAN THANK YOU PRESENT
AMENDMENT COLLEAGUES THERE ARE OF COURSE THANK YOU SO MUCH
JUDY. >> MY NEXT ONE NEXT AND I
JUMPED THE GUN. ALL RIGHT THEN I THINK GOING
BACK TO 21 WE WILL TAKE 21 SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED AND THEN MADAM CLERK,
YOU WILL PLEASE CALL ITEMS 22 THROUGH 37 TOGETHER AND THEN WE
WILL ALLOW OUR BUDGET CHAIR TO TALK TO US.
>> OKAY? PLEASE GO AHEAD 24 2337
TOGETHER ITEMS 22 THROUGH 37 COMPRISE THE CITY'S BUDGET
PURSUANT TO CHARTER SECTION 9.100 B THE BOARD SHALL NOT
ADOPT THE BUDGET EARLIER THAN JULY 15TH NOR LATER THAN AUGUST
1ST. ITEM 22 IS THE BUDGET
AND APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE ESTIMATED RECEIPTS
AND ALL EXPENDITURES FOR DEPARTMENTS OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF JUNE FIRST 2026 FOR FISCAL YEARS ENDING JUNE
30TH 2027 AND JUNE 30TH 2028. ITEM 23 IS THE ANNUAL SALARY
ORDINANCE WHICH ENUMERATES POSITIONS IN THE ANNUAL BUDGET
AND APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE FOR FISCAL YEARS ENDING AND JUNE
30TH JUNE 2027 AND JUNE 30TH 2028 THAT CREATE CONTINUE
ESTABLISH POSITIONS ENUMERATE AND INCLUDING THEIR IN ALL
POSITIONS CREATED BY CHARTER STATE LAW FOR WHICH
COMPENSATIONS ARE PAID FROM CITY AND COUNTY FUNDS
AND APPROPRIATED IN THE ANNUAL APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE TO
AUTHORIZE APPOINTMENTS FOR CONTINUATION OF APPOINTMENTS
THERE TO TO SPECIFY AND FIX THE COMPENSATIONS AND WORK
SCHEDULES THEREOF AND TO AUTHORIZE APPOINTMENTS TO
TEMPORARY POSITIONS FOR AND FIXING COMPENSATIONS THERE
FOR ITEM 24 THIS ORDINANCE AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
TO AUTHORIZE THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR TO PAUSE, REDUCE
OR RETURN THE ANNUAL CONTRIBUTIONS BY THE
DEPARTMENTS THAT CONTRACT FOR PUBLIC WORKS UNDER
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE CHAPTER SIX TO THE SAN FRANCISCO
SELF-INSURANCE SURETY BOND FUND ITEM 25 THIS ORDINANCE MODIFIES
THE BASELINE FUNDING REQUIREMENTS FOR EARLY CARE
AND EDUCATION PROGRAMS IN FISCAL YEARS 2026, 2027
AND 2027 AND 2028 TO ENABLE THE CITY TO USE THE EARNED INTEREST
EARNED FROM THE EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION COMMERCIAL RENTS
TAX FOR THOSE BASELINE PROGRAMS .
ITEM 26 THIS ORDINANCE AMENDING THE HEALTH CODE TO SET PATIENT
RATES FOR SERVICES PROVIDED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
FOR FISCAL YEARS 20 2627 AND 2027 AND 28 ITEM 27 THIS
ORDINANCE AMENDS THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO INCREASE
CERTAIN UTILITY METER FEES AND AUTHORIZE THE COMPTROLLER
TO ANNUALLY ADJUST DEVICE FEES FOR WEIGHTS AND MEASURES
AND UTILITY METERS UP TO THE MAXIMUM ALLOWABLE UNDER STATE
LAW. ITEM 28 THIS ORDINANCE
TEMPORARILY SUSPENDS THE CAP ON THE USE OF HOMELESSNESS GROSS
RECEIPTS TAX REVENUES TO FUND SHORT TERM RENTAL SUBSIDIES
AND TO FIND THAT TEMPORARILY ALLOWING FOR INCREASED
EXPENDITURES ON SHORT TERM RENTAL SUBSIDIES WILL FURTHER
THE PURPOSE OF OUR CITY. >> OUR HOME FUND ITEM 29 THIS
ORDINANCE ADOPTS THE NEIGHBORHOOD BEAUTIFICATION
AND GRAFFITI CLEANUP FUND TAX DESIGNATION CEILING FOR TAX
YEAR 2026 ITEM 30 THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE FISCAL
YEAR 2026 THROUGH 2027 BUDGET OF THE OFFICE OF COMMUNITY
INVESTMENT AND INFRASTRUCTURE OPERATING AS THE SUCCESSOR
AGENCY TO THE REDEVELOPMENT AGENCY OF THE CITY AND COUNTY
AND APPROVES THE ISSUANCE OF BONDS IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL
AMOUNT OF 275 MILLION FOR THE PURPOSE OF FINANCING A PORTION
OF OCR EYES ENFORCEABLE OBLIGATIONS.
ITEM 31 THIS RESOLUTION CONCURS WITH THE COMPTROLLER OR
ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CONSUMER PRICE INDEX FOR 26 AND ADJUSTS
THE ACCESS LINE TAX BY THE SAME RATE ITEM 32 THIS RESOLUTION
AUTHORIZES AS THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC LIBRARY TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND A 1.5 MILLION IN GRANTS AS WELL AS IN-KIND
GIFTS, SERVICES AND CASH MONEYS FROM THE FRIENDS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC LIBRARY FOR DIRECT SUPPORT TO THE CHINATOWN
BRANCH RENOVATION CAPITAL PROJECT WITHIN THE TERM FISCAL
YEARS 2026 THROUGH 2027 THROUGH 2029 2030.
ITEM 33 THIS RESOLUTION AND AUTHORIZES THE ACCEPTANCE
AND EXPENDITURE OF REOCCURRING STATE GRANT FUNDS BY THE SAN
FRANCISCO DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH FOR FISCAL YEAR 2026
THROUGH 27 ITEM 34. THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE
FISCAL YEAR 20 2627 AND 20 2728 EXPENDITURE PLAN FOR THE
DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF HOUSING ITEM 35
THIS RESOLUTION CONCURS WITH THE COMPTROLLER CERTIFICATION
THAT DEPARTMENT SERVICES PREVIOUSLY APPROVED CAN BE
PERFORMED BY PRIVATE CONTRACTOR FOR A LOWER COST THAN SIMILAR
WORK PERFORMED BY CITY AND COUNTY EMPLOYEES FOR THE
FOLLOWING SERVICES FOR BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST
SERVICES. FLEET SECURITY SERVICES.
REAL ESTATE DIVISION. CUSTODIAL SERVICES.
REAL ESTATE DIVISION. SECURITY SERVICES.
CONVENTION FACILITIES MANAGEMENT FOR GENERAL SERVICES
AGENCY ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES AND SECURITY SERVICES FOR THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS SECURITY SERVICES FOR
HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF HOUSING AND THE HUMAN SERVICES
AGENCY FOOD SERVICES AT THE COUNTY JAIL FOR THE SHERIFF'S
DEPARTMENT ASSEMBLY A VOTE BY MAIL SERVICES FOR THE
DEPARTMENT OF ELECTION AND SECURITY SERVICES FOR THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT ITEM
36 THIS RESOLUTION CONCURS WITH THE COMPTROLLER CERTIFICATION
THAT DEPARTMENT SERVICES CAN BE PERFORMED BY PRIVATE CONTRACTOR
FOR A LOWER COST THAN SIMILAR WORK PERFORMED BY CITY
AND COUNTY EMPLOYEES FOR PROTECTIVE SERVICES, FOR ADULT
PROBATION AND SECURITY SERVICES FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
HEALTH AND FOR ITEM 37. THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES THE
RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT TO ISSUE AN AMENDED PERMIT
ALLOWING ANOTHER PLANET ENTERTAINMENT TO HOLD TICKETED
CONCERTS AT THE GOLDEN GATE PARK POLO FIELD TO TAKE PLACE
ON FRIDAY, SATURDAY AND SUNDAY FOLLOWING OR PRECEDING THE
OUTSIDE LANDS FESTIVAL IN 2027, 2028 AND 2029 IN EXCHANGE FOR A
MINIMUM PERMIT FEE OF 1.53 MILLION PER YEAR FOR TWO DAY
EVENTS AND APPROXIMATELY 2.2 MILLION PER YEAR FOR THREE DAY
EVENTS THROUGH 2029 AND WITH OPTIONS TO EXTEND THAT PERMIT
UNTIL 2035 WITH INCREASED MINIMUM PERMIT FEES DURING ANY
SUCH EXTENSION AND TO AFFIRM THE SQUAD DETERMINATION CHAIR
OR CHAN STAY THANK YOU PRESIDENT MAN DOMAIN
COLLEAGUES. AS YOU ARE WELL AWARE THIS IS
THE FIRST APPEARANCE OF THE BUDGET BEFORE YOU.
>> WE WILL BE CASTING OUR FIRST VOTE NEXT WEEK ON TUESDAY JULY
22ND AND THE SECOND VOTE THE FOLLOWING.
BUT SIMPLY TODAY WANT TO PRESENT TO YOU THE BUDGET ITEMS
WITH THE CHILLING LEGISLATION THAT WE HAVE CLERICAL
AMENDMENTS TO THE BOR SPENDING PLAN.
AND AFTER MY PRESENTATION TO YOU FOR THE AMENDMENTS TO YOUR
SPENDING PLAN THAT I'M GOING TO THEN TURN OVER TO THE MAYOR'S
BUDGET OFFICE. MS..
ELIZA PUGH SAYS SHE'S GOING TO PRESENT TO YOU THE TECHNICAL
ADJUSTMENTS PROVIDED FROM THE MAYOR AND SO IF I MAY THAT I'M
GOING. AND SO COLLECTIVELY I WILL MAKE
THAT MOTION TO MOVE THESE AMENDMENTS.
AND SO FIRST FROM ME I'M GOING TO READ OUT LOUD COLLEAGUES IS
FOR ITEM 22 AND THAT IS SPECIFICALLY FOR THESE BOARDS
AND ONLY FOUR BOARDS A SPENDING PLAN.
SO IT'S THE ORDINANCE APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE ON PAGE
ONE, LINE TWO ADDING TO AGENCY FOR HUMAN RIGHTS FORM ONLY
HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION AS AN IMPLEMENTING DEPARTMENT SINCE
THEY CURRENTLY ADMINISTER THE CONTRACT FOR YOUTH EMPLOYMENT.
AND ON PAGE TWO LINE 20 ADDING LANGUAGE TO MORE ACCURATELY
REFLECT INTENT. SO NOW IT READS THAT ACADEMIC
SKILL DEVELOPMENT GED PREP, ESL SKILL BUILDING EDUCATIONAL
SUPPORT SERVICES AND JOB TRAINING AND PREPAREDNESS FOR
CLIMATE RELATED JOBS FOR TRANSITIONAL YOUTH AND ADULTS
IN THE MISSION IMPACTED BY JUVENILE PROBATION, FOSTER
CARE, CHILD FARE WELFARE INVOLVEMENT LANGUAGE BARRIERS
AND LIMITED ACCESS TO TRADITIONAL EDUCATION SYSTEMS.
THEN ON PAGE 1 IN 5 LINES FOUR 5961 REMOVING CHECKBOXES
ERRONEOUSLY PLACED IN COLUMNS WITH THE HEADING ONE X.
AND NOW I'M GOING TO HAND TO TURN THIS OVER TO THE MAYOR'S
BUDGET OFFICE. MISS ELIZA PUGH.
>> HELLO. I DO YOU ALL HAVE COPIES?
>> OKAY, GREAT. UM, MY NAME IS ELIZA PUGH FROM
THE MAYOR'S BUDGET OFFICE AND I'M SUBMITTING THE ATTACHED
ADJUSTMENT TO THE MAYOR'S PROPOSED BUDGET FOR FY 27
AND FY 28. >> TECHNICAL ADJUSTMENTS
INCLUDE CORRECTING EXPENDITURES AT THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE.
THE SET OF TECHNICAL ADJUSTMENTS WILL INCREASE THE
PROPOSED FY 27 BUDGET BY $3,695,945 AND WILL NOT
INCREASE THE FY 28 BUDGET AND RESULTS IN A COST OF
3,000,006 $695,945 IN FY 27 AND NO COST IN FY 28.
>> SO OVER THE TWO YEARS THE NET IMPACT WILL BE A GENERAL
FUND COST OF $3 MILLION 695,945.
THE ATTACHED TABLE ON THE SECOND PAGE DETAILS THESE
CHANGES. I'M AVAILABLE FOR ANY QUESTIONS
. >> THANK YOU.
I. I DON'T SEE ANY QUESTIONS.
UM. CHITCHAT.
ANYTHING FURTHER YOU'VE MADE A MOTION.
IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY CHAN.
AND COLLEAGUES. CAN WE TAKE THAT WITHOUT.
OH, I HOPE WE CAN DO THAT. WE CAN TAKE THE AMENDMENT
WITHOUT OBJECTION. ALL RIGHT, SO A MOTION IS MADE
SECONDED AND THE MOTION PASSES WITHOUT OBJECTION.
>> OKAY. >> AND THEN CHAIR CHAN, DID
YOU. I DO.
AND THEN AND THEN I KNOW THAT WE ALSO HAVE TO HAVE TO MAKE MY
AMENDMENT TO THE OUR CITY OUR HOME SPENDING PLAN.
AGAIN ALSO IS AN ITEM 22 BUT THERE ARE WILL BE DETAILS THAT
SUPERVISOR CHEN IS GOING TO WALK US THROUGH ON THE
AMENDMENTS FOR THE SPENDING PLAN.
SO WE'LL BE SECOND MOTION TO ALSO AMEND.
>> OKAY. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> OKAY. I'M GOING TO SPEAK ON ITEM
NUMBER 28. COLLEAGUES.
AS MANY OF YOU KNOW, I'VE BEEN WORKING WITH THE MAYOR'S OFFICE
TO NEGOTIATE A SPENDING PLAN FOR THEIR OUR CITY OUR HOME
FUNDS THAT THE MAYOR'S TEAM, THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND COMMUNITY COULD ALL SUPPORT.
PAOLI. THIS YEAR'S PROPOSAL WAS
THOUGHTFUL AND CAREFULLY BALANCED.
BUT MY OFFICE HERVE MANY PROVIDERS AND COMMUNITY
STAKEHOLDERS CONCERNS ABOUT THE LACK OF ADDITIONAL LONG TERM
SUBSIDIES IN THE PLAN. AFTER MANY CONVERSATIONS WITH
PROVIDERS AND ADVOCATES AND PARTNERSHIP FROM THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE, WE HAVE NEGOTIATED A MODEST INCREASE OF
50 LONG TERM SUBSIDIES FOR FAMILIES LIVING IN SINGLE UNITS
CITYWIDE. >> I WANT TO THANK BUDGET CHAIR
CHEN FOR ALLOWING ME TO LEAD ON THIS YEAR AND I WANT TO
RECOGNIZE THE WORK OF MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE JACKIE PRAGER
,WHO WORKED DILIGENTLY WITH ALL STAKEHOLDERS TO COME TO AN
AGREEMENT. I WOULD LIKE TO ALSO THANK
DEPUTY CHIEF KUNAL MODI, HIS STAFF JESSICA KOZOL BUDGET
DIRECTOR SOPHIA TAYLOR AND ADAM TOM TOM SABAT FOR THEIR
WILLINGNESS TO WORK WITH MY OFFICE TO ACHIEVE A PLAN THAT
EVERYONE CAN BE PROUD OF. I WANT TO THANK TO PROVIDERS
AND ADVOCATES WHO WORK WITH MY STAFF TO FIGHT FOR MORE
RESOURCES FOR OUR FAMILIES. AND I'M GRATEFUL FOR EVERYONE'S
PARTNERSHIP AND LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING TO WORK WITH,
STABILIZE AND SUPPORT AND HOUSE THAT INDIVIDUAL IN OUR CITY
WHILE IMPROVING OUR CITY'S SYSTEMS.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN
FOR CHAN. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDARIN
IT'S MY MISTAKE COLLEAGUES. I'M RESENDING THAT MOTION THERE
IS NOT A NEED TO AMEND THE ACTUAL SPENDING PLAN TO REFLECT
THAT BECAUSE THIS IS AN AGREEMENT BETWEEN SUPERVISOR
CHEN DIRECTLY WITH THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
AND SUPPORT OF HOUSING ON THE SPENDING PLAN.
THEY CAN MAKE THE ADJUSTMENTS ON THEIR OWN AND SO WE'RE DONE
WITH THE MOTIONS TO AMEND. >> WE CAN NO LONGER AMEND NO
MORE THAN A WEEK. >> I MEAN WE CAN DO WHATEVER WE
WANT TO BUT MR. PRESIDENT WILL PUT A NOTE IN THE FILE AS TO
THE AGREEMENT. THANK YOU.
OKAY, GREAT. SO THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, CHAIR CHAN FOR GETTING US THROUGH THIS YEAR'S
BUDGET PROCESS AS YOU HAVE THE LAST 444 AND SO WE MAKE WE
CANNOT ACT ON THE BUDGET UNTIL JULY 15TH.
SO CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO CONTINUE THESE MATTERS TO THE
JULY 21ST 2026 BOARD MEETING MOVED BY CHEN SECONDED BY
DORSEY AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE BUDGET IS CONTINUED TO AND ALL OF
THESE ITEMS ARE CONTINUED TO JULY 21ST 2026 MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM 38. >> ITEM 38 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE
TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS CODE TO EXTEND THE
WAIVER OF CERTAIN FIRST YEAR PERMIT LICENSE AND BUSINESS
REGISTRATION AND FEES FOR SPECIFIED SMALL BUSINESSES THAT
NEWLY FORM OR THAT OPEN A NEW LOCATION UNDER THE EARLIER OF
JULY 1ST 2027 OR THE DATE ON WHICH ALL FUNDS APPROPRIATE IT
TO REIMBURSE DEPARTMENTS FOR THE WAIVED FEES HAVE BEEN
EXPENDED. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
AND NOW PLEASE CALL ITEM 39 ITEM 30 NINE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO REDUCE INCLUSIONARY
AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROGRAM REQUIREMENTS FOR PROJECTS OF 25
UNITS OR MORE TO DELETE INCLUSIONARY AFFORDABLE HOUSING
PROGRAM REQUIREMENTS FOR PROJECTS UNDER 25 UNITS TO
ALLOW ALL PROJECTS TO DEDICATE LAND TO THE CITY AS AN
ALTERNATIVE TO PAYMENT OF THE INCLUSIONARY AFFORDABLE HOUSING
PROGRAM FEE TO ADOPT A PROCESS FOR PROJECTS TO REQUEST A
MODIFICATION TO CONDITIONS OF APPROVAL RELATED TO
INCLUSIONARY AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROGRAM REQUIREMENTS TO DELETE
CERTAIN ARTICLE FOUR AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND DEVELOPMENT IMPACT
FEES AND TO ADOPT CONFORMING AMENDMENTS TO VARIOUS SECTIONS
OF THE PLANNING CODE TO AMEND THE BUILDING CODE TO REDUCE
PLANNING CODE ARTICLE FOUR DEVELOPMENT IMPACT FEES
AND ALLOW DEFERRAL OF PAYMENTS OF SUCH FEES AND TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO ADOPT CONFORMING AMENDMENTS TO THE
REQUIREMENTS OF THE CITYWIDE AFFORDABLE HOUSING FUND AND TO
AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MINUTEMAN. >> COLLEAGUES, AS I DISCUSSED A
GO COMMITTEE, I'M CONCERNED ABOUT THE IMPACT OF THIS
ORDINANCE ON THE DECADES LONG CAREFUL AND INTENTIONAL
PLANNING THAT IS FOCUSED ON THE MISSION DISTRICT.
>> THE MISSION AREA PLAN IS NOT A GENERIC PART OF SAN
FRANCISCO. >> IT IS AMONG THE MOST STUDIED
,MOST CONTESTED AND MOST INTENTIONALLY PLANNED AREAS
IN THE CITY'S RECENT HISTORY TREATING IT THE SAME AS THE
REST OF THE CITY WITHIN THE SITE INCLUSIONARY PERCENTAGES
IGNORES EVERYTHING THAT OUR PLANNING PROCESSES WERE BUILT
TO PROTECT THE MISSION HAS A UNIQUE PLANNING HISTORY THE
EASTERN NEIGHBORHOODS REZONING AND THE MISSION AREA PLAN WERE
THE PRODUCT OF YEARS OF COMMUNITY BASED PLANNING
EXPLICITLY DESIGNED TO RESPOND TO DISPLACEMENT PRESSURE ON
LATINO RESIDENTS, SMALL BUSINESSES AND LIGHT INDUSTRIAL
OR PDR USES IN THE MISSION THE CITY ALREADY RECOGNIZES THIS
THIS ORDINANCE ITSELF CARVES OUT A HIGHER OFFSITE AND IN
LIEU RATE FOR THE MISSION PROOF THAT PLANNING AND THE CITY
ALREADY TREAT THIS AREA AS DISTINCT WHEN IT COMES TO VALUE
CAPTURE THE ONSITE RATE SHOULD REFLECT THAT SAME DISTINCTION
NOT DEFAULTS TO THE CITYWIDE NUMBER.
THE PRESSURES THAT JUSTIFY THIS SPECIAL TREATMENT HAVEN'T GONE
AWAY. THE MISSION REMAINS ONE OF THE
HIGHEST DISPLACEMENT RISK NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN FRANCISCO
BY THE CITY'S OWN EQUITY MAPPING AND HERE I'M REFERRING
TO THE PRIORITY EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES STUDY AND THE
MISSION ACTION PLANS 2020 AND 2030 LOWERING THE ONSITE
REQUIREMENT TO A CITY WIDE GENERIC 5% BREAKS THE ORIGINAL
BARGAIN WITHOUT REVISITING THE DENSITY AND HEIGHT BENEFITS
THAT DEVELOPERS STILL RECEIVE IN THIS DISTRICT.
IF ANYTHING, CONTINUED DEVELOPMENT PRESSURE ON THE
MISSION STRENGTHENS A CASE FOR HOLDING THE LINE ON THAT
COMMITMENT NOT WEAKENING IT. >> WITH ALL OF THAT SAID, I'M
INTRODUCING AMENDMENTS TO REQUIRE AN 8% ONSITE
INCLUSIONARY RATE IN THE MISSION AREA PLAN WITH 6% AT
LOW INCOME AND 2% AT MODERATE INCOME FOR RENTAL AND OWNERSHIP
UNITS. >> THESE FIGURES ARE STILL WELL
BELOW THE CURRENT RATES OF 17% ONSITE INCLUSIONARY RATE FOR
THE MISSION AND JUST A BIT HIGHER THAN THE NEW PROPOSED
CITYWIDE ONSITE RATE OF 5%. RECOGNIZING THE INTENSIVE
PLANNING PROCESS THAT SHAPED AFFORDABILITY REQUIREMENTS
IN THIS AREA, THE DISPLACEMENT PRESSURES THIS AREA STILL FACES
AND THE SAME STANDARD ALREADY APPLIED TO OFFSITE AND IN LIEU
FEES HERE MY STAFF DISTRIBUTED THE AMENDMENTS EARLIER TODAY.
UNFORTUNATELY THEY WERE NOT READY FOR COMMITTEE SO I'M
INTRODUCING HERE TODAY THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE HAS CONFIRMED
THAT THESE ARE NOT SUBSTANTIVE AND WILL NOT DELAY THE PASSAGE
OF THIS LEGISLATION. SO COLLEAGUES, I ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT AND WITH THAT I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO ADOPT
THE AMENDMENTS ON PAGES 53 THROUGH 55 THAT I JUST
DESCRIBED REQUIRING AN 8% ONSITE INCLUSIONARY RATE IN THE
MISSION AREA PLAN WITH 6% AT LOW INCOME AND 2% AT MODERATE
INCOME FOR RENTAL AND OWNERSHIP UNITS.
THE REMAINING AMENDMENTS AT PAGES 5558 AND 60 SOLELY UPDATE
THE SECTION NUMBERS. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT
MIDDLEMEN SUPERVISOR FIELDER HASN'T MADE A MOTION
AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR HAS SECONDED IT.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN.
I WAS HAPPY TO SUPPORT THIS LEGISLATION COMMITTEE AND I'M
HAPPY TO SUPPORT IT HERE FOR FINAL PASSAGE AS WELL.
>> IT WAS ABUNDANTLY CLEAR FROM THE TECHNICAL ADVISORY
COMMITTEE REPORT THAT WE NEED TO DO ALL THAT WE CAN TO MOVE
THE NEEDLE ON FEASIBILITY IF WE WANT TO HAVE ANY CHANCE OF THE
CITY TO BUILD THE HOUSING REQUIRED TO MEET DEMAND.
>> THE INCREASE IN THE THRESHOLD FOR INCLUSIONARY FEES
FROM TEN UNITS TO 25 UNITS IN PARTICULAR WILL HELP WITH
THE EXACT KIND OF MIDSIZED PROJECTS ENCOURAGED BY THE
FAMILY ZONING PLAN WHEN PAIRED WITH THE HOUSING TRUST FUND
EXPANSION SUPERVISOR MELGAR HAS PROPOSED THESE POLICIES GO A
LONG WAY IN HELPING US MEET OUR PRODUCTION GOALS AROUND
SUBSIDIZED AFFORDABLE HOUSING WHILE ALSO STEMMING THE TIDE OF
RISING RENTS FOR RESIDENTS ON THE OPEN MARKET.
>> AS WAS NOTED, THIS WAS DONE AS AN EXCHANGE ON THE
RECOMMENDATION BY THE TAC BETWEEN THE HOUSING TRUST FUND
AND INCLUSIONARY REQUIREMENTS AND HAD AMENDMENTS MOVE FORWARD
TO ACTUALLY COUPLE THOSE MEASURES.
I WAS SUPPORTIVE. AS FOR SUPERVISOR FIELDERS
AMENDMENT I WILL ALSO BE VOTING IN SUPPORT.
>> WE AS A BOARD SHOULD RESPECT SUPERVISOR PREROGATIVE AND I
TRUST HER TO KNOW HOW TO BALANCE HER SHARED PRIORITY
POLICY GOALS WITH THE FEEDBACK THAT SHE IS GETTING FROM HER
CONSTITUENTS IN THE MISSION. THE NEW RATES ARE STILL A
REDUCTION FROM THE CURRENT BASELINE AND WILL ENCOURAGE
MORE AFFORDABLE HOUSING THAT IS BEING BUILT AS A RESULT OF THE
INCLUSIONARY REQUIREMENT TO BE BUILT IN THE MISSION
REPRESENTING THE OPPORTUNITY FOR RESIDENTS WHO WANT TO LEAVE
SUBSTANDARD OR OVERCROWDED CONDITIONS BUT DON'T WANT TO
LEAVE THE NEIGHBORHOOD. >> I APPRECIATE THAT THIS
AMENDMENT REFLECTS THE CONVERSATIONS A SUPERVISOR
FIELDER HAS HAD WITH MISSION RESIDENTS ABOUT HOW TO ADVANCE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND THEIR NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> AND I'M HAPPY TO SUPPORT IT .
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
PRESIDENT MANDELL MAN. I WANTED TO EXPLAIN MY
CO-SPONSORSHIP OF THIS ITEM AND YOU KNOW ADDRESS A COUPLE
OF CONCERNS HAVE COME UP FROM SOME OF MY COLLEAGUES
AND MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC FOR NON HOUSING NERDS.
>> THE WAY WE SET THE INCLUSIONARY RATE IN SAN
FRANCISCO IS THE SAME AS THE REST OF CALIFORNIA.
IT HAS TO BE BASED ON A NEXUS STUDY.
THIS IS IN SUPPORTING OUR DECISION MANY YEARS AGO AND AT
THE NEXUS STUDY REALLY JUST IS A CALCULATION THAT LOOKS LIKE
HOW MUCH IT COSTS TO BUILD A UNIT AND HOW MUCH A FAMILY OF
LOW INCOME CAN AFFORD. AND AS COSTS GO UP, YOU KNOW
THAT GETS WIDER THAT THAT GAP GETS WIDER AND OUR INCLUSIONARY
FEE GETS LOWER AND WHEN COSTS SHRINK, WHEN IT COSTS LESS TO
BUILD A UNIT, YOU KNOW THAT MEANS THAT THE GAP GETS
SMALLER. WE DON'T HAVE TO SUBSIDIZE AS
MUCH AND THEN WE CAN, YOU KNOW, GET MORE FOR OUR MONEY.
SO THE WAY THAT WE DO IT IN SAN FRANCISCO IS WE APPOINT A BUNCH
OF EXPERTS WITH THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS A BUNCH A POINT THE
TECHNICAL ADVISORY COMMITTEE AND IT'S A SCIENCE THEY CRUNCH
THE NUMBERS BUT IT'S ALSO A LITTLE BIT OF ART BECAUSE WE
GET NONPROFIT DEVELOPERS FOR PROFIT DEVELOPERS.
THEY GET IN A ROOM, THEY LOOK AT THE NUMBERS AND THEY
NEGOTIATE AND WE ARE REQUIRED TO DO THIS EVERY THREE YEARS
BECAUSE THE MARKET CHANGES RIGHT?
>> THE COSTS GO UP THEN THEY GO DOWN THE AREA.
MEDIAN INCOME CONSISTENTLY HAS GONE UP BUT YOU KNOW WHEN TIMES
ARE BOOMING THE MEDIAN INCOME GETS SKEWED BY PEOPLE MAKING
LOTS OF MONEY. SO THOSE THAT FORMULA THAT THAT
SORT OF SCIENCE PART OF THE NUMBERS CHANGES AND EVERY THREE
YEARS THE PEOPLE IN THE TECHNICAL ADVISORY COMMITTEE
GET TOGETHER, THEY CRUNCH THE NUMBERS AND THEY COME UP WITH
THE RECOMMENDATION THAT WE THEN VOTE ON BUT WE CAN VOTE ON IT
AT ANY TIME. WE JUST HAVE THIS BACKUP THAT
IS NOT JUST GOOD PRACTICE IT IS LEGALLY REQUIRED AND IF WE
DON'T DO IT, IF WE IGNORE THAT GAP THAT IS IN THE MARKET IT
RISKS THE INTEGRITY, THE LEGAL INTEGRITY OF THE ENTIRE PROGRAM
NOT JUST RIGHT NOW WHEN THE MARKET IS FLUCTUATING BUT
PERMANENTLY FOR OUR CITY. SO I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE
THAT WE UNDERSTAND THAT BECAUSE WE HAVE TO DO IT.
SO NOW AS IT RELATES TO THE HOUSING TRUST FUND BECAUSE WE
SET THE INCLUSIONARY RATE EVERY THREE YEARS WE ARE ALSO PUTTING
TOGETHER THE HOUSING TRUST FUND FOR 30 YEARS.
IT IS A 30 YEAR COMMITMENT THAT IS PERMANENT 30 YEARS VERSUS A
THREE YEAR RESETTING OF THE FEE BASED ON THE MARKET.
SO WHAT HAS HAPPENED IF WE LOOK BACK AT THE LAST THREE YEARS IS
THAT 0% OF ZERO IS ZERO. IN THE PAST THREE YEARS WE HAVE
GOTTEN ZERO IN INCLUSIONARY FEES.
THIS PAST YEAR WE ACTUALLY GOT LESS THAN THAT.
WE GOT 137,000 OR SOME LESS BECAUSE SOMEBODY ASKED FOR
THEIR MONEY BACK THEY HAD PUT IN THEY HAVE SAID I'M GOING TO
BUILD AND THEN THEY'RE LIKE CHANGE THEIR MIND NEVER MIND SO
THEY CAN ASK FOR THEIR MONEY BACK BECAUSE THAT'S THE WAY WE
WROTE THE LAW. SO WHAT ARE WE REALLY GIVING UP
? YOU KNOW, IN EXCHANGE FOR A 30
YEAR PERMANENT SOURCE OF FUNDING THAT ALLOWS US TO BOND
AND YOU KNOW, INVEST IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING GIVEN
THAT THE PAST THREE YEARS WE'VE BEEN AT ZERO AND AT ZERO BMR
UNITS. SO I JUST WANT TO POINT OUT
THAT 5% OF 100 IS FIVE AND IT'S MORE THAN ZERO.
SO WE ARE HOPING THAT IN THE NEXT THREE YEARS DESPITE THE
TARIFFS COSTING US HIGHER GAS PRICES, HIGHER PRICES FOR GOOD,
MORE INFLATION WE NOW HAVE THE HIGHEST INFLATION APOLOGY SEVEN
COUNTRIES BY THE WAY WE CAN DO NOTHING ABOUT THAT BUT WE CAN
DO SOMETHING ABOUT THIS. IT'S ONE OF THE COST FACTORS
FOR BUILDING HOUSING. SO WE ARE HOPING THAT THIS WILL
INCENTIVIZE MARKET RATE HOUSING BEING BUILT IN THAT ZONES THAT
WE HAVE JUST ALLOWED IN AREAS THAT NOW WILL HAVE ROOM FOR
RENTAL HOUSING. I THINK THAT WOULD BE A GOOD
THING. IT WILL CREATE JOBS, IT WILL
CREATE NEEDED HOUSING THAT WE HAVE COMMITTED TO THE STATE
AND THE ACTION THAT WE JUST TOOK WILL ALSO PROVIDE
FINANCING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING WHICH IS HALF OF OUR
OBLIGATION TO THE STATE IN TERMS OF THE PRODUCTION OF
UNITS. SO I JUST WANTED TO EXPLAIN MY
THINKING IN PUTTING MY NAME ON THIS.
I DON'T LOVE LOWERING THE INCLUSIONARY PERCENTAGE.
I THOUGHT FOR IT I FOUGHT FOR THE PROGRAM.
I WROTE A LOT OF THE POLICIES AND PROCEDURES OF THE PROGRAM
BUT THIS IS THE MOMENT THAT WE'RE IN RIGHT NOW AND IT IS A
TEMPORARY MOMENT. SO IN THREE YEARS WHEN OUR
ECONOMY RECOVERS, WHEN WE NO LONGER HAVE A REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENT THAT IS MAKING EVERYTHING MORE EXPENSIVE
IN OUR COUNTRY AND THINGS GO BACK UP, I HAVE EVERY
EXPECTATION THAT THE INCLUSIONARY RATE WILL BE RESET
HIGHER BY A FUTURE BODY OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THAT
WILL SIT ON TOP OF THE HOUSING TRUST FUND THAT HAS BEEN
EXPANDED SO THAT WE HAVE BOTH. AND SO I WANTED TO JUST EXPLAIN
THAT AND ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT FOR THIS.
I THINK IT MAKES SENSE AT THIS MOMENT IT IS A TRADEOFF BUT THE
MATH SUPPORTS IT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN.
COLLEAGUES, I WILL RESPECTFULLY BE VOTING NO ON THE PROPOSED
AMENDMENT WHILE WE ULTIMATELY HAVE THE FINAL POLICY DECISION
OVER OUR INCLUSIONARY RATES. WE GENERALLY ENTRUST THE BULK
OF THE POLICYMAKING WORK ON OUR INCLUSIONARY RATES TO A GROUP
OF EXPERTS FROM THE DEVELOPMENT AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING
COMMUNITY. THEY LOOK AT THE DATA
AND PROVIDE US WITH RECOMMENDATIONS.
AS LAND USE CHAIR MELGAR JUST EXPLAINED.
AND THIS TIME AROUND THE NUMBERS SHOWED THAT OUR RATES
ARE TOO HIGH AND IN FACT THE REPORT SHOWED THAT THE EVEN
ZERO IS INFEASIBLE. WHILE I FRANKLY HAVE
RESERVATIONS EVEN ABOUT 5%, I RESPECT THE PROCESS THAT LED TO
THAT RECOMMENDATION AND I UNDERSTAND THE DESIRE AND THE
IMPORTANCE OF HAVING A NUMBER THAT'S GREATER THAN ZERO.
BUT I DO BELIEVE WE NEED TO TRUST THE MATH.
I DON'T BELIEVE WE SHOULD SINGLE OUT NEIGHBORHOODS
AND FREEZE THEM OUT FOR NEW HOUSING MARKET RATE OR
AFFORDABLE. IT TAKES TIME TO SEE THE
EFFECTS OF THESE CHANGES AND THAT'S WHY THE TAX PROCESS
HAPPENS EVERY THREE YEARS. I BELIEVE WE NEED TO LET THIS
POLICY PLAY OUT SO I WILL RESPECTFULLY NOT SUPPORT THE
AMENDMENT ON THE PRINCIPLE THAT IT RISKS MOVING THE LEGISLATION
FURTHER FROM ITS GOAL OF MAKING HOUSING PRODUCTION FEASIBLE.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN. THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
COLLEAGUE IN THE FACE OF WIDENING IN THAT INEQUITY
AND THE HISTORIC AND ONGOING DISPLACEMENT OF WORKING CLASS
COMMUNITIES AND COMMUNITIES OF COLOR, THE CITY FACES AN
EXTRAORDINARY IMPERATIVE TO FACILITATE HOUSING OPPORTUNITY.
>> THIS INCLUDES PERMITTING MORE HOUSING FACILITATING ITS
CONSTRUCTION, ENSURING AFFORDABILITY AND PREVENTING
FURTHER DISPLACEMENT. >> I WANT TO SUPPORT DEVELOPERS
TO PRODUCE NEW HOUSING AND I WANT TO MAXIMIZING AFFORDABLE
HOUSING. AND THAT'S WHY I HAVE SERIOUS
CONCERNS ABOUT THIS LEGISLATION.
IT REQUIRES US TO CHOOSE ONE OVER THE OTHER RATHER THAN
ADVANCE BOTH COLLECTIVELY. IT IS REALLY A SAD DAY WHERE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING REQUIREMENTS ARE REFRAMED THAT OBSTACLES TO
PRODUCTION RATHER THAN A REQUEST FOR IT.
>> IF WE BELIEVE THAT A MORE AFFORDABLE SAN FRANCISCO IT'S
OUR GOAL THEN WE MUST RECOGNIZE THAT AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS PART
OF THE COSTS OF DOING BUSINESS FOR NEW DEVELOPMENT.
>> WHAT I HEAR FROM PROPONENTS OF THIS LEGISLATION IS THAT IT
GETS SHUFFLED IN THE GROUND. HOWEVER, I'M NOT CONVINCED IN A
BLATANT ANALYSIS CONDUCTED IN MAY OF THIS YEAR FOUND THAT
PREVIOUS RICH DUCTION DID NOT RESULT IN SIGNIFICANT IMPACT ON
HOUSING PRODUCTION. >> THE TECHNICAL ADVISORY
COMMITTEES OWN REPORT CONFIRMS THAT THERE IS NO RAY OF
INCLUSIONARY HOUSING THAT IS FEASIBLE UNDER CURRENT MARKET
CONDITION. AND BOTH ANALYSIS CONFIRM THAT
MACRO ECONOMIC FACTORS SUCH AS LABOR MATERIALS AND FINANCING
COSTS ARE THE REAL DRIVERS OF DEVELOPMENT ACTIVITY.
I UNDERSTAND THAT THIS LEGISLATION IS PART OF A
PACKAGE BUT PLACING THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING TRUST FUND
ON THE BALLOT AND APPROVING IT ARE TWO VERY DIFFERENT THINGS.
THERE'S NO GUARANTEE THAT THE FUNDING WILL BE APPROVED.
THIS IS AN UNNECESSARY LEAP OF FAITH AND I AND I BELIEVE IT IS
DISHONEST TO ADVANCE THIS LEGISLATION WITHOUT A GUARANTEE
THAT THE FUNDING WILL BE DEDICATED.
>> AND I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT THE INCLUSIONARY FRAMEWORK
. IT'S ALSO ABOUT SOMETHING MUCH
BIGGER THAT IT'S AT THE HEART OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> WE CARE SO MUCH ABOUT THE GOAL OF INCLUSIONARY SIMPLE TO
ENSURE THAT NEW DEVELOPMENT DID NOT CONTINUE TO ECHO THE RACIST
EXCLUSION OF HISTORIC DEVELOPMENT PATTERNS.
INCLUSIONARY REQUIREMENTS ARE THE SINGLE MOST IMPORTANT TO TO
FORCE A MIXED INCOME COMMUNITIES.
WITHOUT IT WE FACILITATE A SAN FRANCISCO THAT ONLY BECOMES
FURTHER SECOND GRADE IT AND I WILL NOT BE SUPPORTING THIS
LEGISLATION IN ITS CURRENT FORM.
BUT I DO WANT TO SPEAK TO SUPPORT SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S
AMENDMENT AND I THINK IN THE MISSION DISTRICT REMAINS ONE OF
THE HIGHEST DISPLACEMENT RISK AREA.
AND IT THIS PRINCIPLE ALREADY EXISTS AND IN THE LEGISLATION
WOULD HIRE OFF OFFSITE AND FEE RAISE IN PRIORITY EQUITY
COMMUNITIES AND THIS NEIGHBORHOOD SPECIFICALLY
TEARING IS JUST RELEVANT FOR THEIR ACTUAL INCLUSIONARY RATE
. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT.
>> I AM A FIRM BELIEVER THAT IN THE SUPPLY OF DEMAND IS THAT
WE NEED THAT SUPPLY OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING BECAUSE WE
ARE DEMANDING AFFORDABLE HOUSING OR REALLY HOUSING THAT
PEOPLE CAN AFFORD. AND THAT'S WHAT WE HAVE TO
BUILD. LOWERING THE INCLUSIONARY
REQUIREMENT ONCE MORE WE ACTUALLY DID THIS TWO YEARS
AGO. WE HAVE SOME PARAMETERS FOR IT
THAT'S INCLUDING LOWERING THE INCLUSIONARY PERCENTAGE FOR FOR
THE PROJECT THAT'S ALREADY CURRENTLY IN THE PIPELINE.
IT SEEMS LIKE IT WASN'T CLEARLY WITH THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE
ANALYST REPORT THAT WE RECENTLY COMMISSION HAD INDICATED TO US
THAT LOWERING THE INCLUSIONARY PERCENTAGE ISN'T THE MAJOR
FACTOR IS SOME FACTOR IS SOME INTENT PROVIDE SOME INCENTIVE.
SO OVERALL I AM NOT INCLINED TO AGAIN TO LOWER IT BUT I AM
AGAIN ALSO INCLINED TO SUPPORT SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S
SUGGESTIONS. IDENTIFYING AND RECOGNIZING
THAT MISSION HAS THE GREATEST GENTRIFICATION A RATE OF
GENTRIFICATION AND DISPLACEMENT AND WOULD LIKE TO INCREASE IT.
I WILL ONLY BE VOTING IN SUPPORT THE ENTIRE
LEGISLATION SHOULD SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S AMENDMENTS IS
ADOPTED. SO IN ANOTHER YEAR I WILL ONLY
BE VOTING. I WILL NOT BE VOTING IN SUPPORT
THE LEGISLATION AS IT CURRENTLY AT 6% FOR LOW INCOME AND 2% FOR
THE MODERATE INCOME FOR RENTAL AND OWNERSHIP.
BUT I WILL BE VOTING IN SUPPORT OF IT SHOULD THIS BODY ADOPT
SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S PROPOSED AMENDMENTS REQUIRING 8% ON
SITES IN THE MISSION AREA PLAN AREA.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG COLLEAGUES SAN
FRANCISCO IS A AND THEY HOUSING PRODUCTION CRISIS.
OVER THE PAST SEVERAL YEARS CONSTRUCTION COSTS HAVE CLIMBED
INTEREST RATES HAVE INCREASED. FINANCING HAS BECOME MORE
DIFFICULT AND HOUSING PRODUCTION HAS SLOWED
DRAMATICALLY. THE CITY'S OWN TECHNICAL
ADVISORY COMMITTEE CONCLUDED THAT OUR EXISTING INCLUSIONARY
REQUIREMENTS HAVE BECOME A SIGNIFICANT BARRIER TO NEW
RESIDENTIAL DEVELOPMENT UNDER TODAY'S ECONOMIC CONDITIONS.
WE CANNOT COLLECT AFFORDABLE HOUSING FEES FROM PROJECTS THAT
ARE NEVER BUILT. WE CANNOT REQUIRE BELOW MARKET
RATE UNITS AND BUILDINGS THAT NEVER LEAVE THE DRAWING BOARD.
THIS LEGISLATION RECOGNIZES TODAY'S ECONOMIC REALITY WHILE
PRESERVING OUR LONG TERM COMMITMENT TO AFFORDABLE
HOUSING ADJUSTS INCLUSIONARY REQUIREMENTS, REDUCES CERTAIN
IMPACT FEES AND PROVIDES GREATER FLEXIBILITY SO PROJECTS
CAN ONCE AGAIN PENCIL OUT AND MOVE FORWARD.
IT ALSO MAINTAINS THE CITY'S COMMITMENT TO REVISIT THESE
REQUIREMENTS THROUGH THE TECHNICAL ADVISORY COMMITTEE.
AS MARKET CONDITIONS CHANGE, GOOD HOUSING POLICY REQUIRES US
TO BE PRINCIPLED BUT IT ALSO REQUIRES US TO BE PRAGMATIC
AND RESPONSIBLE. IF WE WANT MORE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING TOMORROW, WE NEED MORE HOUSING.
TODAY THIS ORDINANCE HELPS PUT SAN FRANCISCO BACK ON THAT
PATH. >> THANK YOU.
AND DID YOU WANT TO SPEAK TO ROSE MILNER?
ALL RIGHT. IF NOBODY ELSE IS IN THE QUEUE
,I WILL JUST WEIGH IN WITH A COUPLE REFLECTIONS.
>> WHEN I WAS IN GRAD WHEN I WAS YOUNG, WHEN I WAS IN GRAD
SCHOOL THE CONVERSATION ABOUT IMPACT FEES WAS VERY MUCH ABOUT
THE WAYS IN WHICH THOSE FEES COULD MAKE DEVELOPMENT PAY FOR
ITSELF. IN A POST PROP 13 WORLD WHERE
LOCAL GOVERNMENTS COULD NOT OTHER WOULD NOT OTHERWISE OVER
TIME BE ABLE TO COLLECT THE PROPERTY TAX THEY NEEDED TO
PROVIDE THE AMENITIES THAT WOULD BE NEEDED FOR THE NEW
HOUSING IN THE SUBSEQUENT 500 YEARS SINCE I WAS IN GRAD
SCHOOL. >> THE CIRCUMSTANCES
IN CALIFORNIA HAVE CHANGED AND WE HAVE A COLOSSAL SHORTAGE
OF HOUSING THAT IS CRUSHING, THAT IS CRUSHING OUR RESIDENTS
AND IS BAD FOR OUR ECONOMY IS BAD FOR OUR PEOPLE.
>> AND SO I HAVE BEEN PERSUADED THAT THE GOOD OF GETTING MORE
HOUSING IS WORTH THE HARM OF REDUCING OUR IMPACT FEES.
AND I TAKE SERIOUSLY THE POINT THAT SUPERVISOR MELGAR HAS MADE
AND THAT A LOT OF PEOPLE HAVE MADE WHICH IS THAT A LARGER
PERCENTAGE OF ZERO IS STILL ZERO.
>> NOW I DO THINK THAT SINCE THE TAX ANALYSIS SHOWS THAT
THAT THAT THE 5% DOES NOT CREATE FEASIBLE PROJECTS I'M
NOT INCLINED TO SUPPORT A RATE THAT IS HIGHER THAN THAT EVEN
FOR A NEIGHBORHOOD THAT IS VERY SPECIAL AND AND HAS A HISTORY
OF DISPLACEMENT. SO THAT THAT IS MY THOSE ARE MY
THOUGHTS. MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU CALL THE
ROLL ON THE AMENDMENT ON THE AMENDMENT TO ITEM 39?
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER. SAUTER NO.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL NO. SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG NO. SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY NO.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD. I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN NO
MIDDLEMAN NO AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I THERE ARE SIX
EYES AND FIVE NOS WITH SUPERVISORS SADR, CHERYL WONG,
DORSEY AND MANDEL MEN VOTING NO.
>> AND THE MOTION PASSES. >> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE AMENDED ITEM ON ITEM 39 AS
AMENDED AS AMENDED SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON I WILTON EYES SUPERVISOR
WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN I MENTAL
BEAN I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I THERE ARE 11 EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING BUT
WAS THAT TONIGHT SO CAN WE UNANIMOUS IN THE VOTES IN THE
VOTE UH HOW DO WE DO THIS MADAM CLERK IS THIS MOTION TO RESCIND
THE VOTE? NO.
THE SECOND SIX VOTES WILL RESCIND THE GREAT MOTION.
THERE'S BEEN A MOTION RECEIVED A VOTE.
>> IT HAS BEEN SECOND BY SUPERVISOR CHAN.
>> CAN WE TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION?
WITHOUT OBJECTION. THE MOTION PASSES.
>> ALL RIGHT. MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE AMENDED ITEM AGAIN ON ITEM 39 AS
AMENDED SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDEL
MAN I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I THERE ARE TEN EYES
AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON VOTING NO AND THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 40 ITEM 40 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MAYOR'S
NOMINATION FOR THE REAPPOINTMENT OF AS A ZELINA
USE UP FORGIVE MY PRONUNCIATION IF I'M PRONOUNCING IT
INCORRECTLY TO THE SANITATION AND STREETS COMMISSION TERM
ENDING JULY FIRST, 2013 PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 40
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDELL
MAN I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I THERE ARE 11 EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
AND MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 41 YES BUT I'LL FIRST STATE ITEMS 41 AND 42
WERE CONSIDERED BY THE PUBLIC SAFETY AND NEIGHBORHOOD
SERVICES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON THURSDAY JULY 9TH
AND BOTH WERE FORWARDED AS COMMITTEE REPORTS ITEM 41 THIS
ITEM WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED BUT WITH THE SAME TITLE IT
READS ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO STATE
THAT IT IS CITY POLICY TO EXPAND THE AVAILABILITY OF SITE
BASED PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING THAT PROHIBITS ONSITE
ILLICIT DRUG USE AMONG RESIDENTS TO MEET THE TO MEET
THE DEMAND OF PEOPLE EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS WHO
PREFER SUCH A RESIDENTIAL OPTION TO REQUIRE THAT THE CITY
FUNDING FOR NEW SITE BASED PASSAGE FOR PEOPLE EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS BE USED FOR DRUG FREE PASSAGE EXCEPT WHERE
OPERATION OF THE HOUSING AS DRUG FREE PASSAGE WOULD
CONFLICT WITH STANDARDS IMPOSED BY LAW OR BY A CONDITION OF
OTHER FUNDING WHERE THE FUNDING IS FOR NEW CONSTRUCTION OR THE
BOARD HAS WAIVED THE FUNDING REQUIREMENT BASED ON SPECIFIC
FINDINGS TO REQUIRE THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
AND SUPPORT OF HOUSING TO SURVEY RESIDENTS OF SITE BASED
SEARCH TO ASSESS THEIR INTEREST IN LIVING IN EITHER DRUG
TOLERANT PASSAGE OR DRUG FREE PASSAGE AND TO REPORT ON THE
SURVEY FINDINGS IN STAGES STRATEGIES TO MEET PCH
RESIDENTS DEMANDS AND TO REQUIRE H S H TO ADOPT RULES
AND REGULATIONS ESTABLISHING STANDARDS AND PROTOCOLS FOR
EVICTIONS FROM CITY FUNDED DRUG FREE HOUSING.
>> CHAIR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
>> COLLEAGUES, AS YOU PROBABLY KNOW THIS LEGISLATION HAS BEEN
A WORK IN PROGRESS AND A LABOR OF LOVE OF MINE FOR MORE THAN
TWO YEARS NOW. I WANT TO THANK ALL MY
CO-SPONSORS ESPECIALLY BOARD PRESIDENT MANDELL MAN WHO HAS
BEEN OUR ORIGINAL THOUGHT PARTNER FROM THE START.
I ASSUME I SPEAK FOR ALL OF MY CO-SPONSORS WHEN I ACKNOWLEDGE
HOW WORTHWHILE IT HAS BEEN TO DEMONSTRATE AN ABUNDANCE OF
COLLABORATION EVEN IF IT TOOK A LOT LONGER IN AN EVOLVING
POLICY LANDSCAPE AT THE STATE AND FEDERAL LEVELS.
WE HAVE HONORED ALL GOOD FAITH REQUESTS TO FIND COMMON GROUND
WITH ADVOCATES WHEREVER POSSIBLE.
I'M PROUD OF THE WAY WE WORKED COLLABORATIVELY WITH VARIOUS
INTERESTS COLLEAGUES HRH THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND BOTH THE
BREED AND LORI ADMINISTRATIONS. WHILE THERE WAS PROBABLY NEVER
A SCENARIO TO WIN UNANIMOUS SUPPORT FOR THIS, I THINK WE
FORGED A BETTER LEGISLATIVE PROPOSAL ONE THAT'LL MAKE MUCH
NEEDED IF MODEST PROGRESS ON DRUG FREE PASSAGE OF OPTIONS
FOR THOSE WHO CHOOSE THEM. THIS LEGISLATION IS AN
INCREMENTAL APPROACH. IT ENSURES THAT ONLY NEW CITY
FUNDED PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING WILL PROHIBIT ILLICIT
DRUG USE ON SITE. IT WILL NOT AFFECT STATE FUNDED
PCH. IT WILL NOT APPLY TO NEW
CONSTRUCTION CURRENTLY IN THE PIPELINE.
AND IT WILL NOT CHANGE A SINGLE EXISTING DRUG TOLERANT AGE
BUILDING OR MODEL THE DRUG FREE LEASE PROVISION WE'RE PROPOSING
TO ADD IS LEGALLY IDENTICAL TO ALL STANDARD RESIDENTIAL LEASES
HERE IN CALIFORNIA. THE SAME LEASES THAT ALREADY
COVER MORE THAN 240,000 SAN FRANCISCANS WHO DON'T LIVE
IN PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING.
THIS IS NOT SOBER HOUSING. IT IS NOT RECOVERY HOUSING.
IT DOES NOT PROHIBIT ALCOHOL OR MARIJUANA OR MEDICALLY ASSISTED
TREATMENT. I ALSO WANT TO BE CLEAR ABOUT
WHOM THIS LEGISLATION IS FOR. IT RESPONDS TO REAL NEEDS OF
PCH RESIDENTS THEMSELVES PEOPLE WHO MAY OR MAY NOT BE
IN RECOVERY BUT WHO SIMPLY WANT TO LIVE IN A DRUG FREE
RESIDENTIAL COMMUNITY. FAMILIES, SENIORS AND OTHERS
WHO PEOPLE WHO DESERVE THE CHOICE OF A DRUG FREE OPTION
FOR ANY REASON THAT COVERS ALL OTHER RESIDENTIAL TENANTS
IN SAN FRANCISCO WITH ONE EXCEPTION AND THAT'S A 42 UNIT
SITE AT 1174 FOLSOM STREET IN MY DISTRICT.
WE CURRENTLY HAVE NO DRUG FREE OPTIONS OPTIONS IN OUR CITY
FUNDED SYSTEM. THIS LEGISLATION AT ITS CORE IS
ABOUT GIVING PCH RESIDENTS A CHOICE.
IMPORTANTLY, RESIDENTS WHO MAY CHOOSE DRUG FREE PCH ARE MAKING
AN INTENTIONAL CHOICE ONE THEY WOULD BE OPTING INTO A
COMMUNITY AS WITH AN ILLICIT DRUG FREE RULE AND MAKING A
COMMITMENT TO ABIDE BY IT. THAT INTENTIONALITY IS THE
FOUNDATION THAT THIS POLICY IS BUILT ON.
IT'S ABOUT RESPECTING THE CHOICES OF THE RESIDENTS
THEMSELVES AND ALSO ALONG WITH THAT HONORING THAT THE
DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF HOUSING WILL
HAVE A NEED TO MANAGE AND ENFORCE IT BASED ON WHAT WE
HAVE SEEN AT 1174 FOLSOM AND WHAT WE'VE ALSO LEARNED
FROM DRUG FREE PCH PROVIDERS IN THE STATE OF OREGON.
WE SHOULD EXPECT EVICTIONS UNDER THIS ORDINANCE TO BE
EXCEEDINGLY RARE. THE SELF-SELECTION OF RESIDENTS
WHO VOLUNTARILY OPT INTO DRUG FREE RESIDENTIAL COMMUNITIES
LARGELY SOLVES IN ADVANCE FOR SCENARIOS THAT INVOLVE
PERSISTENT DRUG RELAPSES OR HABITUAL RETURNS TO USE.
STILL, EVEN THOUGH THEY MAY BE VERY RARE.
EDGE CASE SCENARIOS EXIST AND THIS LEGISLATION MUST
ADDRESS THEM. GIVEN THAT RELOCATIONS MAY BE
NECESSARY TO PROTECT THE INTEGRITY OF DRUG FREE
RESIDENTIAL COMMUNITIES, NO RESIDENT OF DRUG FREE PCH WILL
EVER BE EVICTED FOR A SINGLE RELAPSE.
AND CRITICALLY WE'VE BUILT A ROBUST PROCESS IN THIS
LEGISLATION THAT REQUIRES HCA TO OFFER ALTERNATIVE HOUSING OR
SHELTER TOGETHER WITH SERVICES BEFORE AN EVICTION CAN EVEN
TAKE PLACE. FINALLY, THIS ORDINANCE
PROVIDES FOR A PARTICIPATORY AND INCLUSIVE RULE MAKING
PROCESS. COLLEAGUES AND ADVOCATES WILL
HAVE AN AMPLE OPPORTUNITY TO HELP SHAPE RULES AND POLICIES
THAT BEST SERVE RESIDENTS. AS THIS LEGISLATION IS
IMPLEMENTED. NOW HAVING SAID THAT, I AM
AWARE THAT THERE IS INTEREST FROM COLLEAGUES IN AMENDMENTS
AND I AM ON BOARD WITH ONE THAT WILL FURTHER COMMIT THIS
LEGISLATION TO THE GOAL OF AVOIDING EVICTIONS.
AND ACCORDINGLY I WOULD LIKE TO MOVE AN AMENDMENT TO ADD
EVICTIONS AND TO PAGE EIGHT LINE 24 SO THAT THAT SUB
SUBSECTION NOW READS THREE IN COLLABORATION WITH THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH MAKING GOOD AND MAKING A GOOD
FAITH EFFORT TO ACCOMMODATE SUCH RESIDENTS HOUSING
AND SERVICE NEEDS WHEN IDENTIFYING ALTERNATIVE
PLACEMENTS WITH THE GOAL OF AVOIDING EVICTIONS AND RETURNS
TO HOMELESSNESS. NOW IT'S ALSO MY UNDERSTANDING
THAT THERE IS INTEREST IN AN ADDITIONAL AMENDMENT THAT WOULD
REMOVE SHELTERS AS A RELOCATION OPTION.
I WILL RESPECTFULLY NOT BE SUPPORTING THAT AMENDMENT.
AND ALTHOUGH I'M NOT FOR PHILOSOPHICALLY OPPOSED TO IT
AFTER CONSULTING WITH THE MAYOR'S POLICY DIRECTOR CONOR
MODY WHO HAS BEEN WORKING CLOSELY WITH HSA ON HOW THIS
LEGISLATION WOULD BE ADMINISTERED AND ENFORCED IF
ENACTED, I'M TOLD THAT REMOVING SHELTERS AS A RELOCATION OPTION
COULD RISK SABOTAGING HCA TO HIS ABILITY TO MAINTAIN THE
INTEGRITY OF A DRUG FREE COMMUNITY.
THAT OBVIOUSLY WOULD RUN COUNTER TO THE CORE INTENT OF
THIS LEGISLATION. IN THE EVENT THAT A COMPARABLE
UNIT IS NOT AVAILABLE, I BELIEVE WE NEED TO HAVE THE
OPTION OF SHELTER. THAT'S WHAT HCA AND MR. MOTI
HAVE INFORMED ME. KEEPING ALL OPTIONS OPEN FOR
THESE CASES WILL HELP TO SERVE OUR SHARED GOAL OF AVOIDING
RETURNS TO HOMELESSNESS AS A MAKER.
I THINK WE SHOULD BE SENSITIVE TO NOT BEING OVERLY
PRESCRIPTIVE IN HOW WE LEGISLATE TO AVOID SETTING OUR
DEPARTMENTS UP FOR FAILURE. I WANT TO GIVE HCA TO THE
FLEXIBILITY IT NEEDS TO MAKE DRUG FREE HOUSING SUCCESSFUL.
I AM CONFIDENT THAT THE SPECIFICS ON HOUSING OFFERS
EVICTIONS AND BROADER PROGRAM COMPONENTS CAN BE ADDRESSED
IN THE RULEMAKING PROCESS. I HAVE SPOKEN WITH THE INCOMING
HCA DIRECTOR MIKE LEVINE AND HE HAS ASSURED ME THAT THE RULE
MAKING PROCESS WILL BE PARTICIPATORY AND INCLUSIVE AS
THIS LEGISLATIVE PROCESS HAS BEEN.
SO I DO WANT TO THANK THE LEADERS, ORGANIZATIONS,
ACADEMICS WHO SUPPORTED THIS LEGISLATION.
TWO OF THEM ARE GIANTS IN THE DRUG POLICY REALM.
KEITH HUMPHREYS, WHO SERVED AS PRESIDENT OBAMA'S WHITE HOUSE
ADVISER. AND A LEMKE WHO SERVES AS
DIRECTOR OF ADDICTION MEDICINE AT STANFORD.
THANKS AS WELL TO MY BROTHERS AND SISTERS FROM THE RECOVERY
COMMUNITY ESPECIALLY RECOVERY COMMUNITY ADVOCATES THERE ARE
COATES AND RICHARD BEALL WHO ARE CO-FOUNDERS OF BROTHERS
AGAINST DRUGS. SIMILARLY CEDRIC AKBAR, STEVE
ADAMI, TOM WOLFE, BRANDON CLARKE, AMBER RICHMOND AMONG
OTHERS. POSITIVE DIRECTIONS EQUALS
CHANGE MOTHERS AGAINST DRUG ADDICTION AND DEATHS THE
SALVATION ARMY, BAY AREA COUNCIL AND THE AMERICAN
ADDICTION RECOVERY ASSOCIATION ESPECIALLY AMERICA FITO WHO IS
A MEMBER OF ITS BOARD OF GOVERNORS.
AND WITH THAT I WANT TO THANK ALL MY COLLEAGUES.
THANK THANK YOU FOR HEARING ME OUT AND WORKING WITH ME ON THIS
. >> I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT
ON THE AMENDMENT AND ALSO ON THE LEGISLATION.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY HAS MADE A MOTION TO AMEND THE
LEGISLATION. >> IT HAS BEEN SECONDED BY
SUPERVISOR CHERYL. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THINGS
PRESIDENT MIDDLEMEN. >> COLLEAGUES FIRST I JUST WANT
TO SAY I DO BELIEVE IN HAVING MORE ABSTINENT OR SOBER HOUSING
AS AN OPTION FOR UNHOUSED PEOPLE WHO ARE IN RECOVERY FROM
SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER. SO I SUPPORT THAT SPIRIT OF THE
LEGISLATION AND I SUPPORT THE PROVISION OF THIS LEGISLATION
AND THAT I THINK SMARTLY ADMINISTERS A SURVEY OF
PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING RESIDENTS THE AIM OF WHICH IS
TO ASSESS THEIR INTERESTS IN ABSTINENT HOUSING.
FOR THAT I THINK SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR TAKING ON THIS WORK.
>> HOWEVER, I JUST FIRST WANT TO SAY I THINK THE TERMINOLOGY
IN THIS LEGISLATION IS PROBLEMATIC.
>> I'M NOT SURE HOW BIFURCATING PERMANENT HOUSING INTO DRUG
TOLERANT VERSUS DRUG FREE HOUSING PAST REVIEW AT THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AS THIS KIND OF FRAMING I WOULD THINK PUTS A
LITIGATION TARGET ON THE CITY'S BACK AND THE TERM DRUG TOLERANT
HOUSING SUGGESTS THAT THE CITY ALLOWS PEOPLE TO OPENLY USE
DRUGS IN CITY FUNDED PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING AND THAT'S
JUST NOT THE CASE. LESS LEGALLY RISKY AND TO ME
LESS STIGMATIZING TERMINOLOGY WOULD BE ABSTINENT OR SOBER
HOUSING AND LOW BARRIER HOUSING.
>> I ALSO APPRECIATE SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR ADDING AN AMENDMENT
CLARIFYING THE GOAL OF THIS LEGISLATION IS TO AVOID
EVICTIONS. >> HOWEVER, I FEAR THAT THE
LEGISLATION BEFORE US AS WRITTEN LACKS STRONG PROTOCOLS
FOR PROVIDING SUPPORT TO RESIDENTS FACING EVICTION FROM
ABSTINENT HOUSING AND WILL HAVE THE UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCE OF
ACTUALLY DRIVING UP HOMELESSNESS AND THEREFORE DRUG
USE ON OUR STREETS. >> GETTING PEOPLE INTO
PERMANENTLY SUPPORTIVE HOUSING TAKES A TREMENDOUS AMOUNT OF
CITY EFFORT IN THE FIRST PLACE. THE LEGISLATION AS WRITTEN
ALLOWS FOR SOMEONE TO BE EVICTED FROM SOBER HOUSING TO A
SHELTER THAT IS NOT GOING TO PROVIDE SOMEONE IN RECOVERY
STABILITY. RESEARCH SHOWS THAT RELAPSE IS
A PART OF RECOVERY AS MUCH AS SIX TIMES BEFORE THEY GET SOBER
WHICH IS WHY UPON SECOND RELAPSE PEOPLE SHOULD BE
OFFERED THE OPTION FOR TREATMENT AND IF THEY
PARTICIPATE IN TREATMENT BE ABLE TO RETURN TO THEIR UNIT.
SHELTER IS NOT HOUSING. SHELTER IS A ROUGH PLACE FOR
SOMEONE STRUGGLING WITH SUBSTANCE USE ORDER TO BE A
PERSON IS NOT CONSIDERED HOUSED WHEN THEY'RE IN SHELTER THEY'RE
STILL CONSIDERED HOMELESS. I ALSO THINK IT IS FEASIBLE FOR
THE CITY TO PROVIDE AND RELOCATE SOMEONE TO
COMPARABLE ALTERNATIVE HOUSING .
AS OF RIGHT NOW TODAY SAN FRANCISCO HAS 762 VACANT
PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING UNITS OUT OF ITS INVENTORY OF
OVER 9160 THREE UNITS AND THESE EMPTY UNITS 322 ARE CURRENTLY
UNDERGOING THE MOVE IN PROCESS 345 ARE OFFLINE FOR MAINTENANCE
AND REPAIRS AND A WHOLE 90 FIVE ARE FULLY READY FOR IMMEDIATE
TENANT REFERRALS. I APPRECIATE ALL THE WORK
THAT'S BEEN PUT INTO THIS LEGISLATION TO MINIMIZE THE
LEGISLATION'S IMPACT ON EVICTIONS BUT I STILL THINK IT
DOESN'T PROVIDE ENOUGH POLICY DIRECTION TO ENSURE THAT PEOPLE
WILL NOT BE EVICTED BACK TO SHELTERS AND THEREFORE INTO
HOUSING INSTABILITY. FOR THIS REASON I'D LIKE TO
MAKE A MOTION TO ADOPT THE FOLLOWING AMENDMENTS THAT MY
STAFF DISTRIBUTED EARLIER TODAY .
CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE HAS CONFIRMED THESE ARE NON
SUBSTANTIVE AND WILL NOT DELAY THE PASSAGE OF THIS
LEGISLATION. >> THE AMENDMENTS ARE AS
FOLLOWS PAGE FOUR LINE 19 FOR RELOCATION TO ANOTHER OPTION
STRIKING OUT OR SHELTER. ON PAGES EIGHT ON PAGE EIGHT
LINES 12 AND 13 CONFIRMATION FROM MATRIX H THAT THE RESIDENT
HAS BEEN OFFERED COMPARABLE ALTERNATIVE HOUSING STRIKING
OUT OR SHELTER TO ENSURE THAT THEY ARE NOT EVICTED INTO
HOMELESSNESS. AND PAGE EIGHT LINE 19 AN
OFFERING SUCH RESIDENTS APPROPRIATE ALTERNATIVE HOUSING
BY STRIKING OUT SHELTER PLACEMENT OR A PATHWAY TO
HOUSING PRIOR TO PROGRAM DISCHARGE OR EVICTION.
>> COLLEAGUES I WOULD APPRECIATE YOUR SUPPORT.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER HAS MADE A MOTION IS THERE A SECOND FOR
SECONDED BY MELGAR? SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU SO
MUCH. >> I WANTED TO START MY REMARKS
BY THANKING A SUPERVISOR DORSEY .
WHEN YOU FIRST SPOKE TO ME ABOUT THIS LEGISLATION I WAS
LIKE OVER A YEAR AGO YOU'VE BEEN AT THIS FOR A REALLY LONG
TIME AND THIS LEGISLATION ACTUALLY HAS REALLY MOVED.
SO I WANTED TO FIRST OF ALL THANK YOU FOR YOUR ENGAGEMENT
AND FOR INCORPORATING MY FEEDBACK AND THE FEEDBACK OF
OTHERS IN THE COMMUNITY. AND I KNOW THAT IT TOOK A LOT
OF HAT AND HEART FOR YOU TO DO THAT AND I JUST WANT TO
APPRECIATE YOU FOR THAT. I AM UNCOMFORTABLE IN SOME OF
SIMILAR WAYS AS WERE DESCRIBED BY SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
>> AND I THINK THAT I CAN GET OVER MY DISCOMFORT OF WORDS
ESPECIALLY IF OUR CITY ATTORNEY IS VOUCHING FOR THIS AS I
ASSUME THEY DID BECAUSE IT'S APPROVED AS A FORM AND I WANT
TO LIKE APPRECIATE YOUR PASSION TO PROVIDE SERVICES
AND ALTERNATIVES FOR THIS POPULATION.
>> HOWEVER, I DO WANT TO STRONGLY MAKE A PITCH TO
SUPPORT SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S AMENDMENTS AS PROPOSED.
I THINK WE ARE TRYING TO TRY OUT SOMETHING NEW YOU KNOW
AND I THINK THAT WHENEVER YOU TRY SOMETHING NEW YOU'RE
BUILDING A LOT OF THINGS AND ASSUMPTIONS AND FRAMEWORKS
FROM SCRATCH IN PUTTING THIS FORWARD WE ARE PUTTING FORWARD
A NEW POLICY AND I THINK IT'S ENTIRELY APPROPRIATE EVEN IF
THE DEPARTMENT WANTS MAXIMUM FLEXIBILITY FOR US TO SAY BUT
THESE ARE THE PARAMETERS. THIS IS WHAT WE DON'T WANT TO
HAPPEN. WE DON'T WANT SOMEBODY WHO
DOESN'T HAVE THE LINEAR PROGRESSION OF YOU KNOW LIKE
BEING SOBER FALLS OFF THE WAGON A COUPLE TIMES TO HAVE TO GO
BACK TO SQUARE ONE AND HAVE TO START IN THE COORDINATED ENTRY
SYSTEM AT A SHELTER BECAUSE AS MY COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR FIELDER
DESCRIBED, IT'S NOT A GOOD PLACE TO BE ESPECIALLY IF
YOU'RE IN CRISIS. >> AND SO WE ALL KNOW THAT WE
HAVE HUNDREDS OF UNITS IN PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING
THAT ARE VACANT. I THINK THAT SETTING A
PARAMETER FOR THE DEPARTMENT IS APPROPRIATE.
I WILL SAY I HAD A RECENT EXPERIENCE WITH THE DEPARTMENT
WITH THE RV PROGRAM WHICH WAS MOSTLY SUCCESSFUL AND THERE HAS
BEEN HICCUPS ON THE ONE OFF SCENE OF PEOPLE WHO DON'T QUITE
FIT OR YOU KNOW, FELL THROUGH THE CRACKS IN THE OUTREACH
AND SO I DO THINK THAT IT IS APPROPRIATE TO, YOU KNOW, SORT
OF PUT THAT PARAMETER AND SAY THIS IS WHAT WE WOULD LIKE TO
SEE AND I THINK SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S AMENDMENTS DO SPEAK
TO THAT. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR PREPARING
THEM. SUPERVISOR FIELDER AND THEN
AGAIN THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR THE WORK AND PASSION
THAT YOU HAVE PUT INTO THIS. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN. I JUST I DO WANT TO ADDRESS THE
TERMINOLOGY AROUND DRUG TOLERANT AS DISTINCT FROM DRUG
FREE AND EXPLAIN WHY THROUGHOUT THIS PROCESS I HAVE
CONSISTENTLY IDENTIFIED THIS AS A HILL.
I WOULD ABSOLUTELY DIE ON. THOSE OF US IN THE POLICYMAKING
REALM CAN SOMETIMES ADOPT TERMS OF ART THAT WE UNDERSTAND
WITHOUT FULLY APPRECIATING THAT THESE USE EUPHEMISMS
AND SLOGANS HOLD NO INTRINSIC OR INTUITIVE MEANING FOR THE
PEOPLE THEY'RE DESIGNED TO SERVE.
THERE IS NOTHING ABOUT TERMS LIKE HOUSING FIRST OR
TRADITIONAL PCH OR LOW BARRIER OR HARM REDUCTION HOUSING THAT
COULD REASONABLY OR INTUITIVELY BE EXPECTED TO MEAN DRUG
TOLERANT EVEN THOUGH THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT THE LAW MEANS.
I WANT TO READ FROM CALIFORNIA LAW HERE.
THIS IS WELFARE AND INSTITUTIONS CODE SECTION
8255. THIS IS WHERE THE CORE
COMPONENTS OF HOUSING FIRST MANDATE THE FOLLOWING LEASE
PROVISIONS AND PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FOR STATE
FUNDED PCH. QUOTE THE USE OF ALCOHOL OR
DRUGS IN AND OF ITSELF WITHOUT OTHER LEASE VIOLATIONS IS NOT A
REASON FOR EVICTION. SERVICES ARE INFORMED BY A HARM
REDUCTION PHILOSOPHY THAT RECOGNIZES DRUG USE
AND ADDICTION AS PART OF TENANTS LIVES.
AND IT PRESCRIBES THAT SUPPORT FOR RESIDENTS WHO ENGAGE
IN ILLICIT DRUG USE TO BE NON-JUDGMENTAL COMMUNICATION
IN WHICH TENANTS ARE OFFERED EDUCATION ON HOW TO ENGAGE
IN SAFER PRACTICES. I HAVE NO OBJECTIONS TO THAT.
BUT BY ANY DEFINITION THESE PROVISIONS ARE DRUG TOLERANT.
THERE ARE ALSO WHOLLY UNIQUE TO PCH RESIDENTS.
THESE ARE NOT THESE PROVISIONS FOUND IN ANY OTHER RESIDENTIAL
LEASE IN SAN FRANCISCO OR IN CALIFORNIA FOR THAT MATTER.
YOU KNOW, THERE ARE PROFESSIONAL STANDARDS AROUND
PUBLIC HEALTH COMMUNICATIONS INCLUDING IN THE AMA'S CODE OF
MEDICAL ETHICS THAT CAUTION AGAINST THE YOUTH THE USE OF
EUPHEMISMS AND SLOGAN SLOGANS WHEN IT MASKS INFORMATION THAT
IS IMPORTANT AND MEANINGFUL TO THOSE BEING SERVED.
AND I THINK IT IS THE HEIGHT OF POLICYMAKING ARROGANCE FRANKLY
TO ASSUME THAT INDIVIDUALS EXITING HOMELESSNESS INTO PCH
SHOULD BE EXPECTED TO KNOW THAT THE EUPHEMISM HOUSING FIRST
MEANS DRUG TOLERANT. EVEN THOUGH THAT INFORMATION
MAY MEAN EVERYTHING TO THE HEALTH AND WELL-BEING OF THE
RESIDENT, WE'RE ENDEAVORING TO SERVE.
I HAD A CONSTITUENT NAMED DANIEL MACLENNAN.
DANIEL IS A TALENTED ARTIST, A FORMER PCH RESIDENT ON SIXTH
STREET IN MY DISTRICT. SOME OF YOU MAY HAVE MET HIM OR
RECALL HIM BECAUSE HE TESTIFIED IN FAVOR OF ASSEMBLY MEMBER
MATT HANEY'S LEGISLATION IN SACRAMENTO TO REFORM HOUSING
FIRST AT THE STATE LEVEL. DANIEL IS ALSO A RECOVERING
OPIOID ADDICT. HERE IS SOMEBODY WHO'S
LITERALLY FIGHTING FOR HIS LIFE ON MEDICATION ASSISTED
TREATMENT. AND WE PLACED HIM INTO A
HOUSING FIRST ENVIRONMENT WITH NO FOREWARNING OF HOW DRUG
TOLERANT AND CHAOTIC THE ENVIRONMENT WE WERE PUTTING HIM
INTO WAS. IT WAS VERY NEARLY CATASTROPHIC
TO HIS WELL-BEING. IT BROKE MY HEART TO HEAR HIM
SAY HOW DAMAGING HIS LIVING ENVIRONMENT WAS TO HIS MENTAL
HEALTH AND TO HIS SOBRIETY. HE TOLD ME THAT IF HE DIDN'T
HAVE RESPONSIBILITY FOR A DOG HE WOULD RATHER BE ON THE
STREET BECAUSE IT WOULD HAVE BEEN BETTER FOR HIS MENTAL
HEALTH. THE GOOD NEWS IS THAT DANIEL
JUST CELEBRATED ONE YEAR OF CONTINUOUS SOBRIETY BUT HE HAD
TO DO IT IN FRESNO. I HAVE ANOTHER CONSTITUENT
WHO'S ALSO IN RECOVERY FOR ALCOHOL.
SHE IS A MOTHER OF THREE CHILDREN WHO TOLD ME SHE HAD NO
IDEA THAT THE FACILITY WE MOVED HER FAMILY INTO.
THIS IS THE MARGO IN MY DISTRICT WOULD HAVE SUCH A
RAMPANT DRUG USE. SHE TOLD ME THAT AFTER DOING
EVERYTHING SHE COULD TO RESCUE HER KIDS FROM THE TRAUMA OF
UNSHELTERED HOMELESSNESS THEY WERE BEING RETRAUMATIZED BY
FATAL OVERDOSES HAPPENING ALL AROUND THEM.
SHE WORKED WITH MY OFFICE TO GET RELOCATED.
BUT FOR A MOTHER OF THREE SMALL CHILDREN AND RECOVERY HERSELF,
INFORMATION ABOUT THE DRUG TOLERANT POLICIES SHE WOULD BE
LIVING IN WOULD HAVE BEEN GOOD INFORMATION FOR HER TO HAVE
IN ADVANCE. SHE HAS SINCE MOVED TO ANOTHER
FACILITY WHERE THERE IS MORE SEPARATION BETWEEN FAMILIES
AND HABITUAL DRUG USERS. BUT IT REALLY HAS BEEN A
CHALLENGE FOR HER AND HER FAMILY AND SHE STRONGLY
SUPPORTS A DRUG FREE ALTERNATIVE.
BOTH OF THESE CONSTITUENTS AMONG MANY OTHER BROTHERS
AND SISTERS IN RECOVERY INSPIRED THIS LEGISLATION.
BUT THERE ARE ALSO ABIDING EXAMPLES OF WHY PCH RESIDENTS
DESERVE THE COURTESY OF CLEAR, ACCURATE TERMINATOR TERMINAL
LOGY AND NOT MISGUIDED LEADING EUPHEMISMS ABOUT DRUG POLICIES
AND WHERE THEY RESIDE. THIS IS IMPORTANT TO THEIR
SOBRIETY AND IN MANY WAYS BY EXTENSION IMPORTANT TO THEIR
VERY SURVIVAL. AND THAT WAS WHY THIS IS SUCH
AN IMPORTANT POLICY THAT I THINK WE DESCRIBE IT ACCURATELY
SUPERVISED JEN. >> THANK YOU.
BILL PRESS AND FIRST I ALSO WOULD LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE
SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND THE WATER HE AND HIS TEAM HAVE PUT INTO
THIS LEGISLATION. I RECOGNIZE THAT HE HAS SPENT A
LOT OF TIME WORKING ON AMENDMENTS TO TRY TO ALLEVIATE
CONCERNS FROM DIFFERENT STAKEHOLDERS.
>> I WANT TO SAY THAT ON THE RECORD THAT I AM VERY
SUPPORTIVE OF SOBER HOUSING SOLUTIONS BUT AT THE SAME TIME
I DO HAVE DO HAVE SOME CONCERNS ABOUT THIS LEGISLATION.
I DON'T BELIEVE THAT OUR CITY SHOULD BE IMPLEMENTING SOBER
HOUSING ENVIRONMENTS IN A WAY THAT COULD CAUSE HARM TO THOSE
WHO CANNOT LIVE SUCCESSFULLY IN THAT ENVIRONMENT.
>> SOBER HOUSING SOLUTIONS SHOULD NOT COME AT THE RISK OF
MAKING SOME PEOPLE HOUSING INSECURE.
>> GIVEN THE AFFORDABILITY CRISIS FACING IN THE CITY
COUPLED WITH THE FACT THAT WE ARE ACTIVELY TRYING TO CREATE
MORE FLOW THROUGH THE SYSTEM AND I'M WORRIED ABOUT ADDING
NEW BARRIERS WITH THE COUNTER INTUITIVE WILL BE
COUNTERINTUITIVE TO OUR LONG TERM GOALS.
>> AGAIN, I'M VERY APPRECIATIVE OF ALL THE GOOD FAITH AND GOOD
WORK THAT YOU AND THE CARE THAT YOU PUT IN SUPERVISOR DORSEY
AND ALSO YOUR TEAM AND ALSO ALL THIS DIFFERENT STAKEHOLDERS ON
THIS LEGISLATION. AND I ALSO WOULD LIKE TO SAY
THAT I AM SUPPORTIVE OF SUPERVISOR FIONA'S AMENDMENT
AND IF HER AMENDMENTS PASSES AND I WILL ALSO BE THEN WILLING
AND ABLE TO SUPPORT THIS LEGISLATION.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU.
>> YES, I AM IN AGREEMENT AND SHARED THE SENTIMENT THAT
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY. I THINK THAT IT DOES TAKE A LOT
OF EFFORT TO FOR THE CITY TO HAVE ALTERNATIVES AND I THINK
THAT WHEN I WHEN DIRECTOR DAN CI ACTUALLY WAS APPOINTED TO
HIS POSITION ONE OF THE QUESTIONS WAS ASKED
SPECIFICALLY ABOUT HOW DO WE REALLY PROBLEM SOLVED FENTANYL
CRISIS IN SAN FRANCISCO. AND I REALLY APPRECIATE HIS
ANSWER AT THAT MOMENT I AND I THINK THAT THAT IS WHERE MY
APPROACH IS TO PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS.
AND WHEN IT COMES TO THE DRUG CRISIS IS THAT WE HAVE TO MEET
PEOPLE WHERE THEY'RE AT AND THAT WE NEED TO PROVIDE ALL
OPTIONS. AND I ABSOLUTELY BELIEVE THAT
SOBER HOUSING OR DRUG FREE HOUSING IS AND HAS TO BE
ABSOLUTELY AN OPTION THAT WE OFFER AS A CITY.
>> I THINK FOR A HERE THAT I CAN ALSO UNDERSTAND TO MAKE
SURE THAT WE PROTECT INTEGRITY OF SOBER HOUSING AND DRUG FREE
HOUSING THAT FOR THOSE WHO FALL SHORT OF THAT WE'LL HAVE TO
RECONSIDER OR BE RECONSIDER FOR A DIFFERENT LOCATION FOR TO
CONTINUE ON WITH TREATMENT AND HOUSING OPTION.
I THINK THAT IS WHERE THE RUBBER MEETS THE ROAD AND IT
MAKES IT DIFFICULT FOR US TO FIGURE OUT HOW THEN DO WE STILL
CONTINUE TO SUPPORT THESE INDIVIDUALS WHO ARE CLEARLY
FALL SHORT AND CANNOT MAINTAIN SOBRIETY IN THIS SITUATION
AND ACTUALLY IMPACT THOSE WHO SEEK SOBRIETY AND ARE HAVING
SUCCESS AND ALREADY WORKING HARD, YOU KNOW, TOWARDS TO
MAINTAIN THAT SUCCESS. AND SO WHAT I'M SEEING IS THAT
IT PAINS ME TO SEE THE LANGUAGE IN HERE THAT I TOTALLY
UNDERSTAND THE CHALLENGE AND THE STRUGGLE WITH WORDS
AND HOW TO IDENTIFY IDS, HOUSING AND OPTIONS FOR
INDIVIDUALS AND THEN MAKE SURE THAT THE INTENT IT'S CLEAR THE
POLICY IT'S CLEAR. IT ALSO PAINS ME TO TO SEE THAT
I DON'T SEE THAT THERE ARE MUTUALLY EXCLUSIVE MEANING TO
SUPPORT THOSE WHO ARE FIGHTING HARD AND MAINTAINING SUCCESS
IN SOBER HOUSING AND THOSE WHO HAVE FOR SHORT ANY ALTERNATIVE
OPTIONS SO THAT THEY CAN REMAIN HOUSE AND STILL RECEIVE
TREATMENT. IF YOU AND I THINK THAT IT'S A
REASON WHY I SUPPORT BOTH. SO I SEE DORSEY'S AMENDMENT AS
WOW SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S AMENDMENTS TODAY.
I WOULD LOVE TO SEE THOSE WERE RELOCATION INSTEAD OF EVICTION
IN THIS POLICY. TO BE HONEST AND TO KIND OF PUT
THE RESPONSIBILITY ACTUALLY ON THE CITY GIVEN THE FACT THAT
WE'RE NOW NARROWING IT DOWN TO CITY FUNDED AND NEW SITES.
I THINK THAT THE CITY SHOULD HAVE AN OWNERSHIP IN THIS TO
SAY THAT WE SHOULD OWN THAT TO PROVIDE AND SUPPORT THE
PROVIDERS AND OPERATORS THAT WE REALLY HATE INDIVIDUALS WHO
FALL SHORT IN THE DRUG FREE HOUSING SETTING.
>> I AM STRUGGLING WITH THIS AND I HAVE BEEN SINCE THE TIME
THAT SUPERVISOR DORSEY HAS INTRODUCED THIS LEGISLATION.
I WAS VERY GRATEFUL THE FACT THAT THERE WAS AGREEMENT TO
SEND US BACK TO COMMITTEE SO THAT THERE WAS ONGOING
CONVERSATION AND DISCUSSION AND ALLOWING SOME SPACE.
BUT I DIDN'T KNOW THAT EVENTUALLY WILL COME BACK AND I
WAS HOPING FOR A VERSION THAT WENT USING TERMINOLOGY THAT I
CAN BE ON BOARD WITH AND BE MORE COMFORTABLE WITH BECAUSE I
DO KNOW IS IT IS NOT ACTUALLY ABOUT THE TERMINOLOGY OR JUST
ABOUT THE TERMINOLOGY BEING USED BUT TRULY IS REALLY ABOUT
THE POLICY THAT IT'S BEING IMPLEMENTED AND HOW WE CAN
ACTUALLY SUPPORT INDIVIDUALS WITH THEIR DIVERSE NEEDS
AND WITH DIVERSE OPTIONS AND THAT THEY CAN ALL REACH
SUCCESS AND BECOME FUNCTIONING MEMBERS OF OUR SOCIETY ONCE
MORE. AND BECAUSE I DO RECOGNIZE THAT
IT'S A PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS AND IS A DISEASE THAT NO ONE
SHOULD BE CRIMINALIZED FOR FOR FIGHTING AND TO GET BETTER
AND TRY TO GET YOU KNOW. BUT ALSO NO ONE SHOULD BE
HOMELESS WHEN THEY ALSO TRYING TO AGAIN FIGHT THIS DISEASE.
SO I AM STRUGGLING WITH THOSE COLLEAGUES AND I'M HOPING THAT
WE CAN APPROVE BOTH THE AMENDMENTS SO THAT WE CAN
SUPPORT THIS FOR NOW AND REVISIT THIS CONVERSATION
ONCE MORE ONCE WE LEARN BETTER ABOUT THE DATA AND HOW
SUCCESSFUL INDIVIDUALS CAN BE AND AND WHETHER OR NOT PEOPLE
DO END UP FALLING INTO HOMELESSNESS AND AND HOW DO WE
END UP SUPPORTING THE INDIVIDUALS?
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG COLLEAGUES, I'M
PROUD TO CO-SPONSOR THIS MEASURE BECAUSE AT ITS CORE IT
IS ABOUT GIVING PEOPLE A CHANCE.
PEOPLE WORKING TO OVERCOME ADDICTION DESERVE A CHANCE TO
LIVE SOMEWHERE THAT SUPPORTS THEIR RECOVERY.
FAMILIES WITH CHILDREN, SENIORS AND RESIDENTS WHO SIMPLY WANTS
A HOME FREE FROM ILLICIT DRUG USE DESERVE THAT CHANCE TO.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS TRIED MANY APPROACHES WITH GOOD INTENTIONS
BUT GOOD INTENTIONS ALONE ARE NOT ENOUGH AND THE RESULTS
SPEAK FOR THEMSELVES. TOO MANY PEOPLE REMAIN TRAPPED
IN ADDICTION. TOO MANY RESIDENTS FEEL UNSAFE
IN THEIR OWN BUILDINGS AND TOO MANY PEOPLE TRYING TO RECOVER
ARE BEING ASKED TO DO SO WHILE SURROUNDED BY THE VERY
SUBSTANCES THEY'RE TRYING TO LEAVE BEHIND.
>> WHEN THE CURRENT APPROACH IS NOT PRODUCING THE RESULTS WE
NEED, WE HAVE A RESPONSIBILITY TO TRY NEW NEW IDEAS AND I
DON'T REALLY CARE FOR WHICHEVER TERMINOLOGY WE USE.
THE BOTTOM LINE IS THAT THE CURRENT MODEL MAY NOT MAY WORK
FOR SOME RESIDENTS BUT SHOULD NOT BE THE ONLY OPTION.
THIS LEGISLATION CREATES MORE DRUG FREE SUPPORTIVE HOUSING
FOR PEOPLE WHO ACTIVELY WANT AN ENVIRONMENT THAT SUPPORTS
SOBRIETY AND RECOVERY. THIS IS NOT ABOUT PUNISHMENT
AND IS NOT ABOUT EXPECTING PERFECTION.
RELAPSE CAN BE PART OF RECOVERY AND ONE MISTAKE SHOULD NOT
AUTOMATICALLY COST SOMEONE THEIR HOME.
THE MEASURE INCLUDES PROTECTIONS AND REQUIRES THAT
ALTERNATIVE HOUSING BE OFFERED BEFORE AN OTHERWISE COMPLIANT
RESIDENT CAN BE EVICTED FOR DRUG USE.
COMPASSION MEANS MORE THAN MAINTAINING THE STATUS QUO.
IT MEANS BEING HONEST ABOUT WHAT IS NOT WORKING AND GIVING
PEOPLE BETTER CHOICES. WE CANNOT GUARANTEE RECOVERY
BUT WE CAN GIVE PEOPLE A REAL CHANCE AT IT.
>> NOBODY ELSE IS IN THE QUEUE .
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR FOR THIS IS ONE
OF THOSE MOMENTS WHERE I'M GRATEFUL FOR YOUR PRESENCE ON
THIS BOARD. >> I'M GRATEFUL FOR YOUR
PASSION AROUND AROUND GETTING SAN FRANCISCO ON A DIFFERENT
PATH AND LET'S MAKE NO MISTAKE THE PATH WE'RE ON IS IS A
DISTRESSING AND DISTURBING ONE. THE STATUS QUO IS INSANE.
THE STATUS QUO IN WHICH SO MANY FOLKS LIVING IN PERMANENT PART
OF HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS ARE CONSIGNED TO DEAL WITH THE MOST
OUTRAGEOUS BEHAVIOR FROM THEIR NEIGHBORS AND THE MANAGERS OF
THOSE BUILDINGS ARE UNABLE TO DO ANYTHING ABOUT IT BECAUSE OF
GOVERNMENT POLICY AND THE STATUS QUO IN THOSE
NEIGHBORHOODS THAT ARE IMPACTED BY THE RAMPANT SALES AND USE
IN PUBLIC SPACE OF DRUGS IS UNACCEPTABLE AND SO SUPERVISED
. DORSEY YOUR MEASURE HERE THAT
YOU HAVE LABORED OVER FOR A YEAR MORE THAN A YEAR IS THE
MOST MODEST INCREMENTAL STEP IN THE DIRECTION OF SUPPORTING
RECOVERY IN IN THIS HOUSING. IT DOES NOT APPLY TO EXISTING
THE 10,000 PLUS EXISTING UNITS OF PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING
THAT OUR DRUG TOLERANCE. IT DOES NOT APPLY TO MOST OF
THE NEW PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING THAT WILL COME ONLINE
AS YOU HAVE DESCRIBED IT WILL APPLY TO THE SMALL FRACTION OF
PCH THAT COMES ONLINE. THAT IS FUNDED BY CITY FUNDING
WITHOUT ANOTHER FUNDING SOURCE .
SO I HAVE NO ANXIETY ABOUT YOUR MEASURE.
I THINK IT IS EXTREMELY IMPORTANT THAT WE MAKE THIS
ENFORCEABLE BY OUR DEPARTMENTS. I'M HAPPY TO SUPPORT YOUR
AMENDMENT AND I WILL NOT BE SUPPORTING THE OTHER.
MADAM CLERK, DO YOU CARE WHICH ORDER WE VOTE ON THESE
AMENDMENTS? >> THE MOTION MADE BY
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHERYL WOULD BE
FIRST. >> ALL RIGHT.
COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THAT AMENDMENT ON THE DORSEY
CHERYL AMENDMENT TO ITEM 41. SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I. SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER PEELED HER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
EYES SUPERVISOR MENDELSON EYE MANDALAY ARMAN EYE
AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I THERE ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO
WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON VOTING NO.
>> THE MOTION PASSES. MADAM CLERK COULD YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE SECOND AMENDMENT FOR ALL ON THE FIELD
OR MELGAR AMENDMENT TO ITEM 41 SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER NO.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL NO SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG NO. SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY NO
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD NO
SUPERVISOR MIDDLEMAN NO MIDDLEMAN NO AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR I MELGAR I THERE ARE FIVE EYES AND SIX NOSE WITH
SUPERVISORS SADR CHERYL WONG DORSEY MAHMOOD AND MANDEL MEN
VOTING NO SIR SO THERE ARE FIVE EYES.
FIVE EYES AND THE MOTION DOES NOT PASS.
OKAY. MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE AMENDED ITEM ON ITEM 41 AS AMENDED?
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
EYES SUPERVISOR FOR WALTON WILSON NO SUPERVISOR WONG WONG
EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDEL
MIN I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I THERE ARE SEVEN EYES
AND FOUR NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON CHIN CHIN AND FIELDER
VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING FOR
SUPERVISOR CHAN I SINCERELY APOLOGIZE I WOULD LIKE TO
RECEIVE MY VOTE ON ITEM NUMBER 30 I A 39 IS A MOTION TO
RESCIND THE VOTE ON 39 IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY WALTON?
CAN WE TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION?
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE VOTE IS RESCINDED.
OKAY. AND THEN MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM? YOU DON'T STILL NEED TO TALK
RESOLUTION, RIGHT? I CAN THINK OF YOU ALL RIGHT,
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 39 ON
ITEM 39 SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO.
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN NO.
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MILKER I THERE ARE EIGHT EYES AND THREE NOSE WITH
SUPERVISORS WALTON CHAN AND CHIN VOTING NO AND THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 42 ITEM 42 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO AFFIRM SAN
FRANCISCO'S SUPPORT FOR THE SPEED SAFETY SYSTEM PILOT
PROGRAM AND TO URGE THE EXPLORATION OF CHANGES TO
STRENGTHEN THE PROGRAM TO INCLUDE INCREASING THE NUMBER
OF ALLOWABLE SPEED CAMERA LOCATIONS WITH PRIORITY GIVEN
TO CORRIDORS ON THE HIGH INJURY NETWORK AND OTHER LOCATIONS
WITH DEMONSTRATED SAFETY NEED. AND PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
THIS ITEM ON ITEM 42. >> SUPERVISOR SAUDER SUTTER
EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
NO. SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MANAGEMENT EYE AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYE THERE ARE TEN
EYES AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON VOTING NO THE RESOLUTION
IS ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 43 .
>> ITEM 43 THIS ITEM WAS CONSIDERED BY THE RULES
COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY JULY 13TH.
THIS ITEM IS A MOTION APPOINTING BETTY PACKARD
AND RUTH GRACE WONG TERMS ENDING NOVEMBER 30TH 2026 TO
THE BALLOT SIMPLIFICATION COUNCIL.
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 43.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR ONE WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN EYE
RANDLEMAN EYE AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYE.
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. >> LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL.
>> SUPERVISOR SOUDER REFERS TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS.
SUBMIT THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUBMIT THANK
YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION AND ALSO A BILL A REQUEST.
>> FIRST I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF
CONTINUING THE BABY'S SHADOW. >> DISTRICT TEN RESIDENTS
CONTINUE TO FACE URGENT TRANSPORTATION INEQUITIES THAT
LIMIT ACCESS TO JOBS, HEALTH CARE, EDUCATION, GROCERY STORES
AND OTHER ESSENTIAL SERVICES. THIS RESOLUTION IS TO ENCOURAGE
CONTINUED AND SUSTAINABLE FUNDING AND LONG TERM SUPPORT
FOR THE BAYVIEW COMMUNITY SHUTTLE PROGRAM.
A CRITICAL EQUITY AND ACCESS INITIATIVE SERVING BAYVIEW
HUNTERS POINT. FAR TOO LONG TRANSPORTATION
INEQUITIES HAVE LIMITED ACCESS TO JOBS HEALTH CARE, EDUCATION
,GROCERY STORES AND OTHER ESSENTIAL SERVICES.
FOR MANY DISTRICT TEN RESIDENTS, THE BAYVIEW
COMMUNITY SHUTTLE WAS CREATED TO HELP ADDRESS THOSE
CHALLENGES BY PROVIDING RELIABLE LOW COST
TRANSPORTATION THAT CONNECTS PEOPLE TO OPPORTUNITY WHILE
STRENGTHENING COMMUNITY CONNECTIONS.
SINCE LAUNCHING IN NOVEMBER 2024, THE PROGRAM HAS
DEMONSTRATED REMARKABLE SUCCESS.
RIDERSHIP CONTINUES TO GROW WITH HUNDREDS OF RIDES PROVIDED
EACH DAY AND CONSISTENTLY HIGH SATISFACTION FROM THE PEOPLE
WHO RELY ON THE SERVICE. >> MORE IMPORTANTLY, THE
SHUTTLE HAS BECOME A LIFELINE FOR SENIORS, YOUTH FAMILIES,
WORKERS AND INDIVIDUALS DISABILITIES WHO DEPEND ON
SAFE, ACCESSIBLE TRANSPORTATION .
>> THIS PROGRAM IS NOT ABOUT MORE THAN MOVING PEOPLE.
THIS PROGRAM IS ABOUT MORE THAN MOVING PEOPLE FROM ONE PLACE TO
ANOTHER. IT ALSO CREATES ECONOMIC
OPPORTUNITY BY CONNECTING RESIDENTS TO WORK FORCE
DEVELOPMENT PROGRAMS THAT PREPARE LOCAL COMMUNITY MEMBERS
FOR CAREERS IN THE TRANSPORTATION INDUSTRY.
IT IS A MODEL THAT INVESTS IN BOTH MOBILITY AND ECONOMIC
EMPOWERMENT. AS MANY OF YOU KNOW, DISTRICT
TEN WILL SOON FACE ADDITIONAL TRANSPORTATION CHALLENGES AS
THE LAST CREEK BRIDGE REPLACEMENT PROJECT MOVES
FORWARD. THAT CRITICAL INFRASTRUCTURE
PROJECT WILL BRING YEARS OF CONSTRUCTION RELATED IMPACTS
MAKING RELIABLE NEIGHBORHOOD TRANSPORTATION EVEN MORE
IMPORTANT FOR OUR RESIDENTS, BUSINESSES AND WORKERS.
THIS RESOLUTION RECOGNIZES THE TREMENDOUS PARTNERSHIPS THAT
HAVE MADE THE SHUTTLE SUCCESSFUL FROM S.F. MTA
AND COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATIONS TO WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT PARTNERS AND NEIGHBORHOOD ADVOCATES
AND URGES CONTINUED INVESTMENT TO ENSURE THIS PROGRAM REMAINS
AVAILABLE WELL INTO THE FUTURE. >> I WANT TO THANK ALL OF THE
PARTNERS, ADVOCATES, DRIVERS AND RESIDENTS WHO HAVE HELPED
MAKE THIS PROGRAM SUCH A SUCCESS.
TOGETHER WE ARE DEMONSTRATING WHAT EQUITABLE TRANSPORTATION
CAN LOOK LIKE WHEN WE INVEST DIRECTLY IN OUR COMMUNITIES.
COLLEAGUES, I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT OF THIS
RESOLUTION. I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY
COLLEAGUES WHO HAVE SUPPORTED AND THANK SUPERVISOR CHEN AS
WELL AS SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR THE EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP.
>> COLLEAGUES I AM ALSO REQUESTING THE BUDGET
AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYSTS TO INTERPRET CLEARLY ANALYZE THE
ECONOMIC IMPACT OF THE CHARTER REFORM MEASURES PROPOSED BY
MAYOR LURIE THAT ARE CURRENTLY UNDERGOING THE SIGNATURE
VERIFICATION PROCESS AT THE DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS.
SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS ARE BEING ASKED TO DECIDE ON THREE
CHARTER REFORM MEASURES THIS NOVEMBER THAT WERE FUNDAMENTAL
RESTRUCTURE HOW THE CITY OPERATES INCLUDING A SPENDING
MAYORAL HIRING AND FIRING AUTHORITY AS WELL AS
REORGANIZATION POWER. EXTENDING THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR'S TERM TO TEN YEARS WHILE GIVING THAT OFFICE
SO AUTHORITY OVER PROCUREMENT. AND RAISING THE SIGNATURE
THRESHOLD FOR CITIZEN INITIATIVES FROM 2% TO 8%.
>> THESE ARE NOT SMALL TECHNICAL FIXES.
THEY SHIFT REAL POWER AWAY FROM THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
INDEPENDENT COMMISSIONS AND FROM THE RESIDENTS OF SAN
FRANCISCO. THEY ALSO COME WITH REAL FISCAL
IMPLICATIONS THAT VOTERS DESERVE TO UNDERSTAND BEFORE
THEY CAST THE BALLOT AND NOT AFTER THE MEASURES OWN LANGUAGE
ACTUALLY MAKES THE CASE FOR SCRUTINY.
THE CONTRACTING MEASURE STATES OUTRIGHT THAT THE CITY SPENDS
OVER $5 BILLION A YEAR ON CONTRACTS THAT A SINGLE
PROCUREMENT CAN COST $25,000 AND TAKE UP TO A YEAR AND THAT
DEPARTMENTS ARE RUNNING FIVE DUPLICATE MICROSOFT CONTRACTS
AND 20 SEPARATE TRAINING SYSTEMS.
IF THOSE NUMBERS ARE TO JUSTIFY A CASE FOR CENTRALIZING POWER
IN THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR'S OFFICE WE SHOULD BE ABLE TO
VERIFY THEM AND SEE THE ACTUAL PROJECTED SAVINGS.
AT THE SAME TIME THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH MEASURE OPENS THE DOOR
TO NEW DEPUTY MAYOR POSITIONS WITH NO CAP ON SALARY OR
NUMBER. AT A MOMENT WHEN THE CITY IS
ALREADY CITING BUDGET CONSTRAINTS ELSEWHERE AND AS
WE'VE SEEN IN THE MOST RECENT BUDGET PROCESS WE SAW WHAT
HAPPENS WHEN COORDINATION FAILS.
WITHOUT THIS STRUCTURE IN PLACE THE PATROL FOR EXAMPLE, COSTS
US 465 UNITS OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND LED TO $1 BILLION
MUNI REBUILD INSTEAD. BUT WE HAVEN'T SEEN ANYTHING
SHOWING THIS MEASURE WOULD HAVE PREVENTED THAT OR WITH THESE
NEW POSITIONS WOULD ACTUALLY COST TAXPAYERS.
THIS IS WHY I'M REQUESTING THE BLADE COMPLETE AN INDEPENDENT
COST ANALYSIS BY SEPTEMBER 8TH, 2026 SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS OUR
CITY OFFICIALS, THE PRESS AND COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS
NEED THIS INFORMATION AND WHILE THERE'S STILL TIME TO ACT ON
IT, MY REQUEST IS TO MAKE SURE THE FISCAL CASE AND ECONOMIC
IMPACT FOR THESE MEASURES HOLDS UP TO THE SAME SCRUTINY THAT
WE'D EXPECT FOR ANY OTHER MAJOR POLICY CHANGE OF THIS SCALE.
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUPERVISOR HUANG SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN.
>> SUBMIT. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU,
MADAM CARTE. COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION URGING CONGRESS TO PASS H R 1667 TO
ACUPUNCTURE FOR OUR SENIORS ACT.
>> UNDER THE CURRENT LAW LICENSED ACUPUNCTURIST ARE
PROHIBITED FROM BEING MEDICARE PROVIDERS SIGNIFICANTLY
LIMITING ACCESS TO THIS HEALTH INTERVENTION WHICH HAS BEEN
USED AS TREATMENT FOR MULTIPLE HEALTH CONCERNS INCLUDING
CANCER, INFERTILITY, SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER AND CHRONIC PAINT.
>> THE EFFICACY OF ACUPUNCTURE AS A MEANINGFUL AND EFFECTIVE
TREATMENT OPTION FOR MANY MEDICAL CONDITIONS WAS
VALIDATED WHEN THE ACA HELPED TO INCREASE ACCESS BY ALLOWING
INDIVIDUAL STATES TO COVER ACUPUNCTURISTS IMPLANTS ON
STATE HEALTH EXCHANGES. >> CALIFORNIA IS ONE OF THOSE
EXAMPLES. THIS BILL WHICH WAS INTRODUCED
BY REPRESENTATIVE JUDY CHU AND BRIAN FITZPATRICK AIMS TO
RECOGNIZE LICENSED THAT ACUPUNCTURISTS AS MEDICARE
PROVIDERS AND TO EXPAND ACCESS TO AFFORDABLE ACUPUNCTURE
TREATMENTS FOR SENIORS NATIONWIDE.
AND NEXT I HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM OF COLLEAGUES I WOULD LIKE TO A
JOINT TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF FAY BEN LEE.
>> BEN WAS BORN IN 1948 IN TAIWAN, CHINA AND GREW UP
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> HE PASSED AWAY PEACEFULLY AT
HOME LAST MONTH AT AGE OF 78. BEN WAS A STUDENT ACTIVIST AT
UC BERKELEY AT A TIME WHEN THE ETHNIC STUDIES DEPARTMENT WAS
JUST BORN OUT OF THE 1969 THERE WAS WALL LIBERATION FUNDS
STRUGGLING DURING THIS TIME. BEN HELPED TO DEVELOP ONE OF
THE FIRST ASIAN STUDIES CAMPUS COMMUNITY PROJECTS ASIAN LEGAL
SERVICES. >> JEFF HELP DESPOJA.
IT WAS A GRASSROOTS EFFORT THAT SERVE THE PEOPLE TO PROVIDE
LEGAL SERVICES AND PROTECT YOUNG MEN OFTEN WORKING CLASS
IMMIGRANTS FROM SELECTIVE SERVICE A SYSTEM AND TO ASSIST
VETERANS WITH CANCER INTERESTS OBJECTOR CLAIMS.
>> BEN ALONG WITH HIS PARTNER PAM TALLEY WERE FOUNDING
MEMBERS OF THE CHINESE PROGRESSIVE ASSOCIATION
ORGANIZING CHINESE IMMIGRANTS AND AMERICAN BORN WORKERS
STUDENTS, FOREIGN STUDENTS AND CHINATOWN YOUTHS.
>> AS A CHINATOWN WORKERS HE LED AND WON A UNIONIZATION
STRIKE OF CHINESE WAREHOUSE WORKERS BECOMING A PROUD MEMBER
OF TEAMSTERS EIGHT FIVE SIX. BEN AND HIS WIFE HAVE BEEN
BELOVED MENTORS TO SO MANY ASIAN AMERICAN COMMUNITY
ORGANIZERS AND LEADERS IN SAN FRANCISCO MYSELF INCLUDED.
>> HIS QUICK GREAT SENSE OF HUMOR GENUINE LOVE FOR PEOPLE
WOULD ALWAYS BRING WARMTH TO A SPACE.
>> BEN'S GENTLE NATURE AND BIG HEART WILL BE DEEPLY MISSED.
HIS LEGACY WILL LIVE ON IN THE IN THE ORGANIZATIONS AND PEOPLE
HE HELPED SHAPE. MAY HIS MEMORY BE A BLESSING
AND DARE I SAY SUMMIT. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE ONE RESOLUTION AND ONE BLUE REPORT.
I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION SUPPORTING CALIFORNIA STATE
ASSEMBLY BILL NUMBER 2564 AUTHORED BY ASSEMBLYMEMBER
CHRIS WARD AND COAUTHORED BY ASSEMBLY MEMBER ASH KALRA.
>> RETAILERS ARE USING PERSONALLY IDENTIFIABLE
CONSUMER DATA TO CHARGE SOME CONSUMERS DISCRIMINATORY
PRICES, PRICES AND WHAT IS BEING CALLED SURVEILLANCE
PRICING CONSUMERS CHARACTERISTICS AND BEHAVIORS
LIKE LOCATION DEMOGRAPHICS, BROWSING PATTERNS, MOUSE
MOVEMENTS ON WEB PAGES AND SHOPPING HISTORY ARE NOW
BEING USED AGAINST THEM TO HELP CORPORATIONS SET INDIVIDUAL
ISED PRICES FOR PRODUCTS AND SERVICES.
>> FOR EXAMPLE A FEBRUARY 2025 AS ADVOCATE INVESTIGATION FOUND
THAT THE MOST POPULAR HOTEL BOOKING SITES SHOW PRICES
SUBSTANTIALLY HIGHER. IN ONE CASE $500 MORE PER NIGHT
FOR A MANHATTAN HOTEL TO SAN FRANCISCO INNS USING THEIR
ONLINE BOOKING PLATFORMS COMPARED WITH USERS BROWSING
FROM LESS AFFLUENT CITIES LIKE PHENIX AND KANSAS CITY.
NO EXISTING FEDERAL OR STATE LAW PROHIBITS COMPANIES FROM
USING THE DATA THEY COLLECT TO CHARGE CONSUMERS INDIVIDUALLY
DIFFERENT PRICES. >> THAT IS WHY I'M INTRODUCING
THIS RESOLUTION TO ENCOURAGE THE TIMELY ADOPTION OF AB 2564
TO PROTECT CONSUMERS FROM SURVEILLANCE PRICING.
I HOPE I CAN COUNT ON YOUR SUPPORT AS WELL.
>> I'M REQUESTING THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST'S
OFFICE EVALUATE THE COSTS AND OTHER IMPACTS OF
ESTABLISHING A MICROENTERPRISE HOME KITCHEN OPERATIONS PROGRAM
IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT WOULD ALLOW SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENTS
TO PREPARE FOOD FOR SALE FROM THEIR PRIVATE RESIDENCES AT A
TIME WHEN THE CITY IS BECOMING INCREASINGLY UNAFFORDABLE.
IT'S IMPORTANT FOR US TO CONTINUE LOOKING FOR WAYS FOR
SAN FRANCISCANS, ESPECIALLY THOSE WITHOUT MUCH ACCESS TO
LARGE AMOUNTS OF CAPITAL AND PEOPLE WHO MIGRATE FROM
OTHER COUNTRIES AND ARE AFRAID OF TRAVELING TO AND FROM PLACES
OF WORK AMONG AN INCREASINGLY HOSTILE FEDERAL ADMINISTRATION
TO BE ABLE TO MAKE A LIVING IN THIS CITY IN THE MISSION WE
HAVE MANY LONG TIMES SMALL SCALE LATINO ENTREPRENEURS ALSO
KNOWN AS FOOD VENDORS WHO HAVE BEEN CAUGHT IN A COMPLICATED
FOOD PERMITTING SYSTEM. IT IS MIND AND THAT AMIGO
PROGRAM IN SAN FRANCISCO WOULD COMPLEMENT OUR COMPED PACKED
MOBILE FOOD ORDINANCE PASSED EARLIER THIS YEAR AND HELP FOOD
VENDORS USE THEIR HOMES TO SUPPORT THEIR CMF OF BUSINESSES
OF COURSE ABIDING BY ALL RELEVANT LOCAL PUBLIC HEALTH
AND PERMITTING REGULATIONS. >> COUNTIES SIMILAR IN SIZE
AND URBAN CHARACTER TO SAN FRANCISCO HAVE SEEN SUCCESSFUL
MAKE UP PROGRAMS INCLUDING ALAMEDA, SANTA CLARA, CONTRA
COSTA, SAN MATEO AND LOS ANGELES AND THIS BILL THEY
REPORT WILL LOOK WELL. WE'LL CONSTRUCT COST
AND OPERATIONAL PROFILES FOR EACH OF THESE COUNTIES THAT CAN
BE USED TO ESTIMATE THE NORMALIZED COSTS FOR A SAN
FRANCISCO MEGA PROGRAM. >> I'M HOPEFUL THAT THIS REPORT
CAN GALVANIZE US AS A CITY TO TAKE ON THIS PROGRAM AND ENSURE
SAN FRANCISCO REMAINS A CITY AFFORDABLE TO PEOPLE OF ALL
WALKS OF LIFE. >> I WANT TO THANK THE COOK
ALLIANCE, THE MISSION FOOD VENDORS COUNCIL AND WESTRA CASA
FOR PUSHING THE CITY FORWARD AND ADVISING ON THIS NEXT STEP
FOR AIMCO PROGRAM IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A MOTION TO ALLOW
THE BOARD TO CALL FILE NUMBER 260693 THE AFFORDABLE GROCERIES
ACTS VACANCY TAX. FROM THE BUDGET AND FINANCE
COMMITTEE TO A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE ON JULY 21ST.
THIS MEASURE NEEDS TO REACH THE FULL BOARD BY LATE JULY TO MAKE
THE NOVEMBER BALLOT. THIS MOTION PRESERVES THE ONLY
PATH LEFT FOR THIS BOARD AND THE VOTERS TO HAVE A SAY.
>> THIS MOTION, I'LL REMIND, IS NOT ABOUT THE MERITS OF THE TAX
ITSELF. IT'S ABOUT WHETHER A SAN
FRANCISCANS LIVING IN FOOD DESERTS GOT A PUBLIC HEARING
AND A DISCUSSION ON A POLICY THAT AFFECTS SO MANY OF OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS. I WANT TO ALSO SAY THAT I KNOW
THAT ALL OF US IN CITY HALL, THE MAYOR AND ALL 11 OF US ON
THE BOARD WE ALL AGREE THAT FOOD DESERTS ARE A PROBLEM
IN OUR CITY. WE ALL AGREE THAT AFFORDABILITY
OF FOOD IS A PROBLEM WE ALL SHOULD SOLVE.
I KNOW THAT ALL OF US CARE ABOUT OUR CITY.
>> AND EVEN IF WE OCCASIONALLY DISAGREE ON THE DIFFERENT
APPROACHES TO GET THERE, WE'RE ALTERNATELY TRYING TO DO THE
BEST WE CAN FOR THE CITY IN THE BEST WAY THAT WE KNOW HOW.
I WANT TO THANK THE CO-SPONSORS WHO SIGNED ON TO THIS MOTION
AND FOR STANDING THAT WE SHOULD HAVE THIS HEARING REGARDLESS OF
IF EVEN MANY OF THESE SPONSORS MAY ULTIMATELY LAND ON A
DIFFERENT SIDE OF THIS POLICY ITSELF.
>> THANK YOU AGAIN. >> SECOND COLLEAGUES, MY SECOND
ITEM IS AN OFFICIAL STREET RENAMING OF AVERY STREET TO
BOSWELL WAY IN HONOR OF REVEREND HAMILTON T BOSWELL.
>> REVEREND BOSWELL WAS A RELIGIOUS AND CIVIC LEADER
AND A BEDROCK OF THE FILLMORE NEIGHBORHOOD IN THE BLACK
COMMUNITY IN SAN FRANCISCO. BORN IN TEXAS, REVEREND BOSWELL
WAS ON THE GROUNDBREAKING WILEY COLLEGE DEBATE TEAM WHICH
OVERSAW WITNESSING LYNCHINGS AND INSTITUTIONAL RACISM TO
DEFEAT THE NATIONAL CHAMPION U.S. DEBATE TEAM IN 1935.
HE CAME TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 1947 TO LEAD JONES MEMORIAL
UNITED METHODIST CHURCH. IN HIS TIME LEADING THE CHURCH,
HE COMMITTED TO UPLIFTING THE SAN FRANCISCO BLACK COMMUNITY
BY LEADING THE CREATION OF THE JONES METHODIST CREDIT UNION
AND JONES MEMORIAL HOMES, THE FIRST FEDERALLY FINANCED SENIOR
HOUSING IN THE CITY. HE MENTORED COUNTLESS CHURCH
AND CIVIC LEADERS INCLUDING FUTURE MAYOR WILLIE BROWN WHO
HE MANAGED THE FIRST CAMPAIGN OF REVEREND BRASWELL ALSO
SERVED AS A CHAPLAIN FOR THE CALIFORNIA STATE ASSEMBLY
AND THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT WAS CHAIRMAN OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO HOUSING AUTHORITY COMMISSION AND TWICE AWARDED
THEN ACP FREEDOM AWARD THE STREET TO BE RENAMED AVERY
STREET RUNS FOR ONE BLOCK ALONGSIDE JONES MEMORIAL CHURCH
AND JONES MEMORIAL HOMES HAS NO RESIDENTIAL ADDRESSES ON IT FOR
LONGTIME COMMUNITY MEMBERS IN THE WESTERN CONDITION.
THIS MIGHT FEEL A BIT LIKE DEJA VU.
AS A MATTER OF FACT, IF YOU OPEN UP GOOGLE MAPS THE STREET
IN QUESTION BETWEEN POST AND GEARY JUST OUR FILLMORE IS
ALREADY LABELED AS BOSWELL STREET.
>> IN 2008 THEN DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR ZA ROSS MIRKARIMI
INTRODUCED A RESOLUTION OF INTENTION TO RENAME THE STREET.
RESOLUTION OF INTENTION KICKS OFF THE STREET RENAMING PROCESS
AND ARE MEANT TO BE FOLLOWED BY RESOLUTIONS THAT DIRECT PUBLIC
WORKS TO UPDATE OFFICIAL MAPS UNLESS OF HAPPEN TO TO PUT UP
SIGNS WITH THE NEW NAME. HOWEVER IN A ODD SITUATION OF
THE TWILIGHT ZONE THE SIGNS WENT UP BEFORE THE SECOND
RESOLUTION CAME TO BE AND AVERY WAS SIGNED AS BOSWELL FOR OVER
17 YEARS UNTIL EARLIER THIS YEAR WHEN DEPARTMENT STAFF
NOTED THE DISCREPANCY AND QUIETLY REPLACED THE
BOSWELL SIGNS WITH THE AVERY SIGNS.
THIS WAS DIFFICULT FOR THE JONES MEMORIAL COMMUNITY WHO
NOT ONLY RELIED ON THE BOSWELL NAME FOR NAVIGATION TO THEIR
CHURCH AND ADJACENT SENIOR HOMES BUT SAW THE STREET NAME
AS AN INDELIBLE HONOR FOR THEIR LONGTIME LEADER WHO TOUCHED TOO
MANY LIVES ACROSS THE DECADES. I'M BRINGING FORTH THIS
RESOLUTION TO ONCE AND FOR ALL MAKE SURE THE SIGNS NEVER COME
DOWN AND PERMANENTLY ENSHRINE REVEREND BOSWELL'S NAME ON OUR
CITY MAPS AND DOCUMENTS. >> THANK YOU REVEREND SADIE
STONE AND THE REST OF THE JONES MEMORIAL UNITED METHODIST
CHURCH COMMUNITY FOR BRINGING THIS TO OUR ATTENTION.
THANKS AS WELL TO JOHN MAHMUD MALAMUTE FROM THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE. JASON WANG AND IAN IAN
SCHNEIDER FROM PUBLIC WORKS AND CHADWICK LEE FROM OUR STAFF
MTA FOR HELPING OUR OFFICE PIECE ALL OF THIS VERY BIZARRE
STORY TOGETHER. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE AUGUST 2ND THROUGH
AUGUST 8TH 2026 AS NATIONAL HEALTH CENTER WEEK IN SAN
FRANCISCO FORMED IN 1982, THE SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY
COMMUNITY CLINIC CONSORTIUM IS A BRILLIANT EXAMPLE OF THE
COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTER LEGACY BORN FROM THE CIVIL RIGHTS
MOVEMENT OF THE 1960S. THESE CENTERS SEEK TO SERVE THE
UNDERSERVED AT A COST THEY CAN AFFORD.
TODAY THE CLINIC CONSORTIUM IS COMPOSED OF 12 MEMBER CLINICS
THAT TAILOR THEIR SERVICES TO MEET THE UNIQUE NEEDS OF THE
COMMUNITIES IN WHICH THEY ARE LOCATED.
EACH IS ROOTED IN AND SHAPED BY THE COMMUNITY IT SERVES.
OFFERING CARE THAT REFLECTS THE LANGUAGES, CULTURES AND LIVED
REALITIES OF THEIR PATIENTS. SAN FRANCISCO'S COMMUNITY
HEALTH CENTERS HAVE DELIVERED CULTURALLY APPROPRIATE CARE
AND IMPROVED LINGUISTIC ACCESS TO MORE THAN 10% OF THE CITY'S
POPULATION. FOR THEIR PATIENTS THESE
CENTERS ARE OFTEN OR THE ONLY ACCESS TO PRIMARY CARE.
THIS RESOLUTION IS OUR ACKNOWLEDGMENT AND THANKS TO
SAN FRANCISCO'S COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTERS FOR THEIR WORK
DELIVERING INDIVIDUALIZED DIGNIFIED MEDICAL CARE TO THOSE
WHO WOULD OTHERWISE GO WITHOUT AND FOR IF WE'RE DOING SO EVEN
AS THE LANDSCAPE GROWS MORE DIFFICULT EACH YEAR.
I WANT TO THANK DINA ALLEN OF THE SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY
CLINIC CONSORTIUM FOR HER PARTNERSHIP IN BRINGING THIS
RESOLUTION FORWARD. WE'VE WORKED WITH THEM OVER THE
PAST TWO YEARS TO RECOGNIZE NATIONAL HEALTH CENTER WEEK
IN SAN FRANCISCO. I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUES,
SUPERVISORS CHAN AND CHEN FOR THEIR CO-SPONSORSHIP.
AND I WANT TO THANK YOU DAVE SCULLY IN MY OFFICE FOR HER
WORK ON THE RESOLUTION AND THE REST I WILL SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT SINGH. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. >> THANK YOU.
IT WAS UNCLEAR TO ME THAT WE RESCINDED THE VOTE FOR ITEM
NOTE 39 IS NOT CLEAR TO ME WHY WE RESCIND THE VOTE WHEN WE'RE
ALREADY PASSED ITEM 41. AND SO I NEED TO RESCIND THAT
ITEM 39 VOTE ONCE MORE BUT UNDERSTAND EXACTLY WHAT
HAPPENED ON ITEM 13 WE CAN. >> ANY MEMBER CAN ASK TO
RESCIND THE VOTE ON ANY ITEM OF COMPLAINT.
>> BUT IT WAS NOT CLEAR TO ME THAT WE WERE WE SENDING THAT IT
WAS NOT CLEAR TO ME WHY WE WERE RESCINDING THE VOTE OF ITEM 39
WHEN WE WILL PASS IT. >> I WISH SOMEONE TO HAVE
EXPLAINED WHY WE WERE RESENDING THE VOTE.
>> BUT I WOULD LIKE TO WE SEND THE BILL THERE IS A MOTION TO
RESCIND IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY FIELDER AND WE CAN
TAKE THAT MOTION WITHOUT OBJECTION.
>> I LOVE VOTING ON THIS ITEM MADAM CLERK.
>> MR. WEAVER. YES?
I'D LIKE TO READ THE ITEM PLEASE READ THIS VERY QUICKLY.
>> A SHORT TITLE THIS IS BUT BEFORE WE DO SO HOW WE
UNDERSTAND TO THOUGH WHO WAS IT THAT I ASSUMED A SUPERVISOR
CHEN MAKE THE MOTION TO RESCIND A VOTE AND IT WAS SECOND BY
SUPERVISOR FIELDER WALTON. WHY IS IT THAT WE HAVE TO
RESEND THE VOTE A SO FINALLY HOLD ON HOLD ON.
WAIT A MINUTE. I'M SUPPOSED TO RUN THIS
MEETING. I WILL JUST READ THE TIMES WAS
NOT CLEAR THROUGH THE PRESIDENT TO SUPERVISOR CHEN I COULD HAVE
SLOWED THINGS DOWN AND READ THIS TITLE SO THAT EVERYONE
KNEW WE WERE ON A NEW ITEM NUMBER ONE.
AND SO THIS IS AN ORDINANCE THAT AMENDS THE PLANNING
ADMINISTRATIVE BUILDING CODES INCLUSIONARY HOUSING PROGRAM
UPDATES AND REDUCTIONS AND THE DEVELOPMENT IMPACT FEE
REDUCTIONS. >> THANK YOU.
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 39.
I GUESS THIS WOULD BE THE MOMENT FOR THE SUPERVISOR TO
INDICATE WHY SHE WOULD HAVE LIKED THE ITEM TO BE RESCINDED
IN THE FIRST PLACE. >> YES PLEASE.
>> IF SHE CHOOSES A SUPERVISOR CHANCE TO ANSWER.
>> BUT I WOULD I DON'T OF COURSE I LOVE TO ANSWER THEM.
I AGAIN I THINK I SAID IT I WOULD LOVE TO EVENTS BOTH ON
THE HOUSING TRUST FUND AND ALSO CONTINUE TO BE KEEPING OUR CITY
AFFORDABLE TO SUPPORT OUR INCLUSIONARY RATE.
SO WITH THAT I ALSO SAID PUBLICLY THAT I AM NOT
SUPPORTING THE LEGISLATION BECAUSE WE ARE FORCING TO
CHOOSE ONE OR THE OTHER BUT NOT BOTH.
>> BUT I DID SAY THAT I SUPPORT SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S AMENDMENT
SO WHAT THAT I INITIALLY I WAS CONFUSED AND SO I VOTED BUT I'M
VOTING IN SUPPORT OF SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S AMENDMENT BUT OVERALL
AS THE LEGISLATION EVEN WENT THE AMENDMENT THAT WAS ADOPTED
AND I'M STILL ON NOTE TO THE ENTIRE LEGISLATION BECAUSE I
BELIEVE THAT WE SHOULD DO BOTH TOGETHER.
>> THANK YOU. I JUST WOULD HAVE WISH THAT WAS
AND THE ANYWAYS DONE TONIGHT ITEMS BEFORE IN A TIMELY
FASHION BUT THANK YOU I APPRECIATE COLLEAGUES ALLOWING
ME TO RESENT THE VOTE AFTER THE VOTE WAS RESCINDED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ITEM 39 THIS IS ON THE
ORDINANCE ON FIRST READING AS AMENDED FOR ITEM 39 SUPERVISOR
SAUTER SAUTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR
WALTON WILSON NO SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN
I CHAN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR DORSEY
DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I AND SUPERVISOR
MILL GA MELGAR I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO NOSE WITH
SUPERVISORS WILSON AND CHEN VOTING NO AND THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING AS AMENDED MADAM CLERK I THINK
THAT TAKES US TO PUBLIC GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT THAT'S CORRECT.
>> LET'S DO THAT AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES GENERAL
PUBLIC COMMENT IN PERSON SPEAKERS WILL BE PRIORITIZED SO
PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER ONCE
THE IN-PERSON SPEAKERS LINE IS EXHAUSTED WE'LL MOVE TO THE
REMOTE SPEAKERS. IF YOU ANTICIPATE PROVIDING
REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT, THE TELEPHONE NUMBER AND MEETING ID
IS PUBLISHED ON THE AGENDA AND STREAMING ON YOUR SCREEN.
I BELIEVE IT IS BEST TO CALL IN EARLY AS A REMINDER AS OF
GOTV IS NOT IN SYNC WITH THIS MEETING IT'S DELAYED BY A FEW
SECONDS SO PLEASE PAY ATTENTION TO THE PHONE PROMPT AND TURN
DOWN YOUR TELEVISION GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT YOU MAY SPEAK TO
THE JUNE 9TH 2026 BOARD MEETING MINUTES AS PRESENTED AND THE
ITEMS 46 AND 47 UNDER THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE CALENDAR PLEASE NOTE THAT THE BUDGET ITEMS HAVE
ALREADY BEEN PUBLICLY COMMENTED IN COMMITTEE AND ARE NOT
ELIGIBLE FOR COMMENT TODAY. OTHER GENERAL MATTERS THAT ARE
NOT ON TODAY'S AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT
MATTER JURISDICTION AND TO THAT END JUST NOTE THAT
SELF-EXPRESSION THAT CONTAINS PERSONAL ATTACKS, HARASSMENT OR
DISCRIMINATORY REMARKS DIRECTED AT ANY CITY EMPLOYEE OR BOARD
MEMBER ARE STRICTLY OUTSIDE OF THE SCOPE AND FAILURE TO
REDIRECT YOUR COMMENTS WILL RESULTS IN A TRANSITION TO THE
NEXT SPEAKER. SO WELCOME TO OUR FIRST SPEAKER
WHO IS IN THE CHAMBER. WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES. >> WELCOME.
GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS AMELIA, RESIDENT OF
DISTRICT NINE. I WANT TO THANK EVERYBODY FOR
THE OPPORTUNITY OF SERVING ON THE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH COUNCIL
BUT TO HERE TODAY I'M HERE SPEAKING ONLY AS AN INDIVIDUAL.
>> I'VE BEEN IMPRESSED BY THIS GREATER ADMINISTRATION'S
ABILITY TO CAREFULLY INTEGRATE THE CITY STREET TEAMS DESPITE
THE GROWING PAINS I CAN SEE THE VISION AS CAN MANY OF MY
COLLEAGUES AT THIS MOMENT OF OUR GROWTH IN OUR 24 HOUR
CRISIS CONTINUUM OF CARE. HOWEVER, IN THE NEXT FEW WEEKS
WE ARE FACING THE QUIET REMOVAL OF THE PEER COUNSELORS FROM THE
STREET CRISIS RESPONSE TEAM. THE LOSS OF THE PEER
COUNSELORS, INSTITUTIONAL KNOWLEDGE AND FIELD EXPERTISE
DURING 911 BEHAVIORAL CRISES IS AN OVERSIGHT ON OUR STREET
RESPONSE AND WE CANNOT AFFORD IT.
IN AN ANALYSIS PUBLISHED BY SAN JOSE STATE UNIVERSITY REGARDING
OUR STREET CRISIS TEAM RESEARCHERS IDENTIFIED A QUOTE
DISCONNECT BETWEEN DECISION MAKERS UNDERSTANDING OF THE
WORK AND TEAM MEMBERS EXPERIENCE OF THE WORK THEY
SHOW HOW THIS LEADS TO BURNOUT AND MORAL INJURY IN OUR FIRST
RESPONDERS WHICH QUOTE IMPEDES THEIR ABILITY TO SERVE CLIENTS
AND CAN CREATE STRUCTURAL CHANGES FROM MUNICIPALITIES.
IN RESPONSE TO THE NOW CONFIRMED RUMORS, I HAVE
ALREADY PRESENTED THE VALUE ASSESSMENTS TO BOTH THE HEALTH
COMMISSION AND THE FIRE COMMISSION.
I HAVE FULL FAITH THAT THE ACTORS IN THIS ROOM CAN REVERSE
THIS DECISION AS IT DIDN'T SEEM TO BE MADE ON BUDGETARY
CONCERNS. BUT LET'S LOOK FORWARD.
IF WE WANT OUR PEER COUNSELORS TO GRADUATE TO PERMANENT CIVIL
SERVICE POSITIONS I HAVE A LONG TERM PLAN AND I ASK FOR THE
BOARD'S SUPPORT WHEN IT REACHES WHEN IT REACHES YOU IN THE
INTERIM AS WE REPAIR THIS BLUNDER.
I HAVE A PLAN TO STANDARDIZE TRAINING, ACCOUNTABILITY AND I
HAVE A PLAN TO OPERATIONALIZE EFFICIENCY.
>> KEEPING PEERS IS THE RESPONSIBLE DECISION TO OUR
FIRST RESPONDERS AND TO OUR CITY OUR OFFICERS, PARAMEDICS,
EMTS, PURE COUNSELORS WOULD MUCH RATHER BE OUT THERE
RUNNING CALLS AND SERVING SAN FRANCISCANS THAN IN HERE
PROVING THEIR WORTH OR THEIR EFFICIENCY.
WITH WORD GETTING OUT OVER THE WEEKEND, I HAVE ALREADY GOTTEN
FIELD REPORTS FROM OUR POLICE OFFICERS CALLING THIS WHAT IT
IS A MISTAKE. TOMORROW I WILL BE WARNING THE
POLICE COMMISSION LET'S PLEASE REPAIR THIS NOW WHEN WE HAVE
THE CHANCE. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
>> GOOD EVENING, PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS JULIE SU AND I SPEAK TODAY ON BEHALF OF SONA SAVE
OUR NATIONAL ARCHIVE. I'M HERE WITH BIG SISTER JENNY
LU WHO WILL SPEAK AFTER ME. >> I SPEAK IN GREAT SUPPORT OF
SUPERVISOR CHAN'S RESOLUTION ITEM NUMBER 47 TO HALT THE
CLOSURE OF THE NATIONAL ARCHIVES AND RECORDS
ADMINISTRATION AT SAN FRANCISCO LOCATED IN SAN BRUNO.
20 YEARS AGO WE HAD THIS FIGHT BUT 20 YEARS AGO THERE WAS
PUBLIC TESTIMONY THIS ADMINISTRATION, THIS WHITE
HOUSE ADMINISTRATION HAS FAILED TO FOLLOW THE ADMINISTRATIVE
PROCEDURE ACT GIVING PUBLIC NOTICE, TAKING PUBLIC TESTIMONY
. THIS IS OUR COLLECTIVE HISTORY.
IT'S NOT ONLY OUR STATE'S HISTORY.
IT IS OUR NATION'S HISTORY. AND IF ANY ONE OF YOU THINK
THAT YOU HAVEN'T BEEN TOUCHED BY THE NATIONAL ARCHIVES, I ASK
YOU TO THINK AGAIN. IT CONTAINS NATIVE AMERICAN
ARTIFACTS AND DOCUMENTS AS WELL AS CHINESE-AMERICAN EXCLUSION
ACT DOCUMENTS JAPANESE-AMERICAN RELOCATION FOR THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY. THE PORT CHICAGO DOCUMENTS
JEWISH HISTORY DOCUMENTS FOR RUSSIAN IMMIGRANTS WHO WENT
THROUGH ANGEL ISLAND. >> IT'S NOT A SURPRISE THAT
THERE ARE ATTEMPTS TO ERASE HISTORY.
I KNOW THAT THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS TAKEN GREAT
PAINS TO RIGHT THE WRONGS OF OUR HISTORY.
WITHOUT THIS DOCUMENTATION WE CANNOT HAVE THIS PARTICULAR
ATTENTION TO RIGHTING THE WRONGS OF HISTORY.
AND THIS IS NOT JUST GOVERNMENTAL ACADEMIC HISTORY.
THIS THIS IS ALSO OUR FAMILY HISTORY AND THE PEOPLE WHO LIVE
HERE. IT WAS OUR ANCESTORS WHO
CREATED THIS HISTORY. IT IS A MEANS FOR US TO UNITE
FAMILIES TO HAVE SOME STRENGTH IN OUR FAMILIES KNOWING OUR
HISTORY. AS WE TALK ABOUT EDUCATION
AND MAKING SURE THAT OUR STUDENTS UNDERSTAND OUR
HISTORY, THIS IS AN ARCHIVE AND RECORDS HISTORY THAT IS
RIGHT IN OUR BACKYARD. IT IS ONE OF THE FEW NATIONAL
ARCHIVES THAT ALSO HAS A RESEARCH CENTER WITH VERY
VALUED STAFF WHO CAN LEAD PEOPLE TO DOCUMENT IT.
SO I URGE YOU NOT ONLY TO SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION BUT
ALSO TO BE CO-SPONSOR TO SEND A VERY STRONG MESSAGE THAT WE
WILL NOT LET OUR HISTORY BE ERASED.
THANK YOU. AND NOW TO BIG SISTER JENNY
LOU. >> THANK YOU COMMISSIONER SU
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
>> SHE CALLS ME BIG SISTER BECAUSE I HAVE BEEN WORKING ON
THIS FOR 25 YEARS. >> THEY WERE GOING TO CLOSE ALL
THE REGIONAL ARCHIVES THROUGHOUT THE NATION.
BUT WE WORKED WITH TOM LANTOS TO STOP THAT AND THEN THEY WERE
GOING TO DESTROY ALIEN FILES. >> ALL THE NATIONS ALIEN PARTS
ARE NOT JUST ASIAN FILES. >> THOSE ARE OVER THREE
QUARTERS OF 1,000,000 CUBIC FEET OF FILES AND OUR PACIFIC
REGION THAT COVERS HAS THE LARGEST COLLECTION OF ALIEN
FILES FROM PORT OF HAWAII ALL THE WAY UP THE WEST COAST.
PEOPLE FROM ALL OVER THE WORLD COME TO LOOK AT THESE
IMMIGRATION FILES. AND WE WERE THE ONLY REGION
THAT DEMANDED THAT THEY STAY IN SAN BRUNO.
>> WE ARE THE ORIGIN OF THESE FILES.
THE PEOPLE THAT USE THEM ARE FROM OUR REGION.
THEY ARE OUR HISTORY. AND LIKE JULIE SAID, IT CAN BE
RUSSIAN JEWS, IT CAN BE EASTERN EUROPE, EUROPEAN US.
IT WILL BE LARGELY THE PEOPLE THAT WERE EXCLUDED FIRST FROM
COMING TO THIS COUNTRY. >> AND IN OUR PARTICULAR
CHINESE FILES WE HAVE COACHING DOCUMENTS THAT DETAILED VILLAGE
MAPS OF WHICH PEOPLE FROM MY GENERATION IF THEY WISH TO GO
BACK TO THEIR ANCESTRAL VILLAGES AND FIND THE HOME
WHERE THE ANCESTRAL SHRINE IS THEIR ONLY CHANCE IS MAYBE TOOK
A LOOK AT THESE COACHING DOCUMENTS AND THESE DETAILED
MAPS. >> SO PLEASE GIVE YOUR
STRONGEST SUPPORT. >> WE LOSE THIS.
THEY WILL NEVER COME BACK. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
SUPERVISORS OF SEVEN CISCO. MY NAME IS MICHELLE LAO.
I AM THE PRESIDENT OF THE AMERICAN ALLIANCE OF
ACUPUNCTURE. AND THEN I HAVE BEEN PRACTICING
OVER 45 YEARS. >> TODAY I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT
IT TO THE WE JUST SURPRISED THE CHAIR MENTIONED THE BILL H.R.
167. >> THAT'S FOR 70 MILLION OF THE
ELDERLY THAT WHO CAN BE COVERED BY ACUPUNCTURE.
>> WHICH DISPUTES ARE THE PATHS ABOUT A YEAR AGO WITH THE H.R.
SIX, ACUPUNCTURE IS ALREADY INCLUDING IN THE MEDICARE
SYSTEM. AND AFTER 27 YEARS OF ADVOCACY
AND EFFORT. >> SO LUCKILY WE CAN SERVE NOW
70 MILLION OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE ELDERLY BUT
UNFORTUNATELY WE STILL NEED TO CONTINUE TO WORK.
I REMOVED THE HARDER I'M SORRY. HOW DID YOU GET THE LICENSED
ACUPUNCTURE QUALIFIED ACUPUNCTURE INTO THE PROVIDER
WHICH WE HAVE BEEN DONE TREMENDOUSLY TO OVER THE WHOLE
COUNTRY. >> AND THIS HAS JULY 18TH.
WE WELCOME ALL FOR YOU'LL COME TO JOIN OUR COMMUNITY
AND PATIENT AND THE PROFESSION WE HAVE A YUAN IN THE CHINATOWN
AND THAT WE HAVE A FULL SUPPORT FROM THE COMMUNITY.
AND HOPEFULLY WE CAN SEE THIS BILL CAN PASS HOPEFULLY NEXT
YEAR. SO WE GO TO THE CONGRESS THE F
MONTH TO SERVE THE AMERICAN ALLIES ACUPUNCTURE TO SERVE THE
CONGRESS MEMBER AND THEIR STAFF .
AND THIS YEAR THE UNDERSTAND HOW IMPORTANT THAT FOR TO HAVE
THE ASSETS OF OUR 70 MILLION THE ELDERLY CAN HAVE
ACUPUNCTURE PRETTY SOON AFTER BILLS ALREADY PASS ACUPUNCTURE
IS ALREADY INCLUDED. HOPEFULLY WE CAN GET YOUR GRACE
SUPPORT. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HI, MY NAME IS ELIZABETH
AARON. TODAY IS THE FIRST TIME I FELT
THE NEED TO ATTEND A MEETING ON THE SAN FRANCISCO CITY
SUPERVISORS IN PERSON LAST WEEK I WAS SHOCKED TO FIND THAT
FINAL APPROVAL HAD BEEN GIVEN TO A 23 FLOOR BUILDING AT THE
END OF MY STREET I RECEIVED NO NOTICE OF THIS PROJECT EITHER
AT MY HOME OR POSTED ON THE SITE WHICH I PASS ALMOST DAILY.
WHILE THERE ARE MANY ISSUES WITH THIS PROJECT TODAY I WOULD
LIKE TO HIGHLIGHT ONE ONGOING ISSUE I HAVE BEYOND THE LACK OF
PUBLIC NOTICE. >> MY ISSUE IS THE CONTINUED
PERPETUATION OF THE IDEA THAT RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO
ESPECIALLY THOSE WHO LIVE IN MY NEIGHBORHOOD SHOULD NOT HAVE
CARS. I AM AN ATTORNEY AND HAVE
WORKED IN LAND USE PLANNING SO I UNDERSTAND THE THEORIES UPON
WHICH THIS IDEA ORIGINATED. BUT I ALSO KNOW THAT IN REALITY
NO MATTER HOW TRANSIT FRIENDLY A NEIGHBORHOOD IS, PEOPLE WHO
BUY MARKET RATE HOMES WILL HAVE CARS.
I HAVE LIVED ON CLINTON PARK FOR MORE THAN 20 YEARS WHERE I
HAVE HAD TO DEAL WITH EVER INCREASING PRESSURE AND STRESS
CAUSED BY LOSS OF PARKING DUE TO ILL CONCEIVED BIKE PATHS NEW
INTERSECTION RED ZONES WHICH ARE CONSTANTLY USED BY LYFT
DRIVERS AND PROVIDE NO SAFETY PROTECTIONS.
AND A COMPLETE LACK OF ENFORCEMENT OF TRAFFIC LAWS
ADDING A 200 PLUS UNIT BUILDING WITH ONLY 62 PARKING SPACES IS
DELUSIONAL AND DANGEROUS. PEOPLE ARE ALREADY CONSTANTLY
FRUSTRATED BY THE MAZE THAT HAS BEEN CAUSED BY THE CLOSURE OF
RIGHT AND LEFT TURNS AND MANY ARE JUST BREAKING THE LAW.
ADD TO THAT THE FACT THAT SOMETIMES IT TAKES UP TO 40
MINUTES TO FIND A PARKING SPACE AND YOU HAVE A DANGEROUS
SITUATION FOR DRIVERS, BIKERS AND PEDESTRIANS LIKE MYSELF.
THANK YOU FOR LISTENING TO MY COMMENTS.
>> PERHAPS YOU CAN GIVE THEM CONSIDERATION IN FURTHER
APPLICATIONS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
MA'AM, WE'RE GOING TO OBTAIN YOUR ADDRESS AND WE'LL LET YOU
KNOW MORE INFORMATION ON THAT ADDRESS AND THAT PROJECT BEFORE
THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS
OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT? OTHERWISE THIS WILL BE OUR LAST
IN-PERSON SPEAKER. WELCOME SIR.
>> BOARD OF SUPERVISOR AND MAYOR OFFERS A SENSE OF
SCOPE. >> THE TITLE OF THIS SPEECH IS
AGENT OF CHANGE IN A YEAR 1999. I HOOKED UP A FRIEND DAVID TAM
FROM FRANCISCO AND NANCY FROM LOS ANGELES FOR RELATIONSHIP
AND A POSSIBLE MARRIAGE AFTER GETTING HOLD OF VIOLENCE EMAIL.
DAVIS SAT IN FRONT OF A COMPUTER TO COMPOSE A LETTER.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT TO SAY, HE EXCLAIMED TO HIS YOUNGER SISTER
AMY TRAIN. >> DON'T KNOW WHAT TO SAY.
>> WHAT AN INTERESTING PROPOSITION.
EXPLORE THIS MESSAGE IN CONTEXT FOR TWO AND A HALF DECADE TO
TEARS DOWN PROVIDE TWO TYPES OF MESSAGE.
MINDSET AND PSYCHOLOGY ACCORDING TO WEBSTER'S
DICTIONARY. MINDSET MEANS BEHAVIOR,
ATTITUDE AND VIEWPOINT. >> PSYCHOLOGY HAS A DUTY OF
CARE TO BELIEF SYSTEM MICRO ACTIONS AND ROUTINE.
ACCORDING TO ROBERT DAVID, CHARACTER MEANS CARVING.
>> IT DRIVES DEEP AND NOVEMBER 2018.
I WILL ALWAYS REMEMBER THE DAY I CALL MY FRIEND TYLER CHANG.
DEANNA TEXTED ME FROM THAILAND .
>> LET'S GO TO THAILAND, DEREK. >> HE REPLIED EXHAUSTINGLY.
>> YOU SPENT SEVEN MONTHS HER PHONE NUMBER ANOTHER YEAR JUST
TO TEXT HER. >> YOU DON'T EVEN KNOW WHERE
SHE LIVES. HOW ARE YOU EXPECTED TO MARRY
HER? >> I WAS COMPLETELY DUMBFOUNDED
. >> TWO HOURS LATER FOR MR.
CHINATOWN OF SAN FRANCISCO CALL ME.
SHE STILL WENT ON HER LEFT. DEREK.
I'M GOING TO GO TO HONG KONG TO COMPETE FOR MISS CHINESE
INTERNATIONAL. I NEED YOUR HELP.
SHE CAME OUT WITH THE TITLE OF MOST POPULAR OF MISS CHINESE TO
THE NATIONAL PERSON ADVISOR. >> PEOPLE DO NOT WRITE BOOKS
BECAUSE THEY DON'T FEEL LIKE THEY'LL BE READ AND PEOPLE
DON'T GO INTO POLITICS BECAUSE THEY DON'T FEEL LIKE THEY COULD
MAKE A DIFFERENCE. I'M HERE TO MAKE A DIFFERENCE
IN POLITICS BECAUSE I FEEL LIKE I COULD DO IT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME OTTO DUFFY. >> DUFFY.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT TO SAY EXACTLY.
AS USUAL, MY DAD WAS A MY DAD WAS AN ALCOHOLIC AND AS HE GOT
OLDER HE AND ONE OF HIS MEETINGS HE POINTED OUT THE
CRITICAL THINGS THAT THAT YOU NEED TO DO IF YOU'RE AN
ALCOHOLIC. AS YOU GET OLDER, IF YOU WANT
TO BECOME AN OLD ALCOHOLIC AND THERE WERE ONLY TWO THINGS
ONE YOU HAVE TO KEEP FROM DRINKING AND TWO YOU HAVE TO
KEEP BREATHING. >> THANK YOU, OTTO DUFFY FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. >> THE REST THE REST OF WHAT
HAPPENED HERE AT THIS MEETING I HAVE NO I AM I HAD TO SIGN 100
PAGE BECAUSE I SO MANY PEOPLE SUBSIDIZE MY HOUSING.
THERE'S SO MANY PEOPLE HAVE INVOLVED IN IT.
I SIGNED A 100 PAGE LEASE, 100 PAGES.
>> IT'S GOT ALL KINDS OF THINGS IN IT.
YOU KNOW, I WENT TO A, YOU KNOW, PRE LAW PERSON TO ASK
THEM ABOUT IT AND THEY SAID YOU HAVE NO CHOICE IF YOU WANT TO
LIVE HERE YOU HAVE TO SIGN A LEASE AND IF I DON'T LIVE THERE
I'M GOING TO DIE SO I HAVE TO SIGN THE LEASE.
BUT THEY ALSO POINTED OUT THAT LIKE HALF OF IT HALF OF IT IS
PRETTY MUCH UNENFORCEABLE. >> SO I DON'T KNOW.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
SEEING NO OTHER SPEAKERS IN PERSON, WE'LL GO TO THE
REMOTE CALLERS. I BELIEVE WE HAVE TO I'LL JUST
REMIND THE CALLERS THAT IF YOU IF YOU PLEASE LISTEN TO THE
SYSTEM WHEN IT SAYS YOU HAVE BEEN UNMUTED, THAT IS YOUR CUE
TO BEGIN SPEAKING AND THAT THERE IS NOTHING IN STATE LAW
THAT WILL CONFER ANY PRIVILEGE OR PROTECTION FOR EXPRESSION
THAT CONSTITUTES DISCRIMINATORY OR HARASSING REMARKS.
WE WILL MOVE TO THE NEXT SPEAKER AFTER A QUICK REDIRECT
. >> ALL RIGHT.
LET'S BRING IN OUR FIRST CALLER PLEASE WELCOME.
>> SPEAKER, ARE YOU THERE? >> WELL, HELLO.
I'M SORRY. >> HI.
AND CAN PLAY WITH THE LEAGUE OF WOMEN VOTERS CISCO, I'M HERE
TODAY TO URGE YOU TO JOIN THE OPEN NINE SEAT ON THE SUNSHINE
OR TASK FORCE. >> THE TASK FORCE HASN'T BEEN
ABLE TO MEET SINCE THE BEGINNING OF JULY AND WILL BE
UNABLE TO MEET UNTIL THESE SEATS ARE FILLED.
THE SUNSHINE AREN'T AS TOSSERS IT'S LEARNED A FEW WAYS PEOPLE
HAVE THE WHOLE CHAPTER ON GOVERNMENT ACCOUNTABLE TO
TRANSPARENCY. ALL PEOPLE CAN ASK FOR
GOVERNMENT RECORDS FOR ALL KINDS OF REASONS.
A RESIDENT WANTS TO KNOW WHO A GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL MET WITH
SARCASM CIVIL JOURNALIST IS CHECKING WHETHER A CONTRACT WAS
AWARDED FAIRLY. SOMEONE WANTS TO KNOW WHY
PROJECT IN THEIR NEIGHBORHOOD GOT THE GREEN LIGHT BUT
SOMETIMES WHEN A PERSON ASKS FOR GOVERNMENT RECORDS SOMEONE
IN GOVERNMENT DRIVES OR THEATER SAYS NO, THE PERSON CAN BRING
THEIR PROBLEMS GETTING THE PUBLIC RECORDS TO THE SUNSHINE
ORDINANCE TASK FORCE WHICH REVIEWS A COMPLAINT AND CAN
TELL THE GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL OR DEPARTMENT YOU'RE IN THE WRONG
CABINET OVER AND THEY'LL BE SERVED WITH THE STATUTE BILL
PUBLIC PRESS REPORTED LAST WEEK THE SUNSHINE ORDINANCE TASK
FORCE AND THE PUBLIC'S RIGHT TO KNOW IS IN LIMBO.
>> WHILE THESE ESSENTIAL APPOINTMENTS ARE INEXPLICABLY
AND UNNECESSARILY DELAYED EVERY DAY AND SEATS GO UNFILLED IS A
WEAK GOVERNMENT GETS TO OPERATE IN THE DARK.
>> THE LEAGUE OF WOMEN VOTERS URGES YOU TO PUT THE SUNSHINE
ON TASK FORCE MEMBER APPOINTMENTS ON THE AGENDA FOR
YOUR NEXT MEETING OF THE RULES COMMITTEE WITHOUT FURTHER
DELAY. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> LET'S WELCOME THE NEXT
ANONYMOUS CALLER MAYBE WILL WANT TO KEEP UP WE CAN HEAR YOU
CAN YOU PLEASE SPEAK A LITTLE SLOWER?
>> WE CANNOT UNDERSTAND WHICH ISSUE PEOPLE SPEAK.
ALL RIGHT CALLER IF YOU'VE LEFT THE LINE WE WILL MOVE ON TO THE
NEXT CALLER. OKAY, TEAM IN THE BACK.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER CALLERS? >> THERE ARE NO MORE CALLERS
IN HUMAN. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT, PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 46 AND 47 TOGETHER YES.
>> ITEMS 46 AND 47. THESE ITEMS WERE INTRODUCED FOR
ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST READING TODAY ANY MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST READING TO GO TO COMMITTEE PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON THESE ITEMS ON ITEMS 46 AND 47 SUPERVISOR SAUDER SORTER
EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD TWO
EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE
AGENDA ITEMS THEIR AGENDA REPORT COULD YOU PLEASE READ
THE IN MEMORIAM IS TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED
IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL ON BEHALF OF
SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR THE LATE MR. FAY BEN LEE SUPERVISOR CHEN
EXCUSE ME FOR MR. FAY BEN LEE AND I BELIEVE MADAM CLERK THAT
BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER
BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. THANK YOU MADAM CLERK WE ARE
ADJOURNED